
<TEI.2 id="APB1702">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>04-04-1829</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1922: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1928), 3 vols., Vol 2, pp. 200-205</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Stephen F Austin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Josiah H Bell</document_recipient>
<document_title>Stephen F Austin to Josiah H Bell, 04-04-1829</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Unknown</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Lower Settlement, Texas</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Austin to Josiah H. Bell, April 4, 1829. Pointing out errors in the public attitude toward the ayuntamiento, and explaining its duties. Budget, manuscript translation of the laws, " shyster " lawyers.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes>Compare with this letter Austin to Bell, Mar   17, 1829.    The ayuntamiento's budget
which Austin discusses is in Southwestern Historical Quarterly, XXI, 403-404.
For the duties of a comisario see further an article by the editor in Ibid., 247.
Hosea H. League, second regidor in the ayuntamiento of San Felipe.
The missing words were clipped out with Austin's signature which was on the back
of the same sheet.</barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 200-205</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>08-10-2010</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>


<text id="APB1702T">

<body>
*div1 type="summary"*
*p*Austin to Josiah H. Bell, April 4, 1829. Pointing out errors in the public attitude toward the ayuntamiento, and explaining its duties. Budget, manuscript translation of the laws, " shyster " lawyers.*/p*
*/div1*

*div1 type="body"*

*p**date_mentioned n="04-04-129">April 4 1829*/date_mentioned**/p*
*p**person_mentioned*Mr J. H. Bell*/person_mentioned**/p*

*p*Dr Sir, I have heard with regret and surprise of the numorous
reports and rumors that are in circulation, and fomenting the *person_mentioned*public*/person_mentioned*
mind— When I first heard of them I paid but little attention to
them, for they were so absurd and unfounded that I thought they
would correct themselves— I also felt confident that the good sence
of the *person_mentioned*people */person_mentioned*would point out to them the necessity of harmony and
union, and the justice of at least enquiring into the truth of rumors
before they were received as facts-
It is reported, as I am told, that " the *location_mentioned*colony */location_mentioned*is to be loaded with
Taxes to build a splendid*location_mentioned* court house*/location_mentioned* for the *person_mentioned*lawyers */person_mentioned*to strut in"—
All the answer that is necessary to this rumor is, that it is false*/p*.

*p*The law requires certain duties of the *person_mentioned*Ayumtamiento */person_mentioned*and the
*person_mentioned*members */person_mentioned*can be severely punished if they are not strictly attended
to, and they cannot be discharged without some funds— The *person_mentioned*Ayto*/person_mentioned*
of *date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1828">last year*/date_mentioned* did not comply with their duty in any one particular—
they did nothing that the *person_mentioned*people */person_mentioned*ever heard of, and they were 
therefore popular, but it cost me and *person_mentioned*Williams */person_mentioned*a great deal of labor and
it required all I could do to keep them from being fined severely—
they contracted a debt of upwards of four hundred dollars which
was turned over to this *person_mentioned*Ayto */person_mentioned*to be paid*/p*

*p*It is necessary to have a *person_mentioned*secretary */person_mentioned*who understands both languages
and a Salary of 1000 Dollars was offered to *person_mentioned*Williams*/person_mentioned*- The other
necessary expenses will be two hundred dollars more at least, for
Blank Books, Stationary, fire wood, house rent, *person_mentioned*Indian */person_mentioned*expences;
*location_mentioned*post office*/location_mentioned* account etc these items make $1600—- It is by law the
duty of the *person_mentioned*Ayto */person_mentioned*to provide a safe and secure place to keep the *person_mentioned*public*/person_mentioned*
records in and it is also a duty due to the *person_mentioned*people */person_mentioned*of the *location_mentioned*jurisdiction*/location_mentioned*—
The records are now kept in a *location_mentioned*log cabin*/location_mentioned*, in danger of being distroyed
by fire, and are dayly becoming defaced by wet and exposure and
it was intended to try and build a *location_mentioned*fire proof room*/location_mentioned* of brick merely
large enough for the object, and to put up a *location_mentioned*frame house*/location_mentioned* similar to<barker_pb n="201"/>
the one built by *person_mentioned*Cooper */person_mentioned*which would have cost about three hundred
dollars to serve as a *location_mentioned*court house*/location_mentioned* or *location_mentioned*office */location_mentioned*for the *person_mentioned*Alcalde*/person_mentioned*— The law
requires that there should be a *location_mentioned*jail */location_mentioned*and it was intended to try and
put up a small one— this is the extent of what was contemplated
provided funds could be raised— The plan that was adopted as to
raising funds, was to make an estimate of all the expences, including
every thing, under the supposition that the *location_mentioned*buildings */location_mentioned*would all be
put up, and 4700 dolls was the highest estimate, of this sum 100
would be raised by the ferry and it was calculated that about 1500
could be raised by the tax on *location_mentioned*stores*/location_mentioned*, groceries, *person_mentioned*Lawyers */person_mentioned*and *person_mentioned*doctors*/person_mentioned*,
and out of the sale of town and out lots in this *location_mentioned*place */location_mentioned*making a sum
of 1600 dollars, without calculating anything from fines on 
*person_mentioned*drunkards*/person_mentioned*, a law by the bye which I will insist shall be inforced with the
utmost rigor not because I delight in punishing a *person_mentioned*drunkard */person_mentioned*but
because it is time to stop the confusion and disorder they have 
heretofore produced, agreeably to this calculation there would have been
about $3000 to raise by taxes on property, but it was not intended to
raise this sum all at once— The System that was intended to pursue
was [to] raise enough first to pay off the old debt and to meet the
common current expences; and then to make an exhibit of the same
to the people— to procure the best data that could be obtained as to
the expence of a small *location_mentioned*building */location_mentioned*for the records and another for a
*location_mentioned*court house*/location_mentioned*, or for only one of them, and also for a small *location_mentioned*jail*/location_mentioned*, and
if it was found after making an experiment that the funds could be
raised to build them, it was intended to raise them and not otherwise,
and never to raise them all at once, but gradualfy as they were
needed— and if from the unproductiveness of some of the sources of
revenue that were calculated on, it was found that the tax on 
property would be oppressive, it was intended to lower it and only to
raise as much as was necessary and no more— I did believe that
enough could be raised to defray the common expences and to build
the *location_mentioned*office */location_mentioned*for the records this *date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1829">year */date_mentioned*and the *location_mentioned*jail */location_mentioned*could be built next
year but I am now induced to think nothing can be raised and that
the Municipal Govt must totally stop and be suspended— 
arrangements were made to procure a *person_mentioned*secretary*/person_mentioned*— but they are broken up—
there will be no *person_mentioned*secretary */person_mentioned*and the only way I see of getting along is
for me to do all the writing that has to be done in Spanish— it is a
much heavier burden than is supposed, but it seems that when I
undertook the *location_mentioned*colony */location_mentioned*I inlisted myself for life— I am getting weary
and less patient that I once was, tho I will not " give up the ship 
while I live and the people shall have the use of my time and labor
so long as I can be of use to them in any way <hi rend="italic">except one</hi> I never will
be *person_mentioned*Alcalde */person_mentioned*if I can avoid it for if I ever take the oath required by
that office I will rigidly execute it, and if I do I can hope for noth-<barker_pb n="202"/>
ing but abuse and misrepresentation— the *person_mentioned*people */person_mentioned*are too much 
disposed to lissen to those who have <hi rend="italic">more </hi>to says and <hi rend="italic">less </hi>to loose than
any body in the *location_mentioned*country */location_mentioned*honest *person_mentioned*men */person_mentioned*will become disgusted and will
fly the *location_mentioned*country */location_mentioned*rather than accept of an office—*/p*

*p*Another report is that no petition will be recd unless drawn up by
a *person_mentioned*lawyer*/person_mentioned*— that report is totally false and I cannot but be surprised
that any one should have believed it for one moment— They have
no idea of their rights or of the constitution or they never would
have believed such a rumor— The *person_mentioned*Alcalde */person_mentioned*made a set of Court rules
and posted them up in his *location_mentioned*office */location_mentioned*I never read them untill this day,
and I send you a copy of the articles which I presume gave rise
to the reports— they regulate the number of times that a person may
speak, which is no more than is done in all *location_mentioned*courts*/location_mentioned**/p*

*p*There is a report that the *person_mentioned*Alcalde */person_mentioned*will allow no suits to be brought
before the *person_mentioned*Commisarios */person_mentioned*<hi rend="italic">this is also false</hi> Some have insisted that
he should issue process all over the *location_mentioned*colony */location_mentioned*for all sums and he has
done so I believe in a few instances— for the future he will do so
no more but compel all suits within the *location_mentioned*jurisdiction */location_mentioned*of a *person_mentioned*Commissario*/person_mentioned*
to be brought before that *person_mentioned*officer*/person_mentioned*—the *location_mentioned*jurisdiction */location_mentioned*of a *person_mentioned*commisario */person_mentioned*is
100 Dollars and no more*/p*

*p*Excessive and illegal fees have been allowed to the *person_mentioned*sheriff*/person_mentioned*, but
this *person_mentioned*Alcalde */person_mentioned*followed the example of the last one— I believe that
the fee bill was not published *date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1828">last year*/date_mentioned* because it was feared the
*person_mentioned*sheriff */person_mentioned*would make a clamour, and it appeard that whoever abused
the *person_mentioned*Alcaide */person_mentioned*was lissened to wheither he was right or wrong—
*person_mentioned*Williams */person_mentioned*has translated the fee bill and it was published a few
days ago—*/p*

*p*There appears to be a great prejudice against *person_mentioned*Major Leagues*/person_mentioned* and
the most scurrulous and unjust abuse is heaped upon him—I believe
that all this is unjust and unfounded so far as I can understand or
know of his acts— and I am of opinion that it all originated from
personal animosity and nothing else—*/p*

*p*The ears of the *person_mentioned*people */person_mentioned*have been tickeled and irritated by the cry
of<hi rend="italic"> party party</hi> and <hi rend="italic">corruption </hi>untill they begin to doubt wheither
there is an honest *person_mentioned*man */person_mentioned*in this *location_mentioned*place */location_mentioned*or in the *location_mentioned*world*/location_mentioned*— I believe
that this cry of party and corruption etc is all false, and that it is
gotten up by personal *person_mentioned*enemies */person_mentioned*of *person_mentioned*League */person_mentioned*for the express purpose
of trying to distroy him— I belong to no party and will engage in
no personal animosities but I do say, justice compels me to say that
*person_mentioned*League */person_mentioned*is an injured and persecuted man or I am more deceived than
I ever was before in my life—   he has been challenged and threat-<barker_pb n="203"/>
ened with clubs and death— I know not for what}— It is said the
people will rise and mob him— I cannot understand for what—
he has one fault which has injured him greatly— he is too' 
irritable— his personal *person_mentioned*enemies */person_mentioned*are if possible more so— all is 
combustable matter ready to blaise out at every trifle and thus the best
interests of the *location_mentioned*colony */location_mentioned*are actually sported with by a set of hot
headed *person_mentioned*madmen*/person_mentioned*, let the people frown upon all these inflamitory
beings, alike, and they will all learn to keep their tempers, and not
be wantonly playing with the public tranquility, the character, and
best interests of the *location_mentioned*colony*/location_mentioned*, and let them investigate both sides of
every question, before they condemn or approve—*/p*

*p*As regards the *person_mentioned*Lawyers*/person_mentioned*, they abuse each other-— and charge
each other with unfair practices etc, all this is in the natural order
of things— they do the same in all *location_mentioned*countries*/location_mentioned*, but I have never 
before seen a people who paid any other attention to such quarrels
than to treat them with contempt—in this *location_mentioned*country */location_mentioned*the *person_mentioned*Lawyer */person_mentioned*who
is most active in getting the ears of the *person_mentioned*people*/person_mentioned*, has generally 
succeeded in inlisting their feelings in his favor and in rousing their
inflamitory passions or creating violent prejudices against his 
*person_mentioned*opponent*/person_mentioned*— I totally disapprove of this course in all— It is both
criminal and contemptable in the *person_mentioned*lawyer */person_mentioned*who does it— and displays
a want of common sence in the *person_mentioned*people */person_mentioned*to be operated on by such
means— The *person_mentioned*people */person_mentioned*descend from the lofty dignity of sovereigns,
when they suffer their passions to be inlisted in the disputes and
animosities of a gabling *person_mentioned*lawyer*/person_mentioned*— you wish the *person_mentioned*lawyers */person_mentioned*to be put
down the way to do it is for the *person_mentioned*people */person_mentioned*to curb their contentious
dispositions, and instead of calling on *person_mentioned*lawyers */person_mentioned**person_mentioned*sheriffs */person_mentioned*and *person_mentioned*Alcalde*/person_mentioned*,
call in their *person_mentioned*neighbors */person_mentioned*and settle their disputes by means of 
arbitrations— in this way they will be put down— they fatten on the
dissentions of the *person_mentioned*people*/person_mentioned*, I do believe that a *person_mentioned*Lawyer */person_mentioned*would get
rich by picking to pieces the property of one hundred *person_mentioned*americans*/person_mentioned*,
when he would starve on 20,000 of any other people on earth—*/p*

*p*The truth is the *person_mentioned*people of this *location_mentioned*colony */location_mentioned**/person_mentioned*are better off and might be
happier than any other *person_mentioned*people on *location_mentioned*earth*/location_mentioned**/person_mentioned*—and it is also true that
they are now on the broad road to total ruin—they are destroying
themselves—most of the evils that now exist, or are supposed to
exist have their origin with the people themselves—they are too
much disposed to run into extreems, at one time withholding all
confidence, and suspecting or doubting every thing, and opening their
ears to idle rumors, and at another shewing the most perfect 
indifference as to who are elected to manage their affairs, or wheither the
laws are executed or not—at the last election for *person_mentioned*Alcalde */person_mentioned*but few
votes were taken in any part of the *location_mentioned*Colony*/location_mentioned*, and part of those that
were given in, were worse than thrown away— At the late *person_mentioned*Militia*/person_mentioned*
election about 150 votes were taken out of upwards of five hun-<barker_pb n="204"/>
dred— in the *person_mentioned*3d company */person_mentioned*out of about 140 *person_mentioned*men */person_mentioned*44 votes were taken,
in the 4th company out of 106 *person_mentioned*men */person_mentioned*14 voles were taken—it was
considered a matter of no consequence altho, those who are now
elected are to be commissioned by the *person_mentioned*Governor */person_mentioned*and unless they 
resign or are broke are *person_mentioned*officers */person_mentioned*for life and rise by regular promotion
as vacancies occur to the highest rank in the *person_mentioned*Regiment*/person_mentioned*— It is 
considered a matter of no importance to elect an *person_mentioned*Alcalde */person_mentioned*to administer
justice, an *person_mentioned*Ayuntamiento */person_mentioned*to manage our civil matters, and *person_mentioned*officers*/person_mentioned*
to lead us into battle—notices for elections are treated with 
indifference and contempt, and in this way the best and dearest interests
of the *person_mentioned*Community */person_mentioned*are wantonly sported with, and are as likely to
fall into the hands of a fugitive *person_mentioned*vagabond */person_mentioned*or an ignorant *person_mentioned*fool */person_mentioned*as
into those of an honest or intelligent *person_mentioned*man*/person_mentioned*— A community that
tramples on so sacred a privilege as the elective franchise deserves to
suffer, and sooner or later it will suffer— But if a talking, 
inflamitory and artfull *person_mentioned*demagogue */person_mentioned*opens his mouth, all is attention, these
same *person_mentioned*officers */person_mentioned*whose election was of no consequence are suspected,
watched, and often [abused?] and cursed and condemned by the
awful . . .l ion without invest[gation] . . . This inconsistency . , .
[This is a very seri?]ous situation, there is a general [spirit of cav-?]
iling that will lead to ruin if it is not checked— The *person_mentioned*people */person_mentioned*must
repose confidence in some one, and believe that there is some 
honesty in the world, or they are lost—their own wild passions will
destroy them*/p*

*p*If they will have confidence in me and apply to me to explain
what they do not understand, I will attend to their requests—their
enquiries shall all be answered so far as I can answer them*/p*

*p*The laws cannot be published in print so that every man will
have a copy of them, and there is no other way but for the *person_mentioned*people*/person_mentioned*
to come and read the manuscript translations that are in the *location_mentioned*office*/location_mentioned*,
or to have confidence in some one— I am bold to say that I have
done nothing to forfeit the confidence of the people of this *location_mentioned*Colony*/location_mentioned*-—
and yet I have no doubt but that I should be abused if I was *person_mentioned*Alcalde*/person_mentioned*
as much as any body else*/p*

*p*I hope you will all be satisfied as to the reports which I have
noticed and that there will be no more excitement on that ground—
and I also hope that in future the *person_mentioned*people */person_mentioned*will enquire before they
judge or condemn—*/p*

*p*[Stephen F. Austin.]*/p*

*p*I have written in haste and expressed my feelings frankly—I am
uneasy and concerned to see so much unnessery exictement. Would
it not have been better to have ascertained the truth of all these<barker_pb n="205"/>
matters before passion was indulged—? What I have said to you
I say to all, and if you think proper to shew my letter you can do
so to who you please*/p*

*p**person_mentioned*SFA*/person_mentioned**/p*

*p*It is very important to send in the reports of births and deaths
agreeably to the advertisement on that subject, and I hope it will
not be neglected—for the *person_mentioned*Ayto */person_mentioned*are obliged to make this return every
three months or be fined— I have explained this matter fully to
*person_mentioned*Cap Baily*/person_mentioned* for it is not understood*/p*

*p*[Addressed:] *person_mentioned*Mr J. H. Bell*/person_mentioned*  *location_mentioned* Lower Settlement*/location_mentioned**/p*

*/div1*
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
