
<TEI.2 id="APB1435">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>09-10-1827</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1679-1680</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>H. H. League</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Stephen F. Austin</document_recipient>
<document_title>H. H. League to Stephen F. Austin, 09-10-1827</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Unknown</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>H. H. League to Austin, September 10, 1827. Asking Austin to act for the Nashville company in Saltillo.    Disturbances in the colony.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes></barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1679-1680</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>07-26-2010</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>


<text id="APB1435T">

<body>
*div1 type="summary"*
*p*H. H. League to Austin, September 10, 1827. Asking Austin to act for the Nashville company in Saltillo.    Disturbances in the colony.*/p*
*/div1*

*div1 type="body"*

*p*Dear Sir*/p*

*p*From the shortness of the notice and my unprepared situation I
find it will be impossible for me to meet you in *location_mentioned*Saltillo*/location_mentioned*. I had 
determined to set out in *date_mentioned n="10-xx-1827">October */date_mentioned*nor will it be possible for me under 
Existing circumstances to set out sooner. I grately regret that I can
not go on. and since you have the goodness to offer your assistance
in the Business and it will be impossible for me to meet you in
*location_mentioned*Saltillo*/location_mentioned*. I am certain that you can do infihately more by haveing
the documents without my presents than I could possibly doo by
being thare without yours; I have therefore sent you the whole of
the documents that is in my possession, with a full power of attorney
to act in all Respects for me: I rote on to the *person_mentioned*company at Nashville
*/person_mentioned*by *person_mentioned*General Fulerton */person_mentioned*for other Necessary documents and also for
funds to be sent by mail to *location_mentioned*nachitoches*/location_mentioned*. I started a man for them
about Two weeks since but he has not had time to return. Should I<barker_pb n="1680"/>
receive any necessary papers from thare in time for them to Reach
you before you leave I will inclose them by mail to you.*/p*

*p*You mentioned in your communication that you would be short
of funds I doubt not but I will receive as much as $500 from the
company by my Return from *location_mentioned*nachitoches */location_mentioned*and should you have
occasion to draw on me and you can make it answer you any 
purpose your Draft shall be honoured and paid as soon as the funds
shall come to hand.*/p*

*p*I have also inclosed you a bill of directions imbracing some of the
wishes of the *person_mentioned*company */person_mentioned*any of the requests that you may think 
unpopular or Improper to ask you will please to omit and any thing
that you may Esteam advantageous or proper to be asked for you
will pleas to do so though it is not in the memorial or bill of 
directions*/p*

*p*The difficulty that was apprehended on account of *person_mentioned*Daton */person_mentioned*is over
he has been punished and *location_mentioned*driven out of the colony*/location_mentioned*, his designs on
the *location_mentioned*Colony */location_mentioned*was full of mischief and Rebellion and had become more
formidable than any of us imagined and was On the Eave of 
brakeing out but it is fortunately Over, your *person_mentioned*brother */person_mentioned**person_mentioned*Mr. Williams*/person_mentioned* and
I will write you more fully on the subject, it is all important for
many reasons that I should remain here until after court, if matters
is properly managed then the tranquility and future harmony of the
*location_mentioned*colony */location_mentioned*will be more permanently Established than ever, the 
circumstance of this appeal in the case *person_mentioned*Payton*/person_mentioned*, Vs, *person_mentioned*Parker */person_mentioned*is daily
producing more and more Excitement. I have used Every 
Exertion in my power to have it compromised and thought once I had
done so by *person_mentioned*Peyton */person_mentioned*giving up the damages allowed him and paying
the cost of the suit which he agreed to do but was afterwards broken
off by *person_mentioned*Parker*/person_mentioned*, if it is in your Power to put a stop to the 
Proceedings it will be a finishing stroke to Publick tranquility, the health
of the *location_mentioned*colony */location_mentioned*has been good my self and *person_mentioned*family */person_mentioned*has in joyed fine
health.*/p*

*p**date_mentioned n="09-10-1827">Sept. 10 182*/date_mentioned*7*/p*
*p**person_mentioned*H. H. League  */person_mentioned*  [Rubric]*/p*
*p**person_mentioned*Col. Stephen F. Austin*/person_mentioned**/p*


*/div1*
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
