
<TEI.2 id="APB1105">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>05-13-1825</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1094-1095</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Jacob Betts</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Stephen F. Austin</document_recipient>
<document_title>Jacob Betts to Stephen F. Austin, 05-13-1825</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Unknown</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Jacob Betts to Austin, May 13, 1825. Very angry and disappointed over his allotment of land.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes>See also Betts to Austin, June 27, 1825</barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1094-1095</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>06-09-2010</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>


<text id="APB1105T">

<body>
*div1 type="summary"*
*p*Jacob Betts to Austin, May 13, 1825. Very angry and disappointed over his allotment of land.*/p*
*/div1*

*div1 type="body"*

*p**date_mentioned n="05-13-1825">May the 13 1825*/date_mentioned**/p*
*p**person_mentioned*Colo S F Austen*/person_mentioned**/p*

*p*Sir I feal myself bound from the treatment I have receivd from
you to inform you of my fealings they are Raught to the highest
pitch I appeal to your prommises [you] know how for you 
complyed with them I came to this *location_mentioned*Colony */location_mentioned*with every assurance that
I would be governd by one of our *person_mentioned*Countrymen */person_mentioned*whom I had 
antispated the grates satisfaction of spendin the Remainder of my days
with [With] these expectations I have spent the three Last years
of my life in poverty and misery Looking forward for beter times
part of the thime fed with soft words and fair promises but sir I
appeal to you your own brest to say how fair thay have bin 
complyed with I am now efferd one half of what some others are that
have just arive in the *location_mentioned*country */location_mentioned*[and] take this for the begining
Reaping the rewards of my Laber and I have to say arangement for
me to go to work I have to say all confidence is Lost deceivin one
perhaps in another deceivd as I am by my *person_mentioned*commander */person_mentioned*I feal it
my unbound duty as a *person_mentioned*free man*/person_mentioned* to exclaim against him it ever has
bin my disposition never to harber anything in my brest against
any man without leten him know it I therefore consider myself a
free man and an injured one if I could got justice I should be
settled and attendin to my bisness I therefore thak this methon of
informing you Regardless of conciquences it apears all confidence
is Lost I feal myself prepard to meat the worst and unless I am
plast on an eaquel footing with other men feel it my duty to seek
redress to the Last extents now [no] doubt the justis of my cause
will bear me out I seek now privat advantage of you but Rest you
asurecl if I commence with you I Leave nothing undon to the best
of my skill and ability, though it is not my wish to enter into bisness
of that kind it has bin my determination to seek my redress if I
distroyed the interest of myself and evry other man in this *location_mentioned*provence*/location_mentioned*
Know I leave it to yourself to gave me justes if you will put me
off with a half League of Land I will except of it but you may rest
asure I am not satisfyed with one half Leag if you will gave me
the half of the *location_mentioned*47 Leag*/location_mentioned* and *location_mentioned*one half of a Leag up this River */location_mentioned*of
half of the *location_mentioned*7 or 8 Leag*/location_mentioned* in the *location_mentioned*bay*/location_mentioned* you will find me disposed to
render my services for the benefit of the *location_mentioned*colony */location_mentioned*as fair as is in my
power but if I am not satisfyed you will find I can do you or the
*location_mentioned*colony */location_mentioned*as mutch Injury as any other man though it is not my wish
I want nothing more than is Reasonable you gave me as you see
proper and I think you will gave me justis  I shall start for the<barker_pb n="1095"/>
*location_mentioned*guadalope */location_mentioned*or further in the *date_mentioned n="05-14-1825">morning */date_mentioned*and perhaps I shall return
hear in one or two months I will except of the half Leag of Land
you oferd me but perhaps it will better for the *location_mentioned*Community */location_mentioned*at larg
to deal justly by me you will pleas sen me what you intend to
gave me*/p*

*p**person_mentioned**person_mentioned*Jacob Betts*/person_mentioned*
*/person_mentioned**/p*
*/div1*
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
