
<TEI.2 id="APB1013">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>01-15-1825</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1018-1019</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>J. Iams</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Stephen F. Austin</document_recipient>
<document_title>J. Iams to Stephen F. Austin, 01-15-1825</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Cedar Bayou, Texas</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>J. Iiams to Austin, January 15, 1825.    Concerning land and surveying.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes></barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1018-1019</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>05-23-2010</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>


<text id="APB1013T">

<body>
*div1 type="summary"*
*p*J. Iiams to Austin, January 15, 1825.    Concerning land and surveying.*/p*
*/div1*

*div1 type="body"*
*p**location_mentioned*Cedar Buyo*/location_mentioned* *date_mentioned n="01-15-1825">Jany 15th 1825*/date_mentioned**/p*
*p*Dear Sir*/p*

*p*I have seen *person_mentioned*Mr Cook*/person_mentioned* and he has the variations of the compass on
the same side of the needle that I have and says *person_mentioned*Mr Hunter*/person_mentioned* is wrong.
The Variation is Easterly and Consequently the North point of the
needle is on the East or Eight hand of the true North, and each line
must be run on the left hand of that point of the needle which is
foremost on the Course. Now I am ready to give testimony and the
lines will prove that *person_mentioned*Mr Hunter*/person_mentioned* has run my lines on the right hand
of the Needle and consequently they are wrong. I have also found
some other Errors in the survey as himself has suspected in Closeing
the lines, but I wish him not to survey it again as I believe he will
still be liable to many Errors. As proper Land-marks between 
*person_mentioned*Neighbours */person_mentioned*are of great Consequence in the preservation of peace and 
harmony and my future exertions will probably be on this piece of
ground, I would desire that my lines be run agreeable to the 
Customary rules observed in this *location_mentioned*Province*/location_mentioned**/p*

*p*Therefore I shall proceed to survey the land my self and send
you the field notes unless a line from you or some other information 
should spare me the trouble*/p*

*p*As the Timber on my land is extremely scarce and all too short
for several of the purposes of building which I contemplate and I
shall be under the necessity of Resorting to other Lands for a supply,
I will therefore send you the field notes of a Labour where timber
is uniformly plenty and no Claimant ne[a]r, I will be ready to make
payment according to Custom and hope in some way it will be
granted<barker_pb n="1019"/>*/p*


*p*I have not had the opportunity of seeing *person_mentioned*Mr Hunter*/person_mentioned* since I saw
you but am informed that he declares that he has made no Errors
in his survey, I have paid him about $20 and will pay him any other
part which he may Justly be entitled to as I stated to you before even
tho, I should survey the whole myself.*/p*

*p*Dier Sir I write to you with the full assurance of your friendship
wishing to give you as little trouble as I can as some of my *person_mentioned*Neighbours */person_mentioned*
have already given you too much concerning their Lands*/p*

*p*A line from you on the above subject will be received with pleasure
and all orders promptly obeyed by
*/p*
*p**person_mentioned*J. Iiams*/person_mentioned**/p*

*p**person_mentioned*Col. S. F. Austin*/person_mentioned**/p*

*p*P. S. I have understood that $3.50 will be demanded in cash at
your *location_mentioned*office */location_mentioned*for my Deed which would have been paid when I saw you
had I known the circumstance but I will pay it at the first 
opportunity.*/p*

*p*If I am wrong in the variation of the compass I am willing to pay
the cost of proving it   *person_mentioned*J. I. [J. Iiams]*/person_mentioned**/p*


*/div1*
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
