
<TEI.2 id="APB1697">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>03-25-1829</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1922: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1928), 3 vols., Vol 2, pp. 195-197</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>William Morton</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Stephen F Austin</document_recipient>
<document_title>William Morton to Stephen F Austin, 03-25-1829</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Unknown</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>William Morton to Austin, March 25, 1829. People will support an academy, but will not consent to have it in any way under the authority of the ayuntamiento of San Felipe.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes></barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 195-197</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>08-10-2010</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>


<text id="APB1697T">

<body>
*div1 type="summary"*
*p*William Morton to Austin, March 25, 1829. People will support an academy, but will not consent to have it in any way under the authority of the ayuntamiento of San Felipe.*/p*
*/div1*

*div1 type="body"*

*p*Dr Sir*/p*

*p*Their was handed me by *person_mentioned*Mr Jamson*/person_mentioned* several letters [and a] plan
[of] subscription for an *location_mentioned*Academy */location_mentioned*which I handed to *person_mentioned*Cpt Martin*/person_mentioned*
and *person_mentioned*Ed Jones*/person_mentioned* as directed for their deliberation *person_mentioned*Cpt Martin*/person_mentioned* rather
paused for some time before he gave aney opinion abought it he
finally observed he should not feel safe to subscribe to the bond as
he had no faith in the preasent *person_mentioned*Ayuntamento */person_mentioned*body and not knowing
who would Succeed them theirfore he didnot feel safe in vestin his
money in their handes nor should not tho he observed that he would
contribute as much to that *person_mentioned*Institution */person_mentioned*as aney other person of his
abilites provided it could be established on a fair and satisfactory
basis and the same opinion prevails thrueout this *location_mentioned*nabourhood */location_mentioned*their
has been so maney complaints abought the past conduct of the
*person_mentioned*Ayuntamento */person_mentioned*that it appears to me to be all most out of the question
to do aney thing of a *person_mentioned*publick */person_mentioned*nature thrue them of that kind for to
make them *person_mentioned*men */person_mentioned*appear responsible and addequit to establish an<barker_pb n="196"/>
*person_mentioned*Institutision */person_mentioned*of that kind and by donatisions from the itinerrant
*person_mentioned*settelars of this *location_mentioned*colney */location_mentioned**/person_mentioned*it would be as esey to make the peopel
beleave that black was whit the contrast would be equly as grate
for Equity has been harrowed like the *person_mentioned*Trishman*/person_mentioned*s hors by the tail
Backwardes to much for them to be the sole managers of so 
benovelant an Institutision as that their is a rumor aflote that the 
*person_mentioned*Ayuntomento */person_mentioned*has introdused a projecte of a law to rais $5000 by a direct tax
in this *location_mentioned*colney */location_mentioned*for publick porposes if so and I was allowed my
opion I should say they would have rather to grate an overpluck of
buisness to attend to for if you will vu their past projects 
collectively and impartially you might see that it would prove Abortive
for the worst prejudiced designing moralist will ever be foremost to
thrust themselves into power is a matter desided heir [here?] and the
result will bring ruin uppon themselves and the *person_mentioned*unhappy few*/person_mentioned* over
whome they may preside concequently I do not feal an 
inclinenatision to have anaey thing to do with the *location_mentioned*Acadamy */location_mentioned*thrue them exclucifly
I dont feal like I could stand the Execratisions that: would be heeped
upon me for what I might expect to get for it under the preasant
circumstances not withstanding aney thing that corns in the vue
of my weak fackculteys that I can render you in establishing that
*location_mentioned*Institution */location_mentioned*upon a permeneant and Ecquitable basis is intirly at your
Service and as I have no disposition to animadvert in the past 
grievances or throw aney obstructtision in the way I will name the
ought lines [outlines] of a course by which I think in all probility
it might be established to the genral satisfaction of the whole with
the exception of a part of the *person_mentioned*Ayuntamento */person_mentioned*body that is if you will
take it upon your self to nominate 7 or 8 or more *person_mentioned*persons */person_mentioned*in the
different parts of the *location_mentioned*colney */location_mentioned*to enquire into the utility of such an
*location_mentioned*instutision */location_mentioned*and the requsit *location_mentioned*buildings */location_mentioned*and let them act as a *person_mentioned*commitee
of ways and means */person_mentioned*in the first instance they could decide by vote on
the most important point which would be wheather we would have
such an *location_mentioned*institution */location_mentioned*in the *location_mentioned*Colney */location_mentioned*or not I will venture to Say that
their is not aney person in the Shape of a human that had ever
wore aney garbe larger than a britchclout in this *location_mentioned*colney */location_mentioned*but what
would approve of Such an institution again they could appoint or
elect *person_mentioned*Trustes */person_mentioned**person_mentioned*treasurer */person_mentioned**person_mentioned*auditor */person_mentioned**person_mentioned*colector */person_mentioned*etc and one of the 
*person_mentioned*ayuntamento */person_mentioned*bodey might act as such when they would have a fare Chance
to sho what the Government would do in the first Instance and
thrue them which would be the most esential thinges in order that
the *person_mentioned*trustes */person_mentioned*might proceed leagely and upon a fair basis*/p*

*p*with regard to the plan you Sent me I will be better abel to do
something with it when I See you (when I get my crop planted I will
try to come up and See you) you may think my answer to you rather
ruff and evasive but I pledg you my word it is not with aney desine<barker_pb n="197"/>
to procostinate your desine or throw the least obstical in the way that
would have a tendaneee to cast a shade over workes of so much
utility I must theirfore enjoint on you to excuse my weak epistle as
you know I am no *person_mentioned*Soloman */person_mentioned*or *person_mentioned*Scribe*/person_mentioned**/p*

*p**person_mentioned*Wm Morton  */person_mentioned*  [Rubric]*/p*
*p**person_mentioned*S. F. Austin*/person_mentioned* *date_mentioned n="03-25-1829">March 25th 1829*/date_mentioned**/p*

*/div1*
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
