
<TEI.2 id="APB2101">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>[09-06-1825]</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1922: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1928), 3 vols., Vol 2, pp. 1190-1191</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Stephen F Austin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Laurence Richard Kenny</document_recipient>
<document_title>Stephen F Austin to Laurence Richard Kenny, [09-06-1825]</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Unknown</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Austin to Laurence Richard Kenny, September 6, 1825. Concerning the dispute that Kenny is having with Coles about deed.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes></barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1190-1191</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>12-26-2010</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>


<text id="APB2101T">

<body>
*div1 type="summary"*
*p*Austin to Laurence Richard Kenny, September 6, 1825. Concerning the dispute that Kenny is having with Coles about deed.*/p*
*/div1*

*div1 type="body"*

*p*[September 6, 1825]*/p*

*p*I have seen a letter of yours of this date to *person_mentioned*Col Coles*/person_mentioned* on the 
Subject of *person_mentioned*Richmond*/person_mentioned*s business, and at my request he has declined 
paying any attention to it, and indeed after what I told you as regards
*person_mentioned*Coles*/person_mentioned* I must express some surprise at the nature of your letter. I
told you that I had written to both to send me the paper in 
question, in fact I wrote him a positive order to do so in as much as a
mistake had been made in it but independent of this *person_mentioned*David Richmond*/person_mentioned*
was not such a man as the Law recognized as a *person_mentioned*Suitable person to be
recd as a settler*/person_mentioned*—   he was a *person_mentioned*vagabond */person_mentioned*in the full extent of the<barker_pb n="1191"/>
expression and is not such a man as I should be justifiable in 
returning to the *person_mentioned*Govt */person_mentioned*as a *person_mentioned*Settler*/person_mentioned*—and for this reason and many
others I shall feel my self entirely justifiable in not recognizing him
as a *person_mentioned*settler */person_mentioned*altho I had not finally determined to adopt that course,
the violent steps however indicated in your letter are illy calculated
to obtain the result you wish for, and can only involve yourself in
unnecessary difficulty, a thing which I should also regret because
I believe you are actuated in the affair by what you deem to be your
duty as *person_mentioned*executor*/person_mentioned*, but many men run into error by a mistaken idea
of duty—be that as it may the tendency of your letters is calculated
to break the public peace and as such, if persisted in will place you
under very heavy and unpleasant responsibility. I again repeat that
*person_mentioned*Coles*/person_mentioned* has nothing to do with the affair nor you with him. what he
did was by my order, and I alone am responsible for any legal claim
*person_mentioned*Richmond */person_mentioned*or his *person_mentioned*heirs */person_mentioned*may pretend to have on the subject—*/p*

*p*I wish to assure you that I have none other than friendly feelings
on the subject as regards yourself, and if you fully understood the
exact nature of the business your own good sence and candor would
at once say that were you situated as I am you would at least 
deliberate some time before you made any decission on the matter— 
probably the best way to stop any thing further on the subject would be
for you and me to talk it over to ourselves—*/p*

*p*[S. F. Austin]*/p*

*p*[To Lawrence Richard Kenny]*/p*

*/div1*
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
