
<TEI.2 id="APB2008">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>05-xx-1825</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1922: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1928), 3 vols., Vol 2, pp. 1108</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Agreement</document_type>
<document_author>Unknown</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Unknown</document_recipient>
<document_title>Unknown to Unknown, 05-xx-1825</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Unknown</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Form of agreement [May? —, 1825], Payments to be made for land by colonists.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes>The date supplied is somewhat arbitrary. The document is in Austin's hand. The
statement that married men are entitled to a league and labor of land suggests that this
fee was meant to apply to the few titles lacking to fill the first contract for 300 families,
since a league was the standard grant in subsequent contracts.
</barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1108</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>12-13-2010</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>


<text id="APB2008T">

<body>
*div1 type="summary"*
*p*Form of agreement [May? —, 1825], Payments to be made for land by colonists.*/p*
*/div1*

*div1 type="body"*

*p*[May?—,1825]*/p*

*p*We whose names are subscribed in the third Colum of this book
acknowledge that on the days set down in the second Column 
opposite to our respective names We received from the *person_mentioned*Emp° Stephen F.
Austin*/person_mentioned* a permission to select land in his *location_mentioned*Colony */location_mentioned*as *person_mentioned*settlers */person_mentioned*in the
same by which it appears that as *person_mentioned*married men*/person_mentioned* the Law allows one
sitio and one Labor of Land and therefore in Compliance with the
foregoing regulations which have been heretofore published and
understood by us we do each of us separately hereby covenant and
agree with said *person_mentioned*Austin */person_mentioned*to pay him Fifty dollars each in two 
payments that is to say 20$ in 6 months from the date of the said 
permision as set down in the 2d Column opposite to our respective
names and thirty dollars in one year from the sd. date, for the true
and faithful payment of which sum as above specified by each one
seperately without any defalcation delay or objection whatever to
said *person_mentioned*Austin */person_mentioned*or order we do each of us seperately bind ourselves our
heirs or assigns, and as security for said payment we do each of us
seperately hereby mortgage to said *person_mentioned*Austin */person_mentioned*or to his assigns the Land
which we may each individually receive as *person_mentioned*settlers */person_mentioned*in sd *location_mentioned*Colony*/location_mentioned*, In
faith of which we sign this agreement and obligation in presence
of the witness whose name is signed in the first column opposite
our respective names, and hereby make it binding on us and our
heirs it being a fair contract explained and understood by each one
of us fully before signing and as such guaranteed to the sd. *person_mentioned*Emp°
*/person_mentioned*by the 9th article of the colonization Law of this *location_mentioned*state*/location_mentioned*.*/p*

*/div1*
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
