
<TEI.2 id="APB 3006">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>09-28-1825</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1208-1211</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Public</document_status>
<document_type>Referendum</document_type>
<document_author>Stephen F. Austin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Unknown</document_recipient>
<document_title>Stephen F. Austin to , 09-28-1825</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>San Felipe de Austin, Texas</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Referendum on war with Comanches, Wacoes, and Tahuacanas. His own views are in favor of neutrality if it can be maintained, awaiting settlement of Robertson's and DeWitt's colonies.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes></barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1208-1211</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>05-21-2010</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Cameron L. Sinclair, Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>


<text id="APB 3006T">

<body>
*div1 type="summary"*
*p*Referendum on war with Comanches, Wacoes, and Tahuacanas. His own views are in favor of neutrality if it can be maintained, awaiting settlement of Robertson's and DeWitt's colonies.*/p*
*/div1*

*div1 type="body"*

*p*In Consequence of the depredations commited by the *person_mentioned*Weco*/person_mentioned* or
*person_mentioned*Tahuacana Indians*/person_mentioned* in stealing horses from the *location_mentioned*frontier of this Colony*/location_mentioned* great excitement has been produced, and some of the *person_mentioned*settlers */person_mentioned*express a wish to commence open war with said *person_mentioned*tribes*/person_mentioned*. On hearing of
the *person_mentioned*Comanche*/person_mentioned* War at *location_mentioned*San Antonio*/location_mentioned*, I wrote to the *person_mentioned*Chief of Department*/person_mentioned* on the *date_mentioned n="08-20-1825">20th of Augt*/date_mentioned* Stating the situation of this *location_mentioned*Colony */location_mentioned*and
our illy prepared state for War, owing to our *location_mentioned*scattered settlements*/location_mentioned*
our weak numbers, the scarcity of Arms, Amunition and Horses
fit for long and active service such as an expedition into the *location_mentioned*Indian
Country*/location_mentioned* etc and asked permission for this *location_mentioned*settlement */location_mentioned*to avail themselves of the friendly dispositions of the *person_mentioned*Indians */person_mentioned*to remain Neutral.*/p*

*p*Subsequently I received an order from the *person_mentioned*Military Commandant*/person_mentioned*
dated *date_mentioned n="08-21-1825">21st. Augt*/date_mentioned* to attack the *person_mentioned*Wacos*/person_mentioned* without delay and destroy their
*location_mentioned*Villages*/location_mentioned*, this order was suspended by another dated the *date_mentioned n="08-26-1825">26th of Augt*/date_mentioned* by which I am informed that a body of *person_mentioned*Comanches*/person_mentioned* was at the
*location_mentioned**person_mentioned*Waco*/person_mentioned* Village*/location_mentioned* and the attack directed by the order of the *date_mentioned n="08-21-1825">21st*/date_mentioned* was in
consequence suspended untill I should hear of the departure of the
*person_mentioned*Comanches*/person_mentioned* but repeating the injunction to attack the *person_mentioned*Wacos*/person_mentioned*, the
first favourable opportunity, the *date_mentioned n="09-08-1825">8th of September*/date_mentioned* I acknowledged
the receipt of the two last mentioned orders and availing myself of
the descretion given in the last one as to the time and mode of 
Commencing the War, I informed the *person_mentioned*Military Commandant*/person_mentioned*, that in
consequence of the number of sick and the necessity of gathering
our crops it would be impossible to commence hostilities at present
and that I should therefore wait an answer to my proposition to
the Govt of the *date_mentioned n="08-20-1825">20th of Aug**/date_mentioned* relative to a State of neutralship be<barker_pb n="1209"/>fore any offensive measures should be adopted. It may be proper to
state that the *person_mentioned*Military Commandant*/person_mentioned* has ordered me in case I take
any property from said *person_mentioned*Indians*/person_mentioned* to give him an account thereof that
he may determine what shall be done with it, this is the substance of
what has passed betwen me and the *person_mentioned*Govt */person_mentioned*on the subject. If the
Govt in answer to my proposition of the *date_mentioned n="08-20-1825">20th of Augt*/date_mentioned* repeat the order
for war positively the only subject for consideration will be the most
efficient plan of conducting it, If they leave it discretionaly with
us to commence War or not, several points of great importance present themselves for the mature and deliberate consideration of the
settlers. In this state of things I have deemed it my duty to lay the
subject before the *person_mentioned*inhabitants of each *location_mentioned*Militia district*/location_mentioned**/person_mentioned* for their consideration, opinion and advice, the course determined on by the majority shall be adopted, it is therefore of the highest importance
that the subject should be fully and maturely discussed and deliberated in order that the united voice of the *location_mentioned*Colony*/location_mentioned* may be known
and that the course which is agreed on shall be carried into effect and
supported by the unanimous exertions of every man.*/p*

*p*The propositions which present themselves for the consideration
of the people may be reduced to the following heads—Should the
Govt repeat the order positively for War.,*/p*

*p*1st What is the best plan of defence for the *location_mentioned*frontiers*/location_mentioned*? Will a
chain of *location_mentioned*block houses*/location_mentioned* be nessisary if so at what points, how are those
to be determined on, how are the expences of building them to be
defraid, by the *person_mentioned*people of the imediate *location_mentioned*neighbourhood*/location_mentioned**/person_mentioned* or by general
contribution, will it be nessisary for the *person_mentioned*settlers*/person_mentioned* to abandon their
*location_mentioned*farms*/location_mentioned*, and embody at such *location_mentioned*block houses*/location_mentioned*, if so what will be the best
course to compel those who refuse to embody, and any other ideas
connected with this part of the subject.*/p*

*p*2nd Will an *person_mentioned*expedition */person_mentioned*to the *location_mentioned*Indian Towns*/location_mentioned* be expedient, if so
what is the least number of men that ought to go how soon could it
be fitted out, whether they should all be mounted or part on foot,
how many days provisions ought they to start with—*/p*

*p*3rd Will it be good policy to send for the *person_mentioned*Lepan*/person_mentioned* and *person_mentioned*Tankaway
Indians*/person_mentioned*, to join us in such expedition, those *person_mentioned*Indians*/person_mentioned* will doubtless
do some good as *person_mentioned*auxilleries */person_mentioned*but if we apply to them for aid we shall
have them to feed and support, we must tolerate them to live in the
*location_mentioned*settlements*/location_mentioned*, and if so must expect them to steal our hogs and corn
and kill some of our cattle for they will say we are bound to feed
them as they are fighting for us—*/p*

*p*4th Could the*person_mentioned* men from the *location_mentioned*lower settlements*/location_mentioned**/person_mentioned* be safely drawn
from there on account of the *person_mentioned*Karankaway Indians*/person_mentioned*  or would it be
most prudent to conclude a peace with these *person_mentioned*Indians*/person_mentioned* so as not to
have two *location_mentioned*frontiers*/location_mentioned* to defend at the same time—*/p*<barker_pb n="1210"/>

*p*Should the *person_mentioned*Government */person_mentioned*give us discretionary Power eather for
War or Peace—*/p*

*p*1st Is it most expedient to declare war at once, or to attempt a
treaty of peace?*/p*

*p*2nd If the latter what is the best course to obtain it, will it be
best for me to go in person to their *location_mentioned*Towns*/location_mentioned*, and conclude a treaty
or send a deputation for that object, or to invite the *person_mentioned*Chiefs*/person_mentioned* to meet
us, at the *location_mentioned*San Antonio Road*/location_mentioned*—*/p*

*p*3rd If I go or send to their *location_mentioned*Towns*/location_mentioned*, how many men should compose
the *person_mentioned*party*/person_mentioned*: how soon ought it to Start? will it be best to send a
*person_mentioned*messenger */person_mentioned*a head and notify them of our approach and object, and
request them to send for the *person_mentioned*absent Chiefs*/person_mentioned*.*/p*

*p*4th Will it be best to demand the stolen horses, and make the restitution of them and the punishment of *person_mentioned*Tomlinsons Murderers*/person_mentioned*, a
condition of peace or War? or will it be best to say nothing about
them and leave it for a future demand when we are in a better situation to enforce it?—*/p*

*p*5th Or will it be best to complain of those depredations but without making a positive demand of restitution, because a positive demand if made and refused is of course a declaration of war, for if
it is made it must be enforced—*/p*

*p*6th Or will it be best to be governed by circumstances and the
appearence of things after we see the *person_mentioned*Chiefs*/person_mentioned*, and eather make the
demand or not as those circumstances may require?*/p*

*p*7 I wish the *person_mentioned*people of each*location_mentioned* Militia district*/location_mentioned**/person_mentioned* to elect one person to
accompany me if I go to treat with the *person_mentioned*Indians*/person_mentioned*, for the purpose of
forming a *person_mentioned*council */person_mentioned*or direct representation of the *location_mentioned*Colony*/location_mentioned*, this person
will be elected by each *person_mentioned*company */person_mentioned*when these propositions are submitted to them.—*/p*

*p*The foregoing except the last article I believe embraces the most
material points that have been talked of amongst the *person_mentioned*settlers*/person_mentioned*, the
last one is a proposition of my own,—- This is an important subject in our present situation and I wish the free voice of the *location_mentioned*Colony*/location_mentioned*
to decide what is the best source to be adopted—and with such a
*person_mentioned*council */person_mentioned*as the one I propose I shall feel more Confidence—*/p*

*p*Without wishing or intending to give my opinion as to the points
submitted, it may be proper and nessisary for me to make some re-
flections as to our present situation and future prospects—*/p*

*p*The Government have authorized a new Colony of 800 families on
the *location_mentioned*Brazos*/location_mentioned*and *location_mentioned*Colorado River*/location_mentioned*s above the *location_mentioned*San Antonio road*/location_mentioned* from
*location_mentioned*Tennessee*/location_mentioned*and *location_mentioned*Kentucky*/location_mentioned*, and I have every reason to believe that by
next *date_mentioned n="04-xx-1826">April*/date_mentioned* that *location_mentioned*Colony*/location_mentioned* will be at least 200 strong. Will a war at
this time with the upper *person_mentioned*Indians*/person_mentioned* have a tendency to stop emigration
to that *location_mentioned*Colony*/location_mentioned* altogether?  or to check it materially?    also the <barker_pb n="1211"/>*location_mentioned*Colony*/location_mentioned* on the *location_mentioned*Guadaloupe*/location_mentioned* is about commencing, will a war stop
the settlement there or not? will a war stop emigration to this
*location_mentioned*Colony*/location_mentioned*? will it enduce any to move away? Can the people live
in a state of war without forting and will they remain in the country
if they are compelled to live in that manner?*/p*

*p*The *person_mentioned*Wacos*/person_mentioned* and *person_mentioned*Tawakanys*/person_mentioned* are at peace and in close alliance with
the *person_mentioned*Comanches*/person_mentioned*, the *person_mentioned*Cherokees*/person_mentioned* and all the *person_mentioned*Indians*/person_mentioned* *location_mentioned*to the east of us*/location_mentioned*,
and I am creditably informed that these *person_mentioned*latter Indians*/person_mentioned* are very
much dissatisfied that their *location_mentioned*country */location_mentioned*has been given to the *person_mentioned*American
Empresarios*/person_mentioned* to be settled.— In this state of feeling is there not
some danger that all the *person_mentioned*Indians in the *location_mentioned*Province*/location_mentioned**/person_mentioned* may be induced to
unite against the *location_mentioned*American settlements*/location_mentioned*? If we destroy the *location_mentioned**person_mentioned*Waco*/person_mentioned*
Villages*/location_mentioned* will not the other *person_mentioned*tribes */person_mentioned*consider it as a warning of the fate
that must in the end befal them if the *location_mentioned*american settlements*/location_mentioned* progress?
and is there no[t] danger that they may become alarmed and unite
to cut us off in our infancy ? The history of the *location_mentioned*first settlements in
the U. States*/location_mentioned*, presents numerous and horible examples of such combinations, which in most instances might have been avoided by a
greater degree of prudence and forbearance on the part of the *person_mentioned*settlers*/person_mentioned* in the first years of their establishment—*/p*

*p*No aid whatever may be expected from the *person_mentioned*Government*/person_mentioned*, if we get
into a war, we must get through it the best way we can, without
expecting aid from any *location_mentioned*quarter*/location_mentioned*— In this state of things the question which the people have to decide is whether it is better to submit
to a few insults rather than risque bringing on a war with all the
*person_mentioned*northern Indians*/person_mentioned* by resenting them at this time I know that it is
a difficult thing to control the passions but in such case as the present
all passion should be set aside and cool deliberate Judgement should
decide.— True it is we have received repeated Insults from the
*person_mentioned*Indians*/person_mentioned* which merrit punishment and great excitement and thirst
for revenge exists in many persons, this is a correct feeling, but
whether this is the proper time to seek revenge or not is a question
which cool Judgement and not passion should decide—*/p*
*p**location_mentioned*San Felipe de Austin*/location_mentioned* *date_mentioned n="09-28-1825">Sept. 28th 1825*/date_mentioned**/p*

*p**person_mentioned*Stephen F. Austin*/person_mentioned*    [Rubric]*/p*

*/div1*
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
