
<TEI.2 id="APB4068">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>11-01-1830</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1922: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1928), 3 vols., Vol 2, pp. 525-526</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>John Austin</document_author>
<document_sender>Mr. Borden</document_sender>
<document_recipient>Stephen F Austin</document_recipient>
<document_title>John Austin to Stephen F Austin, 11-01-1830</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Unknown</sent_from>
	<sent_to>San Felipe de Austin, Texas</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>John Austin to Austin, November 1, 1830. Concerning settlement of James Austin's estate</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes></barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 525-526</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>08-31-2010</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>


<text id="APB4068T">

<body>
*div1 type="summary"*
*p*John Austin to Austin, November 1, 1830. Concerning settlement of James Austin's estate*/p*
*/div1*

*div1 type="body"*

*p*[November 1, 1830.]*/p*
*p*Dr. Sir*/p*

*p*Herewith I send the papers of*p* H. Austin*/p* Should Sent them 
before but had no safe conveyance that I could rely upon their being
handed you, enclosed I also send the list of appraisment of the
property at the *location_mentioned*Gin */location_mentioned*I have sold some of the Stock at the appraised
value and think it best to sell all the stock as it has not increased<barker_pb n="520"/>
in value since it was put there and unless a sufficient number could be
put there to make it an object for the person attending to devote
his whole time the stock will not do well *person_mentioned*Harris */person_mentioned*wished to give up
the place I settled with him according to the contract *person_mentioned*W. D. C.
Hall*/person_mentioned* wishes to live at that *location_mentioned*place */location_mentioned*and will take a lease of it for a
number of years and as the land belongs to *person_mentioned*a minor*/person_mentioned* I would advise
you to let*person_mentioned* Mr Hall*/person_mentioned* have it for a certain number of years and for the
rent to leave a certain improvement and in good order by so doing
the place will be Kept in good order without Expence and will 
become every day more valuable, I advised *person_mentioned*Mr Hall*/person_mentioned* to write you
and make his terms to you I think that much the best plan for if
the place should be hired from year to year those who have it will
not take care of the fence Buildings etc which would go to wreck
and then the whole or more rent would be expended in repairing.
The *location_mentioned*buildings */location_mentioned*are good the *person_mentioned*Gin house*/person_mentioned* is sound with the exception of
some of the posts on which it stands not much work to replace them
*person_mentioned*Mr Hall*/person_mentioned* wishes it to Keep stock at and for a summer residence he
will agree to plant fruit trees and to leave good buildings on the
place and in good repair, if the proposition made by him suit you
I think it much the best plan he will write and make proposals to you
I will send you the Sugar the first opportunity there is no flour
in the place, I will come up in a short time any thing that you may
want If to be got here   I will send it by having notice that you want it*/p*

*p**person_mentioned*John Austin */person_mentioned*[Rubric]*/p*

*p*Have not yet heard of the Steam Boat crossing the *location_mentioned*Bar */location_mentioned*the *person_mentioned*Capt*/person_mentioned*.
is rather timid would it not be well to let *person_mentioned*Henry Smith*/person_mentioned* have the
*location_mentioned*land at the Prairie*/location_mentioned* you can esily keep others from troubling you by
putting 5 dollars pr acre price *person_mentioned*Smith */person_mentioned*is poor and a good steady
man has always been on the right side of the Question he is not
in a situation to go on his *location_mentioned*League */location_mentioned*at this time I have not said any
thing to him about your instructions concerning the land and do not
wish to influence you to let him have the land if you think it an injury
to you*/p*               

*p**person_mentioned*J. A.*/person_mentioned**/p*

*p*Since writing the above *person_mentioned*Mr Jesse Thompson*/person_mentioned* has made aplication
for the *location_mentioned*Gin Place*/location_mentioned* will agree to take it and in five years leave the
improvements with 100 Dollars more than at this time I think best
to let him have it for in that time it will rent well, please let me
know your wish on the Subject by the first opportunity*/p*

*p*[Addressed:] *person_mentioned*Col. Stephen F. Austin*/person_mentioned*  *location_mentioned* San Felipe*/location_mentioned*   *person_mentioned*Mr. Borden*/person_mentioned**/p*

*/div1*
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
