
<TEI.2 id="APB4542">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>Unknown [Prior to 04-01-1833]</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1922: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1928), 3 vols., Vol 2, pp. 934-940</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Public</document_status>
<document_type>Convention Address</document_type>
<document_author>Stephen F Austin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Conventional Committee</document_recipient>
<document_title>Stephen F Austin to Conventional Committee, Unknown [Prior to 04-01-1833]</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Unsent</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unsent</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Address of central committee to convention, April 1, 1833. Reciting reasons for separation of Coahuila and Texas.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes>This address was written by Austin for the Central Committee appointed by the convention of October, 1832. It was presented to the convention of Apr. 1, 1833. A slightly different draft exists in the Austin Papers.
Above, Ayuntamiento of San Felipe de Austin to the Fedeial Government.
For a copy see Filisola, Memorias para la Historia de la Guerra de Texas, I, 273-293</barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 934-940</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>11-14-2010</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>


<text id="APB4542T">

<body>
*div1 type="summary"*
*p*Address of central committee to convention, April 1, 1833. Reciting reasons for separation of Coahuila and Texas.*/p*
*/div1*

*div1 type="body"*

*p**person_mentioned*Gentlemen of the convention*/person_mentioned*,*/p*

*p*The *person_mentioned*central committee of safety and correspondence*/person_mentioned* which was
established by the late convention, and by whose request the present
convention has assembled, beg leave to offer their sincere 
congratulations on your arrival at the theatre where you are to exercise the<barker_pb n="935"/>
high and important duties which devolve upon you as the 
*person_mentioned*representatives of the people of your several districts*/person_mentioned*.*/p*

*p*Believing that your deliberations will be fraught with important
results to the interests of our common country, the *person_mentioned*committee */person_mentioned*deem
it a duty they owe you, as the *person_mentioned*delegates of the people*/person_mentioned* to make a
brief exposition of the reasons which have operated on them in 
calling this convention, and in doing this, they wish it to be understood,
not as attempting to dictate to this convention the course it should
pursue in the least degree, nor to prescribed limits to its action, but
to give a satisfactory explanation to you, and through you to the
great body of the *person_mentioned*people of *location_mentioned*Texas*/location_mentioned**/person_mentioned*, of the causes which have impelled
them to the exercise of this responsible duty.*/p*

*p*The situation of *location_mentioned*Texas*/location_mentioned*, is such as to give rise to great anxiety and
even alarm in the heart of every person who inhabits it, or feels
any interest for its prosperity or welfare.*/p*

*p*The whole of this *location_mentioned*country*/location_mentioned*, with the exception of the small towns
of *location_mentioned*Bexar */location_mentioned*and *location_mentioned*Goliad*/location_mentioned*, has been settled and redeemed from the 
*location_mentioned*wilderness */location_mentioned*within a few years by the enterprise of *person_mentioned*immigrants */person_mentioned*who removed
to it in consequence of the express and earnest invitation of the
*person_mentioned*Government*/person_mentioned*, contained in the national and state colonization laws.
Those *person_mentioned*immigrants */person_mentioned*have uniformly evinced their gratitude to the
*person_mentioned*government and *location_mentioned*nation */location_mentioned*of their adoption*/person_mentioned* for all the acts of 
kindness and liberality that have been extended towards them, and they
have faithfully performed their duty as *person_mentioned*Mexican citizens*/person_mentioned*, and 
fulfilled the intention and spirit of the colonization laws, by settling
the *location_mentioned*country*/location_mentioned*, defending it from hostile *person_mentioned*indians*/person_mentioned*, or other *person_mentioned*enemies*/person_mentioned*, and
developing its resources, thus giving value and character to a large
section of the *location_mentioned*Mexican territory*/location_mentioned* which was before wild and almost
unknown. They have introduced agriculture and the usefull arts
and commerce, and if as has been said by a celebrated author " that
man deserves well of his country who makes a blade of grass grow
where none grew before ", how much more do the *person_mentioned*people of *location_mentioned*Texas*/location_mentioned*
*/person_mentioned*deserve from their *location_mentioned*country */location_mentioned*who have so materially added to the
national grandeur, phisical force and resources. The *person_mentioned*people of *location_mentioned*Texas*/location_mentioned*
*/person_mentioned*ought therefore to rely with confidence on the *person_mentioned*government */person_mentioned*for 
protection, and to expect that an adequate remedy will be applied to
the many evils that are afflicting them.*/p*

*p*The invitations in virtue of which they came here, and the 
guarantees of the constitution and laws, evidently contain a pledge on
the part of the government, that they should be governed in 
accordance with the spirit of the free political institutions of the *location_mentioned*Mexican
republic*/location_mentioned*, and in the manner best adapted to the local situation and
necessities of *location_mentioned*Texas*/location_mentioned*. The <hi rend="italic">right </hi>of the people of Texas to represent
their wants to the government, and to explain in a respectfull man-<barker_pb n="936"/>
ner the remedies that will relieve them cannot therefore be doubted
or questioned. It is not merely a right, it is also a sacred and
bounden duty which they owe to themselves and to the whole 
*location_mentioned*Mexican nation*/location_mentioned*, for should evils of great and desolating magnitude fall
upon *location_mentioned*Texas */location_mentioned*for the want of competent remedies, the people here
would have cause to accuse themselves of neglect for not making an
effort to procure such remedies, and the government would also have
cause to complain, that a full and frank and timely representation
had not been made and a remedy solicited.*/p*

*p*It is very evident that these considerations have influenced the
*person_mentioned*people of *location_mentioned*Texas*/location_mentioned**/person_mentioned* in all they have done up to the present time. They
have been governed by the desire to do their duty faithfully to the
*location_mentioned*Mexican nation*/location_mentioned* and to themselves. In the discharge of this duty
the people and *person_mentioned*civil authorities of *location_mentioned*Austins Colony*/location_mentioned**/person_mentioned* made a 
respectfull and humble petition to the General and *person_mentioned*State governments*/person_mentioned* on
the *date_mentioned n="02-18-1832">18 day of Feby 1832*/date_mentioned* setting forth the evils that were afflicting
this *location_mentioned*country*/location_mentioned*. The *person_mentioned*inhabitants */person_mentioned*and *person_mentioned*civil authorities of *location_mentioned*Bexar*/location_mentioned**/person_mentioned*, the
*location_mentioned*ancient and present capital of Texas*/location_mentioned*, also made a very able and
energetic represention on the same subject on the *date_mentioned n="12-19-1832">19th of December
last*/date_mentioned*,2 Numerous other *person_mentioned*representatives */person_mentioned*have been made at various
times by all the *person_mentioned*Ayuntamientos of *location_mentioned*Texas*/location_mentioned**/person_mentioned*, and on the *date_mentioned n="10-01-1832">first of October
last*/date_mentioned* *person_mentioned*delegates of the people of *location_mentioned*Texas*/location_mentioned**/person_mentioned* met in convention at this *location_mentioned*Town*/location_mentioned*
and unanimously resolved that it was expedient that the political
union between *location_mentioned*Coahuila */location_mentioned*and *location_mentioned*Texas */location_mentioned*should be dissolved and that
*location_mentioned*Texas */location_mentioned*should be organised as a *location_mentioned*separate State of the Mexican 
confederation*/location_mentioned* as soon as the approbation of the *person_mentioned*General government
*/person_mentioned*to that effect could be obtained. That convention accordingly 
memorialised *person_mentioned*congress */person_mentioned*on the subject, and elected an *person_mentioned*agent */person_mentioned*to go to
*location_mentioned*Mexico */location_mentioned*in order to forward the views of the *person_mentioned*people of *location_mentioned*Texas*/location_mentioned**/person_mentioned* in
obtaining the sanction of the *person_mentioned*general government*/person_mentioned*. But the 
continuation of the intestine commotions which have raged within the bosom
of the *location_mentioned*Mexican republic*/location_mentioned* for more than twelve months past, and which
threaten'd a total overthrow of the established institutions of the
country, prevented the memorial from being presented in accordance
with the intentions of the *date_mentioned n="10-xx-1832">October */date_mentioned*convention.*/p*

*p*That convention adopted many other memorials and resolutions,
amongst the most important of which was the provisional 
organization of the *person_mentioned*militia*/person_mentioned*, as a precaution against contemplated attacks upon
our *location_mentioned*exposed frontier*/location_mentioned* by the many tribes of hostile *person_mentioned*indians */person_mentioned*who 
inhabit the *location_mentioned*northern and western parts of Texas*/location_mentioned*; and the 
establishment of the *person_mentioned*central and sub-committees of safety and 
correspondence*/person_mentioned* throughout the *location_mentioned*country */location_mentioned*all of which were rendered inoperative<barker_pb n="937"/>
by the decree of the *person_mentioned*governor of the *location_mentioned*state of Coahuila and Texas*/location_mentioned**/person_mentioned*,
who declared the proceedings of the convention null and void, and
ordered the several *person_mentioned*committees */person_mentioned*to dissolve.*/p*

*p*At the time when this *person_mentioned*committee */person_mentioned*determined to convoke the present
convention, they took an impartial survey of our federal relations
and of our local affairs.*/p*

*p*They beheld the *location_mentioned*Mexican confederation*/location_mentioned* torn and broken asunder
by *person_mentioned*political parties*/person_mentioned* each of which sustained its pretentions to the
*person_mentioned*supreme executive power of the nation*/person_mentioned* by force of arms. Civil war
raged in every part of the *location_mentioned*Mexican territory*/location_mentioned* and in looking upon
the face of the nation nothing was to be seen but confusion and
bloody discord—Brother contending with brother in deadly strife
for mastery in political power. They saw that the constitution of
the *location_mentioned*republic*/location_mentioned*, that instrument which they had been taught to look
upon as the sacred charter of their liberties was alternately 
violated and set aside by all parties, and that all the constitutional 
guarantees were merged for the time being in military power. They saw
the constitutional period for the election of *person_mentioned*President */person_mentioned*and *person_mentioned*vice
President of the *location_mentioned*nation*/location_mentioned**/person_mentioned* and of *person_mentioned*members of Congress*/person_mentioned*, pass by, and at
least *location_mentioned*one third of the states*/location_mentioned* refuse or neglect to hold the elections.
The future presented the gloomy prospect that the days of 
constitutional freedom had been numbered to the *person_mentioned*Mexicans*/person_mentioned*, and that we
should ere long see the waves of anarchy and confusion close forever
over the wreck of that *location_mentioned*Mexican republic*/location_mentioned*. The disorganization of the
government was so extreem, that even the *person_mentioned*leaders of the liberal party
*/person_mentioned*who have been contending for the restoration of constitutional
liberty, and whose cause was espoused by the *person_mentioned*people of *location_mentioned*Texas*/location_mentioned**/person_mentioned*, and
generously defended with their blood and treasure, found themselves
conpelled to lay aside all the established forms, and to renovate the
constitution by violent and unconstitutional means.*/p*

*p*The *person_mentioned*committee */person_mentioned*turned from this view of our national affairs to
that of the local internal situation of *location_mentioned*Texas */location_mentioned*which has not materially
changed since the last convention. The political system under which
*location_mentioned*Texas */location_mentioned*has heretofore been governed, tends to check the growth of
the *location_mentioned*country*/location_mentioned*, and to produce confusion and insecurity, rather than
to extend protection to lives liberty and property. The unnatural
annexation of what was formerly the*location_mentioned* province of Texas*/location_mentioned* to *location_mentioned*Coahuila*/location_mentioned*
by the constituent *person_mentioned*congress of the *location_mentioned*Mexican nation*/location_mentioned**/person_mentioned*, has forced upon
the *person_mentioned*people of *location_mentioned*Texas*/location_mentioned**/person_mentioned* a system of laws which they do not understand
and which cannot be administered so as to suit their condition or
to supply their wants.*/p*

*p*The *person_mentioned*Alcaldes */person_mentioned*who are the highest *person_mentioned*judicial officers in *location_mentioned*Texas*/location_mentioned**/person_mentioned* and
have unlimited jurisdiction in all cases, are elected annually by the
people, and those who are ignorant and corrupt and without re-<barker_pb n="938"/>
sponsibiliiy are as liable to be chosen as the wise, the virtuous and
the responsible. This remark is justified by the fact that the office
is without emolument and is extreemly burdensome, and will 
therefore seldom be sought by those who are best qualified to fill it. In
all civil cases there is an appeal to the *person_mentioned*supreme tribunal of the
state at *location_mentioned*Saltillo*/location_mentioned**/person_mentioned* a distance of near seven hundred miles from the
inhabited parts of *location_mentioned*Texas*/location_mentioned*. There are but few *person_mentioned*men */person_mentioned*in *location_mentioned*Texas */location_mentioned*who are
qualified to prepare cases for the *person_mentioned*supreme court*/person_mentioned* and when appeals
have been taken they have generally been sent back several times to
be reformed so that decissions in such cases are seldom had. It has
become proverbial in *location_mentioned*Texas*/location_mentioned*, that an appeal to *location_mentioned*Saltillo */location_mentioned*is a payment
of the debt. It amounts to a total denial of justice especially to the
poor, and this is the frail tenure by which the most important rights
of the *person_mentioned*people of *location_mentioned*Texas */location_mentioned**/person_mentioned*are suspended.*/p*

*p*The manner of trying *person_mentioned*culprits */person_mentioned*for high criminal offences is such
that it amounts to no tryal at all. The tryal by *person_mentioned*jury */person_mentioned*is not sanctioned
by law, and the rights of the accused are committed to an *person_mentioned*alcalde*/person_mentioned*
who is ignorant of the formulas of the laws, and of the language in
which they are written who prepares the cause for the judgment
of the *person_mentioned*supreme tribunal in *location_mentioned*Saltillo*/location_mentioned**/person_mentioned*, thus the lives, liberty and honor
of the *person_mentioned*accused */person_mentioned*are suspended upon the tardy decission of a distant
*person_mentioned*tribunal */person_mentioned*which knows not nor cares not for his suffering, and the
rights of the *location_mentioned*community */location_mentioned*to bring *person_mentioned*offenders */person_mentioned*to speedy and exemplary
punishment are sacrificed to forms equally uncertain and unknown.
The formula required by law in the prosecution of *person_mentioned*criminals */person_mentioned*is so
difficult to be pursued that most of the *location_mentioned*courts in Texas*/location_mentioned* have long
since ceased to attempt its execution. The tryal by *person_mentioned*jury */person_mentioned*has been
attempted in some of the *location_mentioned*municipalities*/location_mentioned*, but being unsupported by the
sanction of law it also has failed of success. A total interegnum in
the administration of justice in criminal cases may be said to exist.
A total disregard of the laws has become so prevalent, both amongst
the *person_mentioned*officers of justice*/person_mentioned*, and the *person_mentioned*people */person_mentioned*at large, that reverence for laws
or for those who administer them has almost intirely disappeared
and contempt is fast assuming its place, so that the protection of
our property- our persons and lives is circumscribed almost 
exclusively to the moral honesty or virtue of our neighbor.*/p*

*p*The people and *person_mentioned*authorities of *location_mentioned*Bexar*/location_mentioned**/person_mentioned* in their representation in
*date_mentioned n="12-xx-1832">December last*/date_mentioned* speaking of the judiciary system in *location_mentioned*Texas */location_mentioned*use the 
following strong and conclusive language.*/p*

*p*"In the judiciary department there never has been any adequate
organization and it may be said with just cause that in this 
department there is not and never has been any government in *location_mentioned*Texas*/location_mentioned*."*/p*

*p*Besides the evils which menace *location_mentioned*Texas */location_mentioned*for the want of a judiciary
there are others of no less appalling effects. This *location_mentioned*country */location_mentioned*is in
danger of being inundated by bands of *person_mentioned*northern Indians*/person_mentioned* who are<barker_pb n="939"/>
removing from the *location_mentioned*east side of the Mississippi*/location_mentioned* to *location_mentioned*Arkansas */location_mentioned*on our
*location_mentioned*borders*/location_mentioned*. Also the *person_mentioned*Comanche*/person_mentioned*, *person_mentioned*Tahuacana */person_mentioned*and other tribes of *person_mentioned*native
Texas indians*/person_mentioned* have recently become hostile and are committing
depredations on the *location_mentioned*frontiers*/location_mentioned*. But [it] is unnecessary to enter into
details—enough is said in the representation of *location_mentioned*Bexar */location_mentioned*by the 
declaration that there is not and never has been any adequate govt in
*location_mentioned*Texas*/location_mentioned*.*/p*

*p*Judging from the past, it must be considered a vain hope to look
to the *person_mentioned*State government of *location_mentioned*Coahuila and Texas*/location_mentioned**/person_mentioned* for a redress of
grievances, or a remedy of wrongs. We have twice beheld the 
mortifying spectacle of the *person_mentioned*corrupt mob of the Capital*/person_mentioned* driving the 
*person_mentioned*legislature */person_mentioned*by force to adopt measures, unconstitutional in themselves,
insulting to the *person_mentioned*inhabitants of *location_mentioned*Texas*/location_mentioned**/person_mentioned*, and disregardful of their
rights, The general neglect of the *person_mentioned*state Legislature*/person_mentioned* of all the 
important interests and rights of *location_mentioned*Texas */location_mentioned*and their repeated violations
of the constitution are very clearly and energetically set forth in
the *location_mentioned*Bexar */location_mentioned*remonstrance of *date_mentioned n="12-xx-1832">last December*/date_mentioned*. There seems to be no
cause to expect any favourable change towards *location_mentioned*Texas */location_mentioned*in the 
politics of *location_mentioned*Coahuila*/location_mentioned*. But even supposing there were the *person_mentioned*legislature*/person_mentioned*
that would suit *location_mentioned*Coahuila */location_mentioned*would be pernicious in *location_mentioned*Texas*/location_mentioned*. No 
organization can be devised under the constitution of the *location_mentioned*State of Coahuila
and Texas*/location_mentioned* that would suit the two extremes, separated as they are
more than 400 leagues, a great part through a *location_mentioned*wilderness */location_mentioned*that cannot
be passed without imminent danger from hostile *person_mentioned*indians*/person_mentioned*, The 
dissimilarity of habits occupation and language also present still greater
difficulties than the distance. These difficulties are hard to 
reconcile for the reason that the state constitution requires that all 
general laws shall be the same throughout the whole state, There cannot
therefore be any organization of the judiciary for *location_mentioned*Texas */location_mentioned*materially
different from that of *location_mentioned*Coahuila*/location_mentioned*.*/p*

*p*In this state of things the *person_mentioned*committee */person_mentioned*considered themselves bound
by a solemn duty to call on the *person_mentioned*people of *location_mentioned*Texas*/location_mentioned**/person_mentioned* through their 
*person_mentioned*representatives */person_mentioned*to meet in general convention with full powers to 
deliberate on the present distracted situation of our infant *location_mentioned*country */location_mentioned*and to
adopt such constitutional measures as in their wisdom they may
deem necessary In exercising this highly responsible duty the 
*person_mentioned*committee */person_mentioned*did not act unadvisedly or without the most mature 
deliberation, and they did not call this convention untill they were satisfied
that a large majority of the*person_mentioned* people of *location_mentioned*Texas*/location_mentioned**/person_mentioned* were in favor of 
applying for a well organized state Govt as the only remedy for existing
evils.*/p*

*p*The law of the constituent *person_mentioned*Congress */person_mentioned*of*date_mentioned n="05-07-1824"> 7 May 1824*/date_mentioned* evidently
contemplates that *location_mentioned*Texas */location_mentioned*should form a *location_mentioned*separate State*/location_mentioned* The 2d
article of that law is in the following words as translated " *location_mentioned*Coahuila
and Texas*/location_mentioned* shall also form another state, but so soon as the latter is<barker_pb n="940"/>
in a situation to figure as a *location_mentioned*separate state*/location_mentioned*, it shall inform *person_mentioned*congress*/person_mentioned*
thereof for its resolution."*/p*

*p*The right which this law confers upon the *person_mentioned*people of *location_mentioned*Texas*/location_mentioned**/person_mentioned* to
inform *person_mentioned*congress */person_mentioned*when they are in a situation to figure as a State,
and to apply for admission into the *location_mentioned*Union */location_mentioned*is certainly very clear and
unequivocal.*/p*

*p*What method may be the best to obtain a remedy for the many
evils which afflict *location_mentioned*Texas*/location_mentioned*, can only be determined by the wisdom of
the *person_mentioned*convention*/person_mentioned*. Trusting that your deliberations will be conducted
with that zeal for the public welfare which the common good of our
*location_mentioned*adopted country*/location_mentioned* requires and that they will tend to that happy issue
which all so confidently anticipate, the *person_mentioned*central committee*/person_mentioned* take leave
of the convention by depositing the power which they have exercised
for a time in the hands of those who gave it.*/p*


*/div1*
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
