
<TEI.2 id="APB4636">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>05-10-1834</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1922: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1928), 3 vols., Vol 2, pp. 1049-1055</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Stephen F Austin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>James F Perry</document_recipient>
<document_title>Stephen F Austin to James F Perry, 05-10-1834</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Mexico</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Austin to James F. Perry, May 10, 1834. Describing prison and his imprisonment incomunicado.   Observations on his past policy in Texas.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes>Biographical sketch in Bancroft, History of Mexico, IV, 451.
For Almonte's mission to Texas, see Barker, The Life of Stephen F. Austin, 462-466.</barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1049-1055</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>12-03-2010</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>


<text id="APB4636T">

<body>
*div1 type="summary"*
*p*Austin to James F. Perry, May 10, 1834. Describing prison and his imprisonment incomunicado.   Observations on his past policy in Texas.*/p*
*/div1*

*div1 type="body"*

*p**location_mentioned*Ex-inquisicion*/location_mentioned* *location_mentioned*Mexico */location_mentioned**date_mentioned n="05-10-1834">May 10th 1834*/date_mentioned**/p*
*p*Dr *person_mentioned*Brother*/person_mentioned*.*/p*

*p*I improve the first moment that I could write to you since I
arrived here which was on the *date_mentioned n="02-13-1834">13 Feby—*/date_mentioned*on that day I was locked
up in one of the *location_mentioned*dungeons */location_mentioned*of this vast building <hi rend="italic">incomunicado</hi>, that
is I was not allowed to speak to, or communicate with any person
whatever except the *person_mentioned*officer of the guard*/person_mentioned*. I remained in this 
situation untill *date_mentioned n="05-09-1834">yesterday */date_mentioned*when I was permitted to communicate with
persons outside, receive books, writing materials, visits etc and to
mix with the other *person_mentioned*prisoners*/person_mentioned*—there are about 60 of them, all *person_mentioned*officers*/person_mentioned*<barker_pb n="1050"/>
except two *person_mentioned*clergymen (Padres)*/person_mentioned* and all men of good *person_mentioned*families */person_mentioned*and
respectability confined for political opinions in the revolution of the
past year. The occupant of my *location_mentioned*dungeon */location_mentioned*before me was a *person_mentioned*Col*/person_mentioned*. who
was banished. *person_mentioned*General Bustamante former vice-President*/person_mentioned* occupied
one in *date_mentioned n="07-xx-1833">July */date_mentioned*and *date_mentioned n="08-xx-1833">August */date_mentioned*last near mine, as I am informed*/p*.

*p*You may have some curiosity to know how I am lodged and
what sort of a place an *location_mentioned*inquisición prison*/location_mentioned* is, about which so many
horrid things are said all over the *location_mentioned*world*/location_mentioned*, and which are no doubt
true and probably much worse.*/p*

*p*My *location_mentioned*room */location_mentioned*is about 16 feet by 13—very high ceiling—two doors,
one flush with the outside surface of the wall, the other near the
inside surface and within the wall which is about 3 feet thick of
large hewn stone—the latter door has an oblong hole large enough
to admit a plate—the other is solid, both were always locked and
bolted untill *date_mentioned n="05-09-1834">yesterday*/date_mentioned*—no windows—a very small sky-light in the
roof which barely afforded light to read on very clear days when
the sun was high, say from 10 to 3 o'clock—quite free from damp
except such as would naturally result from the want of a free 
circulation of air. There are 19 similar *location_mentioned*dungeons */location_mentioned*in this range with
the difference that some of them are a little larger than mine, tho
most are the same size—they are *location_mentioned*in the interior of this extensive
building*/location_mentioned* and the doors open into an oblong*location_mentioned* <hi rend="italic">patio </hi>*/location_mentioned*or open court
about 120 by 60 feet which has a varanda or gallery all round
it supported by pillars and arches—a fountain of good water from
the acqueduct in the centre. This part of the building is one story
but is surrounded on every side by other parts of the same building
that are two stories and present a solid wall above our range without
windows that look into this patio. On two sides of the base of
the two story wall before mentioned there are *location_mentioned*<hi rend="italic">solederos </hi>or sunning
places*/location_mentioned* which are spaces about 14 feet square (one is much larger)
ranged along the back of the *location_mentioned*dungeons */location_mentioned*and between them and the
before mentioned two story wall—they are separated from each other
by high walls—each has a door, locks etc—open above for the sun—
they communicate with the patio by arched passages*/p*.

*p*When I came in each *location_mentioned*dungeon */location_mentioned*had its occupant and all were
<hi rend="italic">incomunicado </hi>the same as myself. All the doors were locked and
bolted no one came into the *location_mentioned*patio */location_mentioned*except the *person_mentioned*sentinel*/person_mentioned*—all was silent-
each one was taken out about two hours the middle of the day and
put into one of the *location_mentioned*solederos */location_mentioned*or sunning places, alone and locked in.
In time of the inquisición the *person_mentioned*prisoners */person_mentioned*were covered with a kind of
sack or over garment with a mask at the top to cover the head and
face, so that they could not be known, even by the guard in going
through the *location_mentioned*patio */location_mentioned*to and from the *location_mentioned*solederos*/location_mentioned*, nothing of the kind
was done with us, we saw each other but could not salute or speak.<barker_pb n="1051"/>
I am told that in the time of the inquisición there were four other
*location_mentioned*patios */location_mentioned*or open courts that belonged to the part of the building that
was used as a *location_mentioned*prison*/location_mentioned*—they formerly communicated with each other
by obscure passages which are now closed. The entrance into each
from the street was always separate as they still are so that if the
*person_mentioned*friend of a prisoner*/person_mentioned* saw him enter one of the outside doors, he could
not from that circumstance form any idea of the *location_mentioned*<hi rend="italic">patio </hi>*/location_mentioned*or part of
the building where he was confined. The *location_mentioned*<hi rend="italic">patio </hi>*/location_mentioned*I am in 
communicates with the street by a narrow dark passage about 150 feet long.*/p*

*p**person_mentioned*Padre Servando Mier*/person_mentioned* a very distinguished *person_mentioned*patriot */person_mentioned*was confined
in the same *location_mentioned*dungeon */location_mentioned*I am in by the *person_mentioned*tribunal of the inquisición*/person_mentioned* in
its time, and also by the *person_mentioned*emperor Iturbide*/person_mentioned*. I visited him here in
this room in *date_mentioned n="10-xx-1822">October 1822*/date_mentioned*, he was a *person_mentioned*member of congress*/person_mentioned* and was
arrested the *date_mentioned n="08-20-1822">20 of August*/date_mentioned* with *person_mentioned*14 other members*/person_mentioned*. *person_mentioned*General Morelos
*/person_mentioned*the most distinguished of the *person_mentioned*generals */person_mentioned*in the beginning of the
revolution, was confined in a *location_mentioned*dungeon */location_mentioned*near mine in this range from
which he was taken to be shot. In short each of these *location_mentioned*dungeons */location_mentioned*has
some tradition of the sufferings of some *person_mentioned*victim of the inquisición
*/person_mentioned*or of the revolution. Since the Independence this building has been
used as a *location_mentioned*prison */location_mentioned*for political opinions or offences—no one accused
of felonious crimes is confined here.    The *person_mentioned*prisoners */person_mentioned*are well treated.*/p*

*p*The *date_mentioned n="04-01-1834">first of April*/date_mentioned* all the *person_mentioned*prisoners */person_mentioned*were put in communication
except myself and four others we remained shut up untill 
*date_mentioned n="05-09-1834">yesterday*/date_mentioned*—our doors are now open from sun rise to 9 o'clock at night—
we have the free use of the *location_mentioned*<hi rend="italic">patio </hi>*/location_mentioned*and can visit another extensive
range of *location_mentioned*dungeons */location_mentioned*in the 2d story of the main building which 
communicates with this patio by a dark passage and much darker stone
staircase. From this range there is a passage onto the *location_mentioned*<hi rend="italic">asotea </hi>or
roof of our range of dungeons*/location_mentioned* which is flat so that we can walk over
our *location_mentioned*dungeons */location_mentioned*and all around our patio and have sufficient room for
exercise I was shewn a *location_mentioned*dungeon */location_mentioned*in the 2d story where a man from
*location_mentioned*Guatamala */location_mentioned*was confined by the inquiscion 30 years he is now
living in a *location_mentioned*hospital */location_mentioned*of this city and has given some account of the
treatment of *person_mentioned*prisoners */person_mentioned*in those days of superstition and despotism*/p*

*p*I have received no personal ill treatment from any of the *person_mentioned*officers*/person_mentioned*
or *person_mentioned*guards */person_mentioned*who have had charge of me since my first arrest up to this
day I received such provisions as I needed them through the
guard—they were handed in at the hole in the inside door. When
I left *location_mentioned*Monterey */location_mentioned*the *person_mentioned*officer of the guard, Cap Manuel Barragan*/person_mentioned*, told
me that he would put no guard over me except my word that I would
not attempt to escape nor speak or write to any one without his
permission. I gave it of course, for I would have returned to *location_mentioned*Mexico*/location_mentioned*
on the simple order of the *person_mentioned*Govt*/person_mentioned*my conscience told me that I had<barker_pb n="1052"/>
committed no crime. I was imprudent in urging the claims of *location_mentioned*Texas*/location_mentioned*
that were confided to me as an *person_mentioned*agent */person_mentioned*with more determination and
obstenancy than was consistent with my personal security or 
wellfare, but nothing more. I accepted the agency with reluctance, but
in good faith and conformed to what I had every right to believe
was the general wish of the people so far as the convention expressed
that wish. Much good will result to *location_mentioned*Texas */location_mentioned*from my sufferings. The
*person_mentioned*state government*/person_mentioned* have been stimulated to apply proper remedies in
many things and some of those who would have ruined the country
and thrown it into confusion merely from personal feelings and low
mean jealousies towards me, are now satisfied and rejoicing and are
in favor of peace and quietness, because they think I am suffering-
others who were restless and dissatisfied with me and with every
thing without knowing why, are more calm and reasonable, and
others who were my *person_mentioned*enemies */person_mentioned*a year ago, have no doubt had the 
magninimity to do me justice— this conduct (if it be true as I am told it
is) will do them honor and be remembered to their advantage at some
future day when all personal feelings have passed away. My own
personal *person_mentioned*friends */person_mentioned*(and the mass of the honest and laboring *person_mentioned*farmers*/person_mentioned*
are so) have always been in favor of peace and quietness and opposed
to turbulence. They have no doubt blamed me for suffering violent
men to involve me as I have been. They have seen that I have 
permitted myself to be thrown into the mire by others whose sole object
was my ruin. I was unsuspicious and acted in good faith—the fact
is that when a few persons combine to ruin another who is 
unsuspicious and acts in good faith and with honest intentions, it is very
difficult for him to escape.*/p*

*p*Thus it is, that those who a year ago were the most anxious for a
state and the most turbulent, are now for peace—they have in fact
adopted my own principles which allways have been <hi rend="italic">peace quietness,
patience and submission to the laws and no revolutions.</hi> If I ever
wandered from those principles, it was because the public feeling
was so disordered and things were so disjointed that my opposition
would have increased the evils and in all probability caused a great
deal of confusion. I yielded from this motive, <hi rend="italic">and yielded in good
faith,</hi> and not to undermine or counteract. Thus my own principles
of peace and quietness are now predominant, when had I attempted
to have made them prevail by direct opposition to violent measures
the reverse would have been the case.*/p*

*p*It is very evident that *location_mentioned*Texas */location_mentioned*must become a state at some future
day and not very distant—all will be in favor of it— the attempt
that has been made was premature and totally wrong as to the
manner. The particular act that involved me in all this, was the
calling of the convention in my absence.   I yielded after my return.<barker_pb n="1053"/>
So far as I am to blame in agreeing to those measures I am ready
to be censured—they grew out of the situation of public feelings at
the time—it would have been worse than useless for me to have
opposed them—the only way I could have done it was to enter into
the thing in bad faith so as to defeat and counteract. Such a course
I did not think was correct or honorable— on my arrival here I
could have put the state question to sleep. If I had done so those
who now blame me for an excess of zeal would have been vociferous
on the opposite extreem. All those things are mere matters of
course—in short it is mankind. The only substantial matter in this
business that is worthy of consideration is <hi rend="italic">that much substantial
good will result to *location_mentioned*Texas */location_mentioned*from my sufferings</hi> and I am content—
as to office or public employ you know that I have always been averse
to it—I am more so now than ever— I am no *person_mentioned*office hunter*/person_mentioned* nor no
*person_mentioned*demagogue */person_mentioned*seeking popularity— I have tryed in good faith to do
all the good I could to everybody—as to *person_mentioned*enemies */person_mentioned*and *person_mentioned*friends*/person_mentioned*—
the common acceptation of those words amongst mankind in general
conveys to the mind the same idea of change, that the word <hi rend="italic">clouds</hi>
does— not so with true personal friends— of these I shall never
want. Such men for example as *person_mentioned*T. F. McKinney*/person_mentioned*. These are the
only kind of friends I wish for.*/p*

*p*I have no idea when I shall be at liberty. I think that all depends
on the report of *person_mentioned*Almonte */person_mentioned*who has been sent to *location_mentioned*Texas */location_mentioned*and I presume
is now there or on his way back. It is much in my favor that all
remains quiet in *location_mentioned*Texas */location_mentioned*I was confident that no *person_mentioned*friend */person_mentioned*of mine
would try to get up an excitement but I feared that my *person_mentioned*enemies*/person_mentioned*
would. Such a thing would have increased my difficulty, for I would
have been blamed for it all. My confinement has been very rigid
but I am in good health and have borne it with tolerable patience.
I had no books the first month, and it was solitary enough—after
that I prevailed on the *person_mentioned*sergeant */person_mentioned*to go to *person_mentioned*D. Victor Blanco*/person_mentioned* who sent
them—he and *person_mentioned*Padre Muldoon*/person_mentioned* have been firm and unwavering in
their friendship to me in all this business, so has *person_mentioned*Ramon Musquis*/person_mentioned*
and many others in *location_mentioned*Bexar */location_mentioned*who have written here in my favor I
have never complained of the *person_mentioned*Vice President Farias*/person_mentioned*—he has been
deceived—he has been made to believe, as I am told, that my object
was to separate *location_mentioned*Texas */location_mentioned*from *location_mentioned*Mexico */location_mentioned*and deliver it to the *location_mentioned*United
States of the north*/location_mentioned*, which is absolutely false and without the shadow
of foundation besides being a great absurdity. In a moment of
irritation I said to the *person_mentioned*vice President*/person_mentioned* that if the evils of *location_mentioned*Texas*/location_mentioned*
were not remedied the public there would remedy them of 
themselves—   this irritated him very much  and my difficulties com-<barker_pb n="1054"/>
menced. The truth is I lost patience and was imprudent and of
course to blame, for patience is necessary in such cases. I hope
that no friend of mine will blame the *person_mentioned*vice President*/person_mentioned* or complain
of him. I put on one side all considerations of personal safety or
consequences to myself and thought only of suffering *location_mentioned*Texas */location_mentioned*and
the fevered and excited situation of my constituents—had I erred
from a want of zeal or industry or dilligence in the discharges of
my duty as an *person_mentioned*agent*/person_mentioned*, all would have had cause to censure me and
my own conscience would have been the first to do it, for nothing
can be more sacred than a public agency. My conscience is at rest-
as an *person_mentioned*agent */person_mentioned*I did my duty, or, only erred from excess of zeal to
do it—good has resulted even from that error if it was one. I am
suffering but the evils of *location_mentioned*Texas */location_mentioned*are remedied— this idea consoles
me for my misfortunes and enables me to bear them firmly. 
Remember me to *person_mentioned*McKinney */person_mentioned*and show him this letter also *person_mentioned*H. Austin*/person_mentioned* and
if *person_mentioned*Mason */person_mentioned*and *person_mentioned*Hotchkiss */person_mentioned*are there remember me to them.*/p*

*p*Love to *person_mentioned*Emily */person_mentioned*and all the *person_mentioned*family*/person_mentioned**/p*

*p**person_mentioned*S. F. Austin*/person_mentioned**/p*

*p*N. B. I sent you two mineatures from *location_mentioned*Monterey */location_mentioned*by *person_mentioned*Mr. Powel*/person_mentioned*
which I hope you have recd. The small one was taken the 
beginning of *date_mentioned n="10-xx-1833">October */date_mentioned*when things were very unfavourable for *location_mentioned*Texas*/location_mentioned*
and I was not in a pleasant humour of course it therefore has
rather a cross or frowning look—the other that is the large one
was taken in *date_mentioned n="11-xx-1833">November */date_mentioned*when all was right. *person_mentioned*Mr Howard*/person_mentioned* who
painted them has gone to *location_mentioned*Texas */location_mentioned*and I recommend him to you
very particularly as a good *person_mentioned*artist */person_mentioned*and a very good worthy young
man. If *person_mentioned*Hotchkiss */person_mentioned*is in *location_mentioned*Texas */location_mentioned*remember me to him very 
particularly-—he is an honorable and high minded man—his friendship
is valuable for he has no deception—he will no doubt blame me
very much for writing the letter of *date_mentioned n="10-02-1833">2d of October*/date_mentioned* don't mind
that—I blame myself because it was the imprudent act of an 
excited impatient moment. If I find that I am to be detained here
long, I will send you a power of attorney to sell any of my 
property you think proper and make titles. I send you an extra-judicial
power under which you can act if you think proper—-deeds may
be wanted for the *location_mentioned*Brazoria */location_mentioned*lots and perhaps you may do some
thing with *location_mentioned*the place at the mouth of the river west side*/location_mentioned*. Do as
you please with anything of mine and try and have a room for
me at your *location_mentioned*house*/location_mentioned*.*/p*

*p**person_mentioned*S. F. Austin*/person_mentioned**/p*

*p**date_mentioned n="05-10-1834">May 10 1834*/date_mentioned**/p*
*p**person_mentioned*Mr James F. Perry*/person_mentioned**/p*

*p*I know nothing about the political situation of the *location_mentioned*country */location_mentioned*but
am told  it is very unsettled—some  say worse than  it has  ever<barker_pb n="1055"/>
been—party spirit is more bitter and vindicative—some think there
will be another civil war worse than any of the others. These
are the rumors which reach us in the *location_mentioned*Patio */location_mentioned*whether true or false
God knows*/p*

*p**person_mentioned*S. F. A.*/person_mentioned**/p*

*/div1*
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
