
<TEI.2 id="APB4123">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>01-04-1831</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1922: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1928), 3 vols., Vol 2, pp. 572-574</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>John A Williams</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Stephen F Austin</document_recipient>
<document_title>John A Williams to Stephen F Austin, 01-04-1831</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>District of Atascosito, Texas</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>John A. Williams to Austin, January 4, 1831. Reviewing political status of
the Sabine border and suggesting form of local government—especially courts—that should be established.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes>These East Texas settlers had drifted in without permit from the government and
settled outside any empressario's grant. The arrest of Padilla, the general land commissioner, at Nacogdoches in the summer of 1830 prevented at that time the extension of titles to their lands. They had a de facto political organization, each community
electing an " alcalde" subject to the ayuntamiento of Nacogdoches,</barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 572-574</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>09-03-2010</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>


<text id="APB4123T">

<body>
*div1 type="summary"*
*p*John A. Williams to Austin, January 4, 1831. Reviewing political status of the Sabine border and suggesting form of local government—especially courts—that should be established.*/p*
*/div1*

*div1 type="body"*

*p**location_mentioned*District of Atascosito. Texas*/location_mentioned* *date_mentioned n="01-04-1831">4th January 1831*/date_mentioned**/p*
*p**person_mentioned*Col S. F. Austin*/person_mentioned**/p*

*p*Dear Sir In conformity with my promise I have endeavoured to
learn from the *person_mentioned*people */person_mentioned*the public opinion as to the best mode of
organizing the *person_mentioned*local government of this *location_mentioned*district*/location_mentioned**/person_mentioned*, no public metting
has been had, but I have conversed with a number of persons whose
opinions are entitled to respect Messrs. *person_mentioned*George Orr*/person_mentioned*, *person_mentioned*Baker McSpinks,
our former Alcalde*/person_mentioned*, and *person_mentioned*Wm Milspaugh the present Alcalde */person_mentioned*are
among those I have consulted They were made acquainted with
the object of your address of the *date_mentioned n="11-17-1830">17th Novbr last*/date_mentioned*, and All concured
in the course there suggested*/p*

*p*If, for the last seven years, the *person_mentioned*people of this *location_mentioned*dist*/location_mentioned**/person_mentioned*, have 
governed themselves in a peaceful and harmonious manner without
courts legally established, without the enjoyment of the rights of
citizenship and almost without law, yet obedient to law when
known.    Is this not conclusive evidence that they are justly en-<barker_pb n="573"/>
titled to the previledges enjoyed by other *person_mentioned*foreigners */person_mentioned*settled in this
*location_mentioned*province*/location_mentioned*? For some years the *person_mentioned*strangers */person_mentioned*residing in more favoured
parts of the *location_mentioned*State */location_mentioned*have had their *location_mentioned*courts */location_mentioned*legally constituted by which
their judicial procedings were entitled to respect, they have been
made the rightful *person_mentioned*proprietors */person_mentioned*of the soil they cultivate, they exercize
the right of suffrage at elections, and have *person_mentioned*representatives */person_mentioned*in the
*person_mentioned*legislative counsels*/person_mentioned* of the *location_mentioned*Nation*/location_mentioned*. In a word they enjoy all the
civil rights which the Municiple laws of this nation permit to be
exerised by *person_mentioned*foreigners*/person_mentioned*.   But not so with us.*/p*

*p*Our judicial procedings altho just, yet they are arbitrary, and
that from necessaty. Although we cultivate the soil, yet we are at
will. Although our civil rights have been suspended since the
day we first set our feet on the soil of *location_mentioned*Mexico*/location_mentioned*, yet we have been
faithful to her political institutions Always ready to defend her
cause when defence was necessary, and obedient to her laws when
her laws were made known.*/p*

*p*These are incontrovertable facts known to your self and also
to many worthy *person_mentioned*Mexicans */person_mentioned*who have traveled among us. But we
complain not nor attribute our misfortune to any willful neglect on
the part of the Govt, but solely consider it the result of unforeseen,
and therefore unavoidable accidents.*/p*

*p*If I had not considered myself authorised by your favor of
the *date_mentioned n="11-17-1830">17th of Novbr*/date_mentioned*. to communicate with you on the subject of the
organization of the *person_mentioned*local government*/person_mentioned* of *location_mentioned*Trinity */location_mentioned*and *location_mentioned*Naches*/location_mentioned*. I
should have been totally silent, but conceiving the correspondence
already opened and that by one of the *person_mentioned*constitutional 
representatives of the people*/person_mentioned*, I consider myself under the greatest obligations
for the honour you have thought fit to confer by asking my opi[ni]on
on the subject now alluded to, and should consider myself liable
to great reproach if I should refuse to answer fully and freely on a
subject of such vital importance to the political existence of this
*location_mentioned*dist*/location_mentioned*.*/p*

*p*I would therefore, with due respect, suggest the following mode
of organization for this*location_mentioned* section of country*/location_mentioned*.*/p*

*p*Let there be a court of equal grade, power, and authority, with
those of other *location_mentioned*jurisdictions */location_mentioned*of the state, legally established. If
other *location_mentioned*courts */location_mentioned*or *person_mentioned*Ayuentamentos */person_mentioned*possess the power of framing police
regulations let this possess the same but this kind of power should
be but sparingly given to any *location_mentioned*court */location_mentioned*for there is always danger
where legislative and judicial powers are vested in the same hands,
and the power of passing police laws is clearly a legislative power
so far as it extends*/p*

*p*The limits of this *location_mentioned*jurisdiction */location_mentioned*should include the *location_mentioned*teritory */location_mentioned*bounded
by the following lines (To wit)*location_mentioned* begining at the mouth of the sabine
River thence runing up the same to the dividing ground between<barker_pb n="574"/>
Cow bayou settlement and Bevells settlement including the former
settlement thenee to the Trinity river below the quosliaío Villedge
including the Jiaches settlement and ail the anierican and Mexican
families on the Trinity nelow the quoshato Viliedge, thence from
immediately below said Viliedge flue west to the Langes into your
eastern country here, thence down the Sangeslnto to its mouth thence
along the eastern line of your colony to the gulf, thence along the
margin of the gulf to the begining The Maches and Cow bayou
bettlements have hitherto been considered  part of this dist.*/location_mentioned* and
held amenable to our courts and voted at our elections, If it shoul
be said this *location_mentioned*teritory */location_mentioned*is too large to form one *location_mentioned*jurisdiction */location_mentioned*I answer,
it is thinly inhabited except on *location_mentioned*Trinity */location_mentioned*and that to appoint 
*person_mentioned*Ayuntamientos */person_mentioned*in every *location_mentioned*settlement */location_mentioned*of ten or fifteen *person_mentioned*families */person_mentioned*would be 
absurd, and further, that when the population becomes more dense it
will be time enough to form new courts.*/p*

*p*As to the place of holding *location_mentioned*courts*/location_mentioned*, At *location_mentioned*Perries point*/location_mentioned* *location_mentioned*one Mile distant
from the mouth of Trinity*/location_mentioned* a *location_mentioned*Town */location_mentioned*has lately been laid out, by *person_mentioned*Col.
Bradburn*/person_mentioned* of the *person_mentioned*Mexican -Army*/person_mentioned* his detachment is stationed there
and making rapid improvements A number of *person_mentioned*american families
*/person_mentioned*will settle in that place so soon as they can procure lots and 1 am
informed by *person_mentioned*Col Bradburn*/person_mentioned* that a quantity of*person_mentioned* Mexican families*/person_mentioned* have
or soon will embark for the purpose of settleing there, I am 
therefore induced to believe it will soon be a place oí considerable 
commercial importance. Would it not, therefore be better to fix the
*location_mentioned*Seat of Justice*/location_mentioned* at *location_mentioned*Perries point*/location_mentioned* ?*/p*

*p*If the plan of organization here suggisted should meet your 
approbation together with those who will have to decide its fate, the *location_mentioned*state*/location_mentioned*
will never lament the act, for stern necessity requires that there
should be some legal tribunal within the reach of every member of
society by which every real, or imaginary wrong might have its
remedy and every ex[ist]ing difficulty adjusted.*/p*

*p*Whether we may be so fortunate as to succeed in this application,
or not, you Will please to have the goodness to inform us of the
result as soon as practicable and if successful some provision should
be made for organizing the court as soon as posible, and ought not
(in my humble opinion) to be delayed until the time of the anual
election of *person_mentioned*Alcaldes*/person_mentioned*.   *person_mentioned*Jno A. Williams */person_mentioned*   [Rubric]*/p*


*/div1*
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
