
<TEI.2 id="APB4031">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>09-22-1830</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1922: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1928), 3 vols., Vol 2, pp. 493-497</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Stephen F Austin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>James F Perry</document_recipient>
<document_title>Stephen F Austin to James F Perry, 09-22-1830</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>San Felipe de Austin, Texas</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Austin to James F. Perry, September 22, 1830. Much biographical matter. Conditions in Texas.   Land matters.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes></barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 493-497</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>08-27-2010</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>


<text id="APB4031T">

<body>
*div1 type="summary"*
*p*Austin to James F. Perry, September 22, 1830. Much biographical matter. Conditions in Texas.   Land matters.*/p*
*/div1*

*div1 type="body"*


*p**location_mentioned*San Felipe de Austin*/location_mentioned* *date_mentioned n="09-22-1830">Sept 22 1830*/date_mentioned**/p*
*p*Dr *person_mentioned*Brother*/person_mentioned**/p*

*p*I have just got your letter of *date_mentioned n="07-18-1830">July 18*/date_mentioned* and am truly glad that you
had so quick a trip *location_mentioned*home */location_mentioned*and found all well with the addition of
another *person_mentioned*son*/person_mentioned*— I was surprised that you thought me silent and 
reserved—it was what I never dreamed of-— I told you the *location_mentioned*grant */location_mentioned*was
in *person_mentioned*your and Emilys name jointly*/person_mentioned*— however I hope it is enough
for me to say that if I appear reserved exteriourly I was not so in
heart, and I will here apprise you and *person_mentioned*Emily */person_mentioned*of a change which
time care and something like disgust towards the *location_mentioned*world */location_mentioned*and human
affairs, has wrought upon my disposition I find from your letter
that I ought to have done it the first day we met—- I have for the
last few years been gradually loosing my taste for society, or for
conversation— I am getting tactiturn, or what may be called absent
minded— Silence is more agreeable to me than talking or noise—
this thing is becoming habitual and in spite of myself it is growing
upon me very rapidly— I therefore apprise you both that if you
move here, you must not expect to find me the cheerful companion
I once was,— if you wish to know any thing from me, you must
ask the question direct, if I answer, <hi rend="italic">yes</hi>, or <hi rend="italic">no</hi>, and say no more,
which may often be the case, you must not think that it proceeds
from coolness on my part*/p*

*p*I expect *person_mentioned*Henry Austin*/person_mentioned* here *date_mentioned n="09-23-1830">tomorrow*/date_mentioned*, he has arrived in the
*location_mentioned*Brasos */location_mentioned*with his boat, and on the first interview with him I shall<barker_pb n="494"/>
tell him of this part of my habits so that he may not be misled as you
were, and think I am cool because I am not a great talker; dismiss
that impression from your mind for ever I pray you I told you
the *location_mentioned*grant */location_mentioned*was in *person_mentioned*your and Emilys name jointly*/person_mentioned* — that was in fact
saying all that could have been said on the subject by a days talking,
and so far from casting any reflection on you as to *person_mentioned*Bryans children*/person_mentioned*
I felt gratefull for the care you had taken of them and was truly
gratified that it was in my power to aid you in providing for them
by means of this *location_mentioned*grant*/location_mentioned*, and besides this it was necessary to state in
the petition for the land that there were two *person_mentioned*families */person_mentioned*to be provided
for in order to give a sufficient reason for asking for such a quantity
as *location_mentioned*Eleven Leagues*/location_mentioned*, without this it would not have been granted—.
I hope this is sufficient on this point and that your mind will be at
rest and never again think that I am silent or cool towards you for
I again assure you there is nothing of that, in my heart, nothing—*/p*

*p*I am as I was when you were here litterally overwhelmed with
perplexities worse if possible than when you left I have no prospect
of much quiet for the future, nor of being able to enjoy much of
your society even if you move, at least for two years, for I was
elected on the *date_mentioned n="09-05-1830">5 of this month*/date_mentioned* *person_mentioned*a member of the Legislature of this
State*/person_mentioned* for the *date_mentioned n="01-01-1831  -  01-01-1833">two years from the 1 of Jany next*/date_mentioned* and must leave here
in *date_mentioned n="12-xx-1830">Decr */date_mentioned*for *location_mentioned*Saltillo */location_mentioned*where I shall probably be detaind one year and
perhaps longer—*date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1821"> nine years ago*/date_mentioned* I inlisted my self as the *person_mentioned*slave */person_mentioned*of
this *location_mentioned*colony*/location_mentioned*, and there is no remedy now, for I am bound in honor
and duty to labor for it untill its affairs are finally done Our
affairs with Govt, are on a much better footing than when you left
here and are getting better—tho on that point changes are frequent.
Now as to your removal—I have no *location_mentioned*house */location_mentioned*up nor under way—I made
an arrangement with *person_mentioned*Morton */person_mentioned*to build one he was taken sick and 
disappointed me— The *location_mentioned*Steam Mill*/location_mentioned* did not get under way as soon as
was expected and has broken several times and done but little— I
am now contracting with a *person_mentioned*carpenter */person_mentioned*to put up a *location_mentioned*frame store*/location_mentioned* in this
place and will try and have it ready by the time *person_mentioned*Hunter */person_mentioned*arrives—*/p*

*p*From what you say I do not expect the *person_mentioned*family */person_mentioned*untill *date_mentioned n="Fall - 1831">next fall—*/date_mentioned*
It will be hazarding too much to come in the *date_mentioned n="Spring - 1831">Spring */date_mentioned*and besides 
perhaps you can come on during the *date_mentioned n="Spring - 1831">spring */date_mentioned*or *date_mentioned n="Summer - 1831">summer */date_mentioned*yourself and
have a place provided for them to suit yourself—*/p*

*p*There is much difficulty with *person_mentioned*Edwards */person_mentioned*about the *location_mentioned*place at the
point*/location_mentioned* and I know not as yet how to settle it without much bad feeling
of an unpleasant nature, and your delay in removing will make the
thing much worse— that *location_mentioned*place */location_mentioned*is of no value except as a pleasant
situation— land of more value can be had— I will do the best I
can— The titles are not yet finished because *person_mentioned*Padilla */person_mentioned*still is in 
confinement and no new *person_mentioned*Commissioner */person_mentioned*has been appointed—   I now say<barker_pb n="495"/>
to you once for all that any place which I have you may have for a
residence or farm or what you please—the place where I originally
intended to settle all my *person_mentioned*family */person_mentioned*is at *location_mentioned*peach point*/location_mentioned* *location_mentioned*below Brasoria,
on the Sea Shore prairie at the edge of the timber 6 miles from the
sea beach—*/location_mentioned* Every body says it is the best land and the best situation
in the *location_mentioned*colony*/location_mentioned*— It is my first choice for a *location_mentioned*residence*/location_mentioned*, and on 
*location_mentioned*Chocolate Bayou*/location_mentioned* is my second choice— I need you here to take care of my
pecuniary affairs— unless I have some one to manage them for me
I shall be as poor as a church mouse as long as I live, but you must
consult your own feelings and your own wishes and act for yourself.
If you come here, all that I can do shall be done. I am expecting
instructions as to the introduction of *person_mentioned*negros*/person_mentioned*, and as I have now no
hope of seeing you *date_mentioned n="Fall - 1830">this fall*/date_mentioned* there will be time enough to send them
to you before I leave here for *location_mentioned*Saltillo*/location_mentioned*.*/p*

*p*My confidence in the ultimate rise and prosperity of this *location_mentioned*country*/location_mentioned*
is in no degree impared, it must prosper in the end— I have recd
by the last mail the most friendly and satisfactory letters from
*person_mentioned*Mr. Lucas Alamán the minister of state*/person_mentioned*, and from the *person_mentioned*vice President
Bustamante*/person_mentioned*, and from *person_mentioned*Genl. Teran*/person_mentioned*, they all say to me that this
*location_mentioned*colony */location_mentioned*will be fully protected and encouraged by the Govt, and
their confidence in me and in this *location_mentioned*colony */location_mentioned*is full and unimpaired and
that they always have had confidence in me and the *location_mentioned*colony */location_mentioned*etc.
these assurances are very flattering, and I think them sincere— My
election to the *location_mentioned*legislature */location_mentioned*will also place me on still higher ground,
tho I think it very probable that some change may take place as
to our *person_mentioned*local government*/person_mentioned* *location_mentioned*Texas */location_mentioned*does not suit to be united with
*location_mentioned*Coahuila*/location_mentioned*— But I am running into the all absorbing subject of
public affairs, and general interests a thing which has always
occupied so much of my time that I have neglected my own private
affairs in toto, and I fear will always neglect them unless you
are here to manage them. I had determind to put all my affairs
of a private nature into your hands— I am laboring more for *person_mentioned*yours
and Emilys children*/person_mentioned* than for myself—what do I want with
property or fortune? but little will do me, and every year less,
for I am dayly getting more tired of the *location_mentioned*world */location_mentioned*and its entercourse
and affairs— however let no wish of mine influence you, do as
you please—only never again think that I am <hi rend="italic">silent </hi>or <hi rend="italic">reserved</hi>
because I am not a great talker*/p*

*p*I know not what else to say— I am opposed to your removing
in the *date_mentioned n="Spring - 1831">spring*/date_mentioned*, tho if you put the *person_mentioned*family */person_mentioned*at *location_mentioned*Peach point*/location_mentioned* I believe they
will be [as] healthy as at any other place in the *location_mentioned*wood */location_mentioned*so do as you
please on that subject— I shall be absent from here but that will
make no difference I shall leave a full power of attorney with
*person_mentioned*Williams */person_mentioned*to deliver to you all notes due to me, as soon as you arrive<barker_pb n="496"/>
so that you may collect them in stock and also take charge of all my
affairs   I shall also leave my <hi rend="italic">will </hi>with him to be delivered to you—*/p*

*p*If you come *date_mentioned n="Fall - 1830">this fall*/date_mentioned* you must be content to quarter in *location_mentioned*log cabbins*/location_mentioned*,
which you will have to put up after you get here but that is no
great job and I could do it, but I prefer that you would look at
*location_mentioned*Peach point*/location_mentioned* and other places and chuse for yourself— If you want
any thing let me know, and not think I am reserved because I do not
offer it— I again tell you and *person_mentioned*Emily */person_mentioned*that I am far different in my
habits of cheerfulness and loquacity from what I once was— 
remember this and run no more into an error that is calculated to mar the
happiness of us all— I hope next mail to get an answer from the
Govt, as to the appointment of a *person_mentioned*commissioner */person_mentioned*and will finish the
letter but I do not know how I shall manage the thing with *person_mentioned*Edwards*/person_mentioned*
and you must not be disappointed if that place is not included. I
mean the situation at the *location_mentioned*point on the Bay*/location_mentioned*— write me as to this and
whether not getting that *location_mentioned*place */location_mentioned*will make any material difference
with you— The situation *location_mentioned*on the Bay between the point and clear
creek*/location_mentioned* is as good as that*location_mentioned* at the point*/location_mentioned* in some respects— Let me know
your wishes and as you justly observe be very frank with me—*/p*

*p*I am sorry to say that some of the people here are in a tangle
amongst themselves. *person_mentioned*Seth Ingram*/person_mentioned* and *person_mentioned*H. H. League*/person_mentioned* are in 
confinement for killing a man by the name of *person_mentioned*Holtham*/person_mentioned*—it happened
in an affray in the street—public opinion is very much excited against
*person_mentioned*League */person_mentioned*It all happend, as most of such things do in my absence
the *date_mentioned n="09-xx-1830">beginning of this month*/date_mentioned* at *location_mentioned*Bexar*/location_mentioned*—- The fate of *person_mentioned*League */person_mentioned*and
*person_mentioned*Seth Ingram (the surveyor)*/person_mentioned*  is very doubtful, particularly the
former— There is a furious excitement all over the *location_mentioned*colony */location_mentioned*against
him— I think that you cannot complain that this letter is short so
I will close it —-*/p*

*p*remember me to the *person_mentioned*children*/person_mentioned**/p*

*p**person_mentioned*S. F. Austin*/person_mentioned* [Rubric]*/p*

*p**date_mentioned n="09-26-1830">26th */date_mentioned*   I am perplexed about your removal,
I have not yet seen*person_mentioned* H. Austin*/person_mentioned*.   I really want you here to take care
of my pecuniary affairs, and have some idea of throwing the whole
of them into *person_mentioned*John Austin*/person_mentioned*s hands*/p*

*p*There is no remidy for me, I must continue to devote all my time
to the general interests of the *location_mentioned*colony */location_mentioned*or it will not advance, it may
be necessary for me to go to *location_mentioned*Mexico */location_mentioned**date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1831">next year*/date_mentioned*— I cannot request
you to advise any of my *person_mentioned*relations */person_mentioned*to come here— They would all
think as you have that I am silent reserved cold or some thing else—¦
better live apart than in that way so for the future I never will say
one word about any person who is in any degree related to me, 
removing to this *location_mentioned*country*/location_mentioned*.  If you were here to attend to it there might<barker_pb n="497"/>
be two hundred cows and calves collected for me this *date_mentioned n="Winter - 1830">winter */date_mentioned*and
*date_mentioned n="Spring - 1831">spring */date_mentioned*and as many more in the *date_mentioned n="Fall - 1831">fall*/date_mentioned*— this would be a sufficient
start for a stock farm— I wish to know definitely what you intend
to do for I must make some final arrangement before long, I have
an impression that I told you all this when you were here, but 
perhaps I only thought it— At all events let me know what you are
going to do and when you will be here, but act for yourself and do
not be influenced by me in any part of your movement, I only want
to know what to depend upon and what arrangements I must make
to try and get some one to take charge of my affairs while I am
absent and occupied about other matters */p*                            *p* *person_mentioned*S. F. A*/person_mentioned**/p*

*p**person_mentioned*Sam Browne*/person_mentioned* is well*/p*

*p**date_mentioned n="09-27-1830">27th.*/date_mentioned* I send you a power of attorney which you must sign at both
the places marked with pencil thus—*/p*

*p*It is appointing *person_mentioned*S. M. Williams*/person_mentioned* your and your *person_mentioned*wife*/person_mentioned*s *person_mentioned*agent */person_mentioned*to
attend to getting your titles completed—send this back by some safe
conveyance as soon as you can. it ought to have been signed when
you were here and is dated then. Be sure and sign it at both places
*person_mentioned*Emily*/person_mentioned* need not sign it—*/p*

*p*[Rubric]*/p*


*/div1*
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
