
<TEI.2 id="APB4154">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>02-19-1831</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1922: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1928), 3 vols., Vol 2, pp. 599-604</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Stephen F Austin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Samuel M Williams</document_recipient>
<document_title>Stephen F Austin to Samuel M Williams, 02-19-1831</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Saltillo, Coahuila</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Austin to Samuel M. Williams, Saltillo, February 19, 1831. Influence of the
Texas Gazette in correcting erroneous opinions concerning Texas in Mexico.
Advice for its successor. Texas must hold aloof from parties. His own
method of avoiding friction with Mexicans. Threatening situation foreseen;
hands off.   Muldoon</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes> This was The Mexican Citizen, edited by R. M. Williamson.    There are four numbers
of this paper in the Wagner collection of Yale University, but no other copies are known,
The Texas Gazette
Austin uses this term frequently during this period. It evidently refers to a person,
but the context is never clear enough to identify him with certainty, Teran, as 
commissioner of colonization and general commandant, is a likely guess.
Evidently a group of advisers, probably including Luke Lesassier, R. M. Williamson,
and F. W. Johnson, and perhaps others.
The article excluding slavery.
The article prohibiting settlement of immigrants from the United States in Texas.</barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 599-604</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>09-06-2010</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>


<text id="APB4154T">

<body>
*div1 type="summary"*
*p*Austin to Samuel M. Williams, Saltillo, February 19, 1831. Influence of the
Texas Gazette in correcting erroneous opinions concerning Texas in Mexico.
Advice for its successor. Texas must hold aloof from parties. His own
method of avoiding friction with Mexicans. Threatening situation foreseen;
hands off.   Muldoon*/p*
*/div1*

*div1 type="body"*

*p*[From Williams Papers, Rosenberg Library, Galveston, Tex.]*/p*

*p**location_mentioned*Saltillo */location_mentioned**date_mentioned n="02-19-1831">Feb. 19. 1831*/date_mentioned*.*/p*
*p**person_mentioned*S M. Willams.  */person_mentioned* Dr Sir*/p*

*p*Yours of *date_mentioned n="01-25-1831">25 Jany*/date_mentioned* is recd and the letters enclosed except the one
from my *person_mentioned*sister */person_mentioned*which I hope you will send by next mail as I am very
anxious to see it.*/p*

*p*I am much pleased with the new arrangement of the pap[er] tho I
do not like the motto—<hi rend="italic">*location_mentioned*Mexico */location_mentioned*es mi patria</hi>, would do better, for it
will be as much as to say to people *location_mentioned*abroad  */location_mentioned*"we have a *location_mentioned*country */location_mentioned*and
are proud of it, and we are ready and willing to defend her rights,"
and it will remind our <hi rend="italic">home folks</hi> whom they belong to. I 
recommend that [the] motto I have suggested be adopted, or something
like it.*/p*

*p*That *location_mentioned*paper */location_mentioned*must be conducted with great prudence, you have no
idea there, what importance is attached, even to trifles, coming from
the <hi rend="italic">*person_mentioned*Austinians*/person_mentioned*</hi>. That little establishment badly as it has been 
conducted, has been of great service to [Texas] and has had an agency
in warding off some blows that were meditated against that *location_mentioned*country*/location_mentioned*,
for it has in some degree tended to correct some very erronious
opinions as to the character of the *location_mentioned*new settlements*/location_mentioned* and their feelings
towards the *person_mentioned*Govt*/person_mentioned**/p*.<barker_pb n="600"/>

*p**date_mentioned n="Spring-1830">Last spring*/date_mentioned* the idea was very general in *location_mentioned*Mexico */location_mentioned*that *location_mentioned*Texas */location_mentioned*was
the *location_mentioned*Botany Bay of the U. S.*/location_mentioned* and that the *person_mentioned*Govt, of the North*/person_mentioned* was
secretly encouraging the emigration of bad *person_mentioned*men */person_mentioned*and *person_mentioned*vagabonds*/person_mentioned*,
who were destitute of principle, for the purpose of enciting them
to rebel against this Govt, and produce confusion on the *location_mentioned*frontier*/location_mentioned*,
which would have been a pretext to enter the *location_mentioned*country */location_mentioned*and put
things to rights as *person_mentioned*Jackson */person_mentioned*entered *location_mentioned*Florida */location_mentioned*etc. This *person_mentioned*Govt*/person_mentioned*, now
believes that the *person_mentioned*settlers of <hi rend="italic">*location_mentioned*my colony*/location_mentioned* </hi>*/person_mentioned*at least, are men of principle
who will respect their oaths of fidelity, and will never forget that
they have recd fortunes from this *person_mentioned*Govt*/person_mentioned*, and favors which no other
Govt ever extended to any people. The suspicions against the
*person_mentioned*U. S. Govt*/person_mentioned*, are also all removed. But what is deemed to be the
dignity of this Govt, will not suffer it to move the repeal of the
law of *date_mentioned n="04-06-1830">6 April*/date_mentioned* unless some prominent reason can be given for so
doing. I wish the *person_mentioned*people of *location_mentioned*Texas */location_mentioned**/person_mentioned*to give such a reason by proofs
of fidelity and attachment to *location_mentioned*Mexico */location_mentioned*and the best way of 
manifesting these proofs is through the *location_mentioned*news paper*/location_mentioned*-— Let it be what its
title <hi rend="italic">[The Mexicon Citizen]</hi> professes. A <hi rend="italic">*person_mentioned*Mexican */person_mentioned*</hi>defends 
everything that is *person_mentioned*mexican*/person_mentioned*—but in genl terms, without being in favor or
against political *person_mentioned*parties*/person_mentioned*.*/p*

*p*The *person_mentioned*parties */person_mentioned*of this *location_mentioned*country */location_mentioned*are not clearly defined and have not
that definite and fixed character, nor permanency of purpose which
*person_mentioned*parties */person_mentioned*generally have in other *location_mentioned*countries*/location_mentioned*. Thus, since the to[t]al
overthrow and imprisonment of *person_mentioned*Guerrero*/person_mentioned*, a new *person_mentioned*party */person_mentioned*has sprung
up composed of <hi rend="italic">*person_mentioned*Guerreroists */person_mentioned*</hi>and <hi rend="italic">*person_mentioned*Pedrassistas*/person_mentioned*</hi> a most unnatural
connection, for the former expelled the latter by the revolution of
the *person_mentioned*Acordada*/person_mentioned*, and it seems as tho they had now united to put down
the present *person_mentioned*administration*/person_mentioned*—that effected, the *person_mentioned*Guerreroists */person_mentioned*will 
perhaps enter the lists with *person_mentioned*Pedraza */person_mentioned*for the supremacy. If we enter
into such a scramble we shall be like children in a mob, and as
likely to be trodden upon by *person_mentioned*friends */person_mentioned*as by *person_mentioned*foes*/person_mentioned*. Hence it is that
situated as we are, it is dangerous to be classed as belonging to any
party. Our neutrality injures neither, for our weight is of not
sufficient importance to injure or benefit either materially, and it
may gain us the good will of both, or what is of just as much
importance to us, both will let us alone.*/p*

*p*You are well aware that in my intercourse with this govt. I have
followed a few fixed rules from which I have never deviated since
*date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1821">1821*/date_mentioned* when I first entered the *location_mentioned*country*/location_mentioned*. In the first place I came
with pure intentions. I bid an everlasting farewell to my *location_mentioned*native
country*/location_mentioned*, and adopted this, and in so doing I determined to fulfil
rigidly all the duties and obligations of a <hi rend="italic">*person_mentioned*Mexican */person_mentioned*citizen</hi>—- have
endeavored to keep all the *person_mentioned*officers */person_mentioned*with whom I was in direct 
communication in a good humor, and to make *person_mentioned*friends */person_mentioned*of them. I have
excused and even invented plausable reasons to justify or explain<barker_pb n="601"/>
away all the political errors of my *person_mentioned*adopted countrymen*/person_mentioned*. I have
been silent as to all their defects, and lavish of praise where there
was the least pretext for bestowing it, but at the same time 
decissive and unbending where a constitutional or vested right of vital
importance was directly attacked. Rights of minor consideration
I have paid no attention to, for bad feeling might be engenderd
about <hi rend="italic">trifles</hi>, that would jeapordise an important interest. To sum
up all I have endeavored to do my duty as a <hi rend="italic">*person_mentioned*Mexican citizen.*/person_mentioned*</hi>*/p*

*p*My *person_mentioned*native countrymen */person_mentioned*are blunt *person_mentioned*republicans*/person_mentioned*, and do not always
reflect sufficiently, and some of them have accused me of debility,
want of firmness temporising etc. It was my duty to steer my
precious bark (the *location_mentioned*Colony*/location_mentioned*) through all the shoals and quicks [ands]
regardless of the curses and ridicule of the *location_mentioned*passengers*/location_mentioned*. I knew what
I was about—<hi rend="italic">they </hi>did not.*/p*

*p*The law of *date_mentioned n="04-06-1831">6 April*/date_mentioned* was founded in error and unjust suspicions,
but to have said so, would have been very impolitic, and highly 
injurious, for it would have wounded <hi rend="italic">self love, pride</hi> etc. (dangerous
things to touch among any people) and it would have strengthened
the suspicions which produced the law for everything said against
it would have been taken as evidence of disaffection. For these 
reasons in the remarks which were made in the *location_mentioned*<hi rend="italic">Texas</hi>[Gazette]*/location_mentioned* in
*date_mentioned n="06-xx-1830">June*/date_mentioned*, *date_mentioned n="07-xx-1830">July */date_mentioned*etc the policy of the Govt, was rather defended than
condemned, and circumstances were stated to shew that there were
reasons for that measure which justified it. This gratified the <hi rend="italic">self
love</hi> of its *person_mentioned*authors */person_mentioned*on the one hand, (a great point gained) and they
were very much surprised on the other to see that the very people
who were most injured by the measure, were the first to excuse and
defend it. This caused inquiries to be made through various 
channels, as to the real characters of the *person_mentioned*settlers */person_mentioned*and their feelings
towards the Govt, and the result has been very favourable as to my
*location_mentioned*colony*/location_mentioned*. This at once explains the reasons why so many more favors
have been extended to that *location_mentioned*colony */location_mentioned*than to any other. The people
at large know of no favors they have recd, neither do they know,
nor can they appreciate what I have done for them for the past ten
years, but <hi rend="italic">you </hi>and <hi rend="italic">I </hi>know that emigration to that *location_mentioned*colony */location_mentioned*could have
been stopped, and that all the *location_mentioned*ports */location_mentioned*could have been closed, or a
*person_mentioned*George Fisher*/person_mentioned* with a guard put at each. These things ought to
convince every reflecting *person_mentioned*man */person_mentioned*in that *location_mentioned*Colony */location_mentioned*that this Govt, will
reward and properly appreciate all those who <hi rend="italic">do their duty as 
*person_mentioned*Mexican */person_mentioned*Citizens</hi>, and who obey the laws and set their faces against 
confusion and illegal proceedings.*/p*

*p*The foregoing remarks are made as an introduction for what is to
follow—you will soon find yourselves in an awkward and rather
delicate situation in that *location_mentioned*Colony*/location_mentioned*, and I thought it might shed some<barker_pb n="602"/>
light upon the path which you ought to take, to explain fully the
rules and policy I have uniformly pursued.*/p*

*p*There are two points of collision in prospective in that *location_mentioned*country*/location_mentioned*,
both of them, *location_mentioned*East of my Colony*/location_mentioned*. One is between *person_mentioned*Madero */person_mentioned*and
*person_mentioned*Teran*/person_mentioned*—The other between *person_mentioned*Zavala */person_mentioned*and *person_mentioned*Teran*/person_mentioned*—or rather between
the latter and a *person_mentioned*company */person_mentioned*who have contracted to settle *person_mentioned*Zavalas*/person_mentioned*,
*person_mentioned*Vielen */person_mentioned*and *person_mentioned*Burnetts */person_mentioned**location_mentioned*grants*/location_mentioned*—the *person_mentioned*Settlers */person_mentioned*are to be *person_mentioned*Germans*/person_mentioned*, *person_mentioned*Swiss*/person_mentioned*
*person_mentioned*french */person_mentioned*etc—all *person_mentioned*Europeans*/person_mentioned*—have nothing to do with these collisions-
do as I have frequently been compelled to do—play the turtle, head
and feet within your own shell—some of the people may curse and
abuse—no matter—they abused me the best friend they ever had.
Better break all the timber in *location_mentioned*Texas*/location_mentioned*, than to break*person_mentioned* Boss [Teran?]*/person_mentioned*
for the former is plenty and can be replaced, but the lat[t]er being
a fine texture is not to be found everyday. That *location_mentioned*colony */location_mentioned*is the heart of
*location_mentioned*Texas*/location_mentioned*; keep all sound there, and we shall gain the confidence of the
Govt, and save the *location_mentioned*Country*/location_mentioned*, but if you go to the extremities to try
and cure diseases, you interfere with the head doctor, which he will
take very ill (for all doctors are jealous of their prerogatives), and
besides there will be danger of introducing disease into the <hi rend="italic">heart</hi>,
by infection.*/p*

*p*XXX Whether the *person_mentioned*Genl Govt*/person_mentioned*, has authority to annul *person_mentioned*Zavala*/person_mentioned*'s
*location_mentioned*grant */location_mentioned*or not is no question for us to interfere with, neither have we
anything to do with *person_mentioned*Madero*/person_mentioned*'s commission etc. those are matters 
between the interested *person_mentioned*parties */person_mentioned*and the *person_mentioned*Govt*/person_mentioned*, with which my *location_mentioned*colony*/location_mentioned*
ought to have nothing to do, in any shape manner or form. My *location_mentioned*colony*/location_mentioned*
has cleared away the rude asperities of the *location_mentioned*wilderness*/location_mentioned*—made *location_mentioned*Texas*/location_mentioned*
known—given it a station in geography—a place, and a distinguished
one, in the class of <hi rend="italic">desirable *location_mentioned*countries */location_mentioned*</hi>and has demonstrated its value,
by developing its resources. In doing <hi rend="italic">this</hi>, it has done enough to
aid others who now wish to settle in that *location_mentioned*country*/location_mentioned*, and they ought
not to expect that we will unite with them in projects for forcing
their way against the will of the *person_mentioned*Govt*/person_mentioned*, or that we are to make 
common cause of their quarrels and collisions, and if they do expect
it I hope they will be deceived, hope! I know they will, for there
is too much sound common sense and too much honest patriotism
in the people of *location_mentioned*Austins colony*/location_mentioned* for them to be misled, or to deviate
from the line of their duty as *person_mentioned*Mexican Citizens*/person_mentioned*, and besides they have
a <hi rend="italic">great deal</hi> to loose, the others have much to gain but <hi rend="italic">nothing </hi>to
loose. XXX*/p* 

*p*But while, on the one hand, you avoid suffering yourselves to
be made *person_mentioned*parties */person_mentioned*to the collisions which I have alluded to, against
the Govt, also try on the other, not to take any active, or open,
or any part at all in them against the new *person_mentioned*settlers*/person_mentioned*—   Be mere lookers<barker_pb n="603"/>
on—say nothing—give no opinions—no advice—-take no part—have
nothing to do with the matter at all—refer them to the Govt, but
if *person_mentioned*Genl Teran*/person_mentioned* issues any orders <hi rend="italic">obey them</hi>. He is our main stay.
You may rely upon it and he is worthy of our confidence and support.
Don't let the *location_mentioned*paper */location_mentioned*be made the vehicle for venting the spleen or
abuse of *person_mentioned*Madero */person_mentioned*or anybody else, make it a <hi rend="italic">Dignified Calm Judicious
" *person_mentioned*Mexican */person_mentioned*Citizen "</hi> adopt the motto I have proposed and adhere to
its principles rigidly—all will come round right—many of the most
influential men of all parties, in office, and out, in the *location_mentioned*City of
Mexico*/location_mentioned* and elsewhere have procured *location_mentioned*grants in Texas*/location_mentioned* and more are
dayly making. <hi rend="italic">All these </hi>are true friends to the real prosperity of that
*location_mentioned*country*/location_mentioned*. We can make them <hi rend="italic">our </hi>friends by adopting the policy
I have indicated, or rather by following the policy I have always
followed.*/p*

*p*You can submit this letter to the *person_mentioned*Congress */person_mentioned*or to as many of my
*person_mentioned*friends */person_mentioned*as you think prudent, and should any serious difficulty arrise
and you should think that it would do any good to make my 
opinions known, you can have it done so far as <hi rend="italic">Congress </hi>may judge
prudent and correct, by means of an editorial article—that plan
would do better than to make any extracts [f]rom this letter.*/p*

*p**person_mentioned*Padre Muldoon*/person_mentioned* left some days since—he wrote me from 
*location_mentioned*Monterrey */location_mentioned*that he had recd his appointment of <hi rend="italic">*person_mentioned*Cura de Austin*/person_mentioned*</hi> from the
*person_mentioned*Provisor*/person_mentioned*, and I presume will soon be with you—his councils will be
of service to you, and the *location_mentioned*colony*/location_mentioned*, for I believe he has the true
interests of that *location_mentioned*colony */location_mentioned*much at heart—he has some vanity, and I
think a very benevolent heart, and pure intentions. I told him that
*location_mentioned*Texas */location_mentioned*might be made a *location_mentioned*Bishoprick */location_mentioned*of in a few years, if we could
get rid of the 13 article of our State Constitution,2 and the 11
Article3 of the law of *date_mentioned n="04-06-1830">6 April*/date_mentioned*. I am very much pleased with him,
as a man, and much better as a <hi rend="italic">Padre</hi>.*/p*

*p*I have spun out a long thread and it is time to break off, which
I will do by requesting you to remember me affcy. to*person_mentioned* Mrs. W.*/person_mentioned* and *person_mentioned*Mrs.
S.*/person_mentioned* and to *person_mentioned*Luke [Lesassier]*/person_mentioned*, *person_mentioned*Willy [E. M. Williamson]*/person_mentioned*, *person_mentioned*Jack [one of
three brothers—William H., Spencer, or Patrick C]*/person_mentioned*, *person_mentioned*[Oliver] Jones*/person_mentioned*,
*person_mentioned*[F. W._] Johnson*/person_mentioned* etc, and take good care of my *person_mentioned*nephew Moses
Austin Bryan*/person_mentioned*, besides being the *person_mentioned*grandson */person_mentioned*and bearing the name of
the man who was the first *person_mentioned*author */person_mentioned*of all our fortunes in that *location_mentioned*country*/location_mentioned*,
he is the *person_mentioned*son */person_mentioned*of a very favourite *person_mentioned*sister */person_mentioned*of mine.
Hasta Cada Rato*/p*

*p**person_mentioned*S. F. Austin.*/person_mentioned**/p*

*p*N. B. If times get very bad and public opinion should seem to
waver, it might be well to publish the paragraph marked thus—[Inserted XXX XXX on each side as symbols did not transfer.  DML] as an extract from me—tho all this left <hi rend="italic">totally </hi>to the wisdom of <hi rend="italic">congress</hi>.*/p*<barker_pb n="604"/>




 

*/div1*
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
