
<TEI.2 id="APB1632">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>11-03-1828</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1922: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1928), 3 vols., Vol 2, pp. 138-139</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Thomas F McKinney</document_author>
<document_sender>John Williams</document_sender>
<document_recipient>Stephen F Austin</document_recipient>
<document_title>Thomas F McKinney to Stephen F Austin, 11-03-1828</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Nacogdoches, Texas</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Thomas F. McKinney to Austin, Nacogdoches, November 3, 1828. Relating difficulties with Colonel Piedras, and asking help.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes></barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 138-139</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>08-08-2010</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>


<text id="APB1632T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Thomas F. McKinney to Austin, Nacogdoches, November 3, 1828. Relating difficulties with Colonel Piedras, and asking help.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><location_mentioned>Nacogdoches </location_mentioned><date_mentioned n="11-03-1828">Nov. 3rd 1828<</date_mentioned>/p>
<p>D. Col.</p>

<p>I should certainly have written to you Since my arrival from my
wild voyage from <location_mentioned>Orleans </location_mentioned>but I have been so immerced in business
of an unpleasant nature that I could attend to nothing in reality</p>

<p>I was not aware of having to deal with <person_mentioned>Col. Piedras</person_mentioned> when I made
a contract with a <person_mentioned>Mr Mora</person_mentioned> in <location_mentioned>Orleans </location_mentioned>to bring freight from there
to this <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>in a Keal Boat I likewise contracted with some 
<person_mentioned>Americans </person_mentioned>and with them I have had no difficulty but unfortunately the
goods I received of <person_mentioned>Mora </person_mentioned>has proved to belong to the <person_mentioned>Col</person_mentioned>. and he
has used every means to influence <person_mentioned>Mora </person_mentioned>to relate palpable 
falshoods for the purpose of injuring me and had <person_mentioned>Mora </person_mentioned>not been a man
of integrity he certainly would have put me to much trouble though
when ever we have come to an arbitration or suit I have fortunately
had every decision in my favour but I find [Piedras] the most inde-<barker_pb n="139"/>
fatigable <person_mentioned>man </person_mentioned>in dishonesty I ever knew he still Contemplates
more suits against me relative to the boat Concern and I have become
so fatigued with his molestations that I have almost dispaired of ever
getting a fair settlement with him I had rather make any sacrifice
which my circumstances would admit than cavel with him eternally.</p>

<p>His conduct in this <location_mentioned>place </location_mentioned>renders a residence here unpleasant and
unsafe I have presumed to make a brief relation of his acts to
<person_mentioned>Genl Bustamante</person_mentioned> without having the slightest acquantance with the
<person_mentioned>general </person_mentioned>but the facts were such as I hope he will at least investigate
the matter and there his conduct will appear in its true feature my
trip which would have been otherwise prosperous has already sunk
two hundred and fifty or three hundred Dollars and where the loss
will stop is uncertain. If I could dispose of My <location_mentioned>land in the Colony</location_mentioned>
I should be relieved of some little embarasment which otherwise I
must labour under. <person_mentioned>John Williams</person_mentioned> the <person_mentioned>bearer </person_mentioned>of this 
communication tells me he will buy it of me on seeing you if the title suits him
you will render me a favour by aiding the sale so far as is consistent
with your ideas of the matter</p>

<p>Our land difficulties and confusion here I hope will be at an end
when the <person_mentioned>Comisioner </person_mentioned>arrives as I am informed he is comisd for the
purpose of adjusting all diferences relative to land If the situation
of your buisness would permit you to come on with the <person_mentioned>comisioner</person_mentioned>
I think much good would arise there from to the <person_mentioned>inhabitants </person_mentioned>though
perhaps in reality none to yourself.</p>

<p>I confess My silence ever since my arrival requires an apology
though I should assure you my dear sir be happy at all times to
hear from [you] hoping the greatest prosperity may attend you</p>

<p><person_mentioned>Thomas F. McKinney </person_mentioned>   [Rubric]</p>

<p><person_mentioned>Col Stephen F. Austin</person_mentioned></p>

<p>NB Accept of the respects of <person_mentioned>Mrs. McKinney</person_mentioned> And if Possible
for you to visit this <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>we would be glad you would call Stay
with us</p>

<p>Sincerely</p>

<p><person_mentioned>McK</person_mentioned></p>


</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
