
<TEI.2 id="APB4353">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>06-15-1832</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 779-782</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Stephen F Austin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Samuel M Williams</document_recipient>
<document_title>Stephen F Austin to Samuel M Williams, 06-15-1832</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Matamoros, Tamaulipas</sent_from>
	<sent_to>San Felipe de Austin, Texas</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Austin to Samuel M. Williams, Matamoros, June 15, 1832. Tariff politics. Teran against foreigners, but favors repeal of law of April 6, 1830. Smuggling.   Galveston Bay & Texas Land Co.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes></barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 779-782</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>09-24-2010</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>


<text id="APB4353T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Austin to Samuel M. Williams, Matamoros, June 15, 1832. Tariff politics. Teran against foreigners, but favors repeal of law of April 6, 1830. Smuggling.   Galveston Bay & Texas Land Co.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p>[From Williams Papers, Rosenberg Library, Galveston, Tex.]</p>

<p><location_mentioned>Matamoros </location_mentioned><date_mentioned n="06-15-1832">June 15—1832</date_mentioned></p>
<p>Dr Sir.</p>

<p>I left <location_mentioned>Saltillo </location_mentioned>on the <date_mentioned n="05-12-1832">12th May</date_mentioned>—thence by <location_mentioned>Monterrey</location_mentioned>, <location_mentioned>Pelon</location_mentioned>,
<location_mentioned>Linares</location_mentioned>, <location_mentioned>Victoria </location_mentioned>to the <location_mentioned>Hacienda del Cojo, the head quarters of<barker_pb n="780"/>
<person_mentioned>Genl Teran</</person_mentioned>location_mentioned> <location_mentioned>20 leagues back of Tampico</location_mentioned>, thence by <location_mentioned>Soto Marina</location_mentioned>
here. <person_mentioned>Genl Mason</person_mentioned> accompanied me to this place, and we both 
intended to have gone to <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, but the fatigues of so long a journey
as the one we have just made through excessive heat and drought
in an almost<location_mentioned> uninhabited country</location_mentioned>, has worn us both down very
much—he has concluded to embark for<location_mentioned> N. York</location_mentioned> from here, and I
shall return to <location_mentioned>Saltillo </location_mentioned>to wait the meeting of the <person_mentioned>Legislature </person_mentioned>in
<date_mentioned n="09-xx-1832">September</date_mentioned>, consequently shall not reach home untill <date_mentioned n="10-xx-1832">October</date_mentioned>.</p>

<p><person_mentioned>Mr Alexr Greaves,</person_mentioned> who came directly here from <location_mentioned>Victoria </location_mentioned>proceeds
to <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>. I have told him to go direct to your <location_mentioned>house</location_mentioned>—he is the
most useful man for an office I have ever seen in this country—rigidly
moral, industrious, and in every respect worthy of confidence—his
knowledge of the Spanish is most accurate—you will discover that
his general knowledge of human nature and of mankind is not quite
as extensive as that of some men, but his judgement in general is
very correct. I think him a very worthy <person_mentioned>man</person_mentioned>-—a better man could
not be found for the <person_mentioned>Secretary of the Ayto</person_mentioned> either of <location_mentioned>Austin</location_mentioned>, or of
<location_mentioned>Brazoria</location_mentioned>.</p>

<p>I send you the law extending the privilege of introducing certain
articles free of duty in <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>for two years—it is not as extensive
as we need. I wish the <person_mentioned>Ayto</person_mentioned>. to petition again on this subject, and
ask for a modification of this new law, so as to leave out <hi rend="italic">whiskey</hi>
and <hi rend="italic">lumber </hi>from the law, and include all tools made of iron and
wood used for farming or the <hi rend="italic">trades</hi>—furniture—carte and 
waggons—iron and steel—cotton baging and bale rope.</p>

<p>It will not do to go any farther, and nothing else ought to be
included or mentioned in the petition. Send one <hi rend="italic">original </hi>copy to
<person_mentioned>Genl Teran</person_mentioned> and one to the <person_mentioned>Minister of Hacienda</person_mentioned>—also let the <person_mentioned>Ayto</person_mentioned>.
write an official letter to <person_mentioned>Bradburn</person_mentioned>, <person_mentioned>Piedras</person_mentioned>, and <person_mentioned>Elosua</person_mentioned>, enclosing
the memorial, and requesting each of them to give his opinion in
writing to the<person_mentioned> Comt Genl Teran</person_mentioned> on the subject. If their opinions
are all favourable <person_mentioned>Teran </person_mentioned>will also support it, and the measure will
succeed. Also request<person_mentioned> father Muldoon</person_mentioned> to write to his <person_mentioned>friends </person_mentioned>on
the subject.</p>

<p>The <location_mentioned>news papers</location_mentioned> will have informed you of the political state of
affairs in <location_mentioned>Mexico</location_mentioned>—we have no information here as to who are to
compose the new <location_mentioned>ministry</location_mentioned>. Some think the revolution will stop
with the removal of the <person_mentioned>ministers</person_mentioned>, others are confident it will not.
I think myself that not much quietness can be expected untill after
the Presidential election is over—and even then—-<hi rend="italic">quien sabe</hi>.</p>

<p><person_mentioned>Genl Teran</person_mentioned> has gained much credit with moderate men for 
avoiding bloodshed—but he has also <hi rend="italic">lost </hi>with the same men, and with
everyone except <person_mentioned>fanatic fools</person_mentioned> and <person_mentioned>old Spaniards</person_mentioned>, for the manner in
which he has spoken of  <person_mentioned>foreigners </person_mentioned>in his letter to <person_mentioned>Moctezuma</person_mentioned><barker_pb n="781"/>
written from here, and his Altamira proclamation both of which
you have seen published, the latter begins " Ya lo habéis visto." I
sincerely believe that neither of those papers contains his real 
sentiments as to <person_mentioned>foreigners</person_mentioned>—but most people are in the habit of judging
of a man by what he <hi rend="italic">says</hi>, and not by what he thinks, and for this
reason I think those two papers will do the <person_mentioned>Genl </person_mentioned>great harm both
at <location_mentioned>home </location_mentioned>and <location_mentioned>abroad</location_mentioned>. They will also irritate the other party 
excessively, for they contain a direct charge that the<person_mentioned> Santana party
</person_mentioned>are the mere tools of <person_mentioned>foreigners</person_mentioned>, which is certainly an incorrect
charge.</p>

<p>The <person_mentioned>Genl </person_mentioned>was greatly perplexed, and overwhelmed with <hi rend="italic">affairs</hi>
when I saw him at the cojo. He had just retreated from <location_mentioned>Tampico</location_mentioned>—
had just heard of the removal of the <person_mentioned>ministers</person_mentioned>—was not in very
good health, and in a camp in the midst of his army, of course not
in a situation to talk much about <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>matters—however, we had
considerable conversation on the subject. He expresses great 
interest for the prosperity of the <person_mentioned>settlers</person_mentioned>—is in favor of repealing the
11 Article of the law of <date_mentioned n="04-06-1830">6 April</date_mentioned> and of extending the commercial
privileges. He told me that he had sent on <person_mentioned>Fisher</person_mentioned>s resignation to
the Govt, to be acted on by the <person_mentioned>President </person_mentioned>as he might deem proper
etc. etc.</p>

<p>If harmony and confidence can be maintained between the 
<person_mentioned>merchants </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>settlers </person_mentioned>and the <person_mentioned><hi rend="italic">local </hi>officers of the<location_mentioned> custom house</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> and of
the <person_mentioned>army </person_mentioned>at <location_mentioned>Brazoria</location_mentioned>, all will get on very well. <hi rend="italic">Some one</hi> reported
to <person_mentioned>Genl Teran</person_mentioned> that there were more goods imported into <location_mentioned>Brazoria</location_mentioned>
in <date_mentioned n="10-xx-1831">October </date_mentioned>and <date_mentioned n="11-xx-1831">November last</date_mentioned>, than had entered the port of 
<location_mentioned>Matamoros </location_mentioned>for one year—this was the real cause of his sudden trip to
<location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>last <date_mentioned n="11-xx-1831">Novr </date_mentioned>when he took out <person_mentioned>Fisher</person_mentioned>.</p>

<p>He says that what the <person_mentioned>Settlers </person_mentioned>need for their own use is of no
consequence, and if goods could be prevented from being taken from
<location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>to the <location_mentioned>interior</location_mentioned>, no <location_mentioned>custom house</location_mentioned> would be established there for
many years—but he says that the importations there for the purpose
of the <location_mentioned>interior </location_mentioned>trade reduces the revenue of of this port, and defrauds
the Govt. etc. I told him that the <person_mentioned>person </person_mentioned>who made such a report
to him stated what was false. He said that every indulgence would
be allowed on all articles for the necessary use of the <person_mentioned>settlers</person_mentioned>, but
that the utmost rigor would be used as to light and fancy dry goods,
suitable for the <location_mentioned>interior </location_mentioned>trade. By the by this <location_mentioned>interior </location_mentioned>trade has
never been carried on from <location_mentioned>Brazoria </location_mentioned>or <location_mentioned>Galveston</location_mentioned>—it is a loosing
business at best, and I hope for the future our <person_mentioned>merchants </person_mentioned>will let
it alone. It is more important at this time to encourage the <person_mentioned>farmers</person_mentioned>
than the <person_mentioned>merchants</person_mentioned>.</p>

<p>I shall go to <location_mentioned>Monterrey </location_mentioned>and try to enlist some <person_mentioned>friends </person_mentioned>there who
have influence in <location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned>to use it with the new <person_mentioned>administration </person_mentioned>in<barker_pb n="782"/>
favor of a repeal of the 11 Article of the law of <date_mentioned n="04-06-1830">6 April</date_mentioned>. I have
every confidence that, that law will be modified. I shall probably
be in <location_mentioned>Saltillo </location_mentioned>in <date_mentioned n="07-xx-1832">July </date_mentioned>where I shall expect letters from you, giving
me the news as to how the <location_mentioned>colony </location_mentioned>is getting on. I hear you had a
very wet spring and have fine prospects for crops.</p>

<p><person_mentioned>Genl Mason</person_mentioned> has succeeded <hi rend="italic">in part</hi> in getting the <person_mentioned>New York 
Company</person_mentioned> business arranged, and I think they will go on with the 
settlement of those <location_mentioned>colonies </location_mentioned>by <person_mentioned>europeans</person_mentioned>.</p>

<p>Remember me particularly to <person_mentioned>Padre Muldoon </person_mentioned>and <hi rend="italic">all others</hi>.
These long trips in the sun through such a <location_mentioned>wilderness </location_mentioned>as this 
country totally destitute of every comfort for the <person_mentioned>traveller</person_mentioned>, are truly
wearisome to the body, to the health, to the patience and to the mind,
but if I can do any good to the <location_mentioned>colony </location_mentioned>I shall feel myself well 
compensated for all.</p>

<p><person_mentioned>S. F. Austin </person_mentioned>   [Rubric]</p>

<p>[Addressed:] <person_mentioned> Mr.  Sam M. Williams</person_mentioned>   <location_mentioned> San Felipe de Austin</location_mentioned></p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
