
<TEI.2 id="APB1730">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>07-06-1829</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1922: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1928), 3 vols., Vol 2, pp. 226-228</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Stephen F Austin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>J L Woodbuy</document_recipient>
<document_title>Stephen F Austin to J L Woodbuy, 07-06-1829</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>San Felipe de Austin, Texas</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Austin to John Lucius Woodbury, July 6, 1829. Welcoming him as a fellow empresario and describing the natural advantages of Texas. Manufacturing would be profitable—particularly cotton textiles.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes>Compare with this letter Williams to Austin, June 9, 1829</barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 226-228</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>08-12-2010</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>


<text id="APB1730T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Austin to John Lucius Woodbury, July 6, 1829. Welcoming him as a fellow empresario and describing the natural advantages of Texas. Manufacturing would be profitable—particularly cotton textiles.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><location_mentioned>San Felipe de Austin</location_mentioned> <date_mentioned n="07-06-1829">July 6. 1829</date_mentioned></p>

<p><person_mentioned>Doctor Lucius Woodberry</person_mentioned>.</p>

<p>Dr Sir, On my return to this place a few since I recd your
much esteemed favor of <date_mentioned n="05-27-1829">27 May.</date_mentioned> I regret that I was absent when
you passed as I should have been happy to have seen you</p>

<p>It gives me great pleasure to hear that you are bound to 
<location_mentioned>Philadelphia </location_mentioned>for the purpose of consulting with the <person_mentioned>House </person_mentioned>in that City
who are concerned with you in Colonization, and I flatter myself
that an efficient impulse will be given to the <location_mentioned>settlements </location_mentioned>on <location_mentioned>Trinity</location_mentioned>
by your exertions and those of your <person_mentioned>friends</person_mentioned>—there cannot be a
doubt that individual profits, as well as much general good to the
<location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>will result from the settlement of the <location_mentioned>section which has
been assigned to you</location_mentioned> to the <location_mentioned>eastward of my Colony—</location_mentioned> That section
embraces a very interesting portion of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>-—the <location_mentioned>Trinity and
Neches rivers run through it</location_mentioned>, both navigable, and the former 
discharges into <location_mentioned>Galvecton Bay</location_mentioned>— you will however obtain a more
correct knowledge of its geographical position by examining my <location_mentioned>map
of Texas </location_mentioned>which you can see by calling on<person_mentioned> Mr. Thos. F. Learning</person_mentioned> of
that City to whom I have sent it.</p><barker_pb n="227"/>

<p><location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>as a <location_mentioned>Country</location_mentioned>, wheither viewed with reference to its 
geographical position, its soil, its climate, the number of its <location_mentioned>rivers </location_mentioned>and
creeks of pure running water, its <location_mentioned>Bays </location_mentioned>and the variety, abundance,
and value of its productions, may be advantageously compared with
any portion of <location_mentioned>north America</location_mentioned>. This <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>has laid dormant for
ages— It was the policy of the <person_mentioned>Spanish Govt </person_mentioned>to keep it out of view
and to conceal, as much as possible, its natural advantages— The
<location_mentioned>grant </location_mentioned>to my Father <person_mentioned>Moses Austin </person_mentioned>to settle a <location_mentioned>colony in Texas </location_mentioned>made
by the <person_mentioned>Spanish Authorities</person_mentioned> in <date_mentioned n="01-xx-1821">January 1821</date_mentioned>, a few months before the
independence of <location_mentioned>Mexico</location_mentioned>, was the first deviation from this policy
that had ever occured. After the death of my <person_mentioned>father </person_mentioned>I explored the
<location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>in the <date_mentioned n="Summer - 1821">summer </date_mentioned>and <date_mentioned n="Fall - 1821">fall of 1821</date_mentioned>, and in the succeeding <date_mentioned n="Winter - 1821">winter</date_mentioned>
and <date_mentioned n="Spring - 1822">spring </date_mentioned>commenced my <location_mentioned>settlement </location_mentioned>in the midst of its <location_mentioned>wilderness</location_mentioned>
<location_mentioned>on the Brasos and Colorado rivers</location_mentioned> Since when the progress of the
<location_mentioned>new settlements</location_mentioned> under the fostering hand of the <location_mentioned>Republic of Mexico
</location_mentioned>has gradually developed the value of <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>and brought it into
notice. The touch Stone of experience has been applied, and the
result has shewn that our climate is healthy and pleasant, our soil
productive beyond expectation, our seasons regular and rain 
sufficiently abundant. Our <location_mentioned>rivers </location_mentioned>are navigable, and our <location_mentioned>harbors </location_mentioned>safe
and of sufficient depth for all the purposes of commerce.</p>

<p>When I entered <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>in the winter of <date_mentioned n=Winter - 1821/1822">1821-22</date_mentioned> with the first 
<person_mentioned>emigrants</person_mentioned>, the idea of forming a <location_mentioned>settlement in this remote wilderness</location_mentioned>
amidst <person_mentioned>tribes </person_mentioned>of uncivilized <person_mentioned>Indians</person_mentioned> was ridiculed by my best <person_mentioned>friends</person_mentioned>
as visionary and impracticable— The value of the <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>was
unknown or greatly doubted, and it was entirely uninhabited except
by <person_mentioned>savages </person_mentioned><location_mentioned>from the Sabine to the Towns of Bexar and La Bahi</location_mentioned>a
(now called <location_mentioned>Goliad</location_mentioned>) and those places were reduced to a weak state
by the <person_mentioned>indian </person_mentioned>war Also at that time the <person_mentioned>Mexican Govt</person_mentioned> was in an
unsettled and revolutionary state and it was beyond the calculation
of the most judicious to say what shape or form it would ultimately
assume. In answer to any doubts that may now exist as to the value
of <location_mentioned>Texas as a Country</location_mentioned>, I would merely refer to what it was when I
commenced, to the difficulties and impediments which retarded my
progress and then ask, wheither I or any other person however
great his perseverance may have been could have formed a 
settlement of intelligent worthy and industrious <person_mentioned>north Americans</person_mentioned> in this
<location_mentioned>wilderness</location_mentioned>, and that too without the aid of power full patronage or
wealth,<hi rend="italic"> if the <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>itself had not afforded the strongest 
inducements to emigration by its real and intrinsic value.</hi></p>

<p>There is an immense opening in <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>for the establishment of
<location_mentioned>Cotton Manufactories</location_mentioned>— The raw material is raised here in
abundance and of superior quality.— Provisions are cheap and will
daily become cheaper, there are numerous good situations for 
Machenery and abundance of good oak, Pine, Cypress, Cedar, Ash<barker_pb n="228"/>
and other timber—the Tariff of <location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned>causes a Domestics " to sell
high and as the restrictive System appears to have become a part
of the national policy, fair prospects may be calculated on for the
manufacturer for Many years to come. [Deleted:] I would very
freely engage in an establishment of this kind and nothing but my
being tied down here with colonizing matters prevents my visiting
the <location_mentioned>north[ern] States </location_mentioned>of that union with the view of trying to form a
<location_mentioned>large manufacturing company</location_mentioned> in <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>.</p>

<p>[Added In a copy—apparently made by J. E. B. Austin:] It will
afford me much pleasure to become acquainted with the <person_mentioned>house in
<location_mentioned>Philadelphia</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> with which you are concerned in colonization and to
render them any aid in my power in forwarding the settlement of
<location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>.</p>

<p><person_mentioned>Stephen F. Austin</person_mentioned>.</p>


</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
