
<TEI.2 id="APB4645">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>05-30-1834</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1922: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1928), 3 vols., Vol 2, pp. 1057-1060</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Stephen F Austin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Oliver Jones</document_recipient>
<document_title>Stephen F Austin to Oliver Jones, 05-30-1834</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>En Inquisicion, Mexico</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Austin to Oliver Jones, Mexico, May 30, 1834. Suggests that ayuntamientos of Texas thank State and Federal governments for recent relief measures and petition for his own release.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes>Copy by Moses Austin Bryan</barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1057-1060</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>12-05-2010</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>


<text id="APB4645T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Austin to Oliver Jones, Mexico, May 30, 1834. Suggests that ayuntamientos of Texas thank State and Federal governments for recent relief measures and petition for his own release.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><location_mentioned>En Inquisición Mexico</location_mentioned> <date_mentioned n="05-30-1834">May 30th 1834</date_mentioned></p>
<p><person_mentioned>Mr. Oliver Jones</person_mentioned></p>

<p>Sir I am still in <location_mentioned>prison </location_mentioned>and I can form no idea when I shall be
at liberty</p>

<p>When I left <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>in <date_mentioned n="04-xx-1833">April 1833</date_mentioned> the position taken by the people
was that the evils that threatened that <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>with ruin must be
removed by the <person_mentioned>Government </person_mentioned>or the <person_mentioned>people </person_mentioned>[would] remedy them
themselves and ought to do so as in that case they would have the
right to do it. I sustained this position as the<person_mentioned> agent of the people</person_mentioned>
firmly both verbally and in writing before the <person_mentioned>ministers </person_mentioned>and the
<person_mentioned>Vice President</person_mentioned> and also in my letter to the <person_mentioned>Ayuntamiento of <location_mentioned>Bexar</location_mentioned>
</person_mentioned>of <date_mentioned n="10-02-1833">2nd of Oct.</date_mentioned> last I represented my constituents as they were when
I left them, and as I had right to believe they continued to be; 
regardless of my personal safety liberty or life, it was my duty so to<barker_pb n="1058"/>
do—great good has resulted to <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>from my labors, and the noise
which this business has made—all the evils complained of have been
removed, my conscience is clear, I have discharged my duty faith
fully, and for having done so I have suffered five months inprison
ment-—Three of them in close and solitary confinement locked up
in a <location_mentioned>dungeon </location_mentioned>day and night, the reflection that <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>would be
benefited by my sufferings kept up my spirits and I have borne it all
with patience and fortitude, I have understood indirectly from
common rumor that those people in whose service I am suffering and
have sacrificed so much time and money and fatigue are now
calumniating me and rejoicing in my misfortunes, I do not believe this
report—a few may do so, but not the mass—not the <person_mentioned>farmers</person_mentioned>-
the honest and sound part of the community—they have always been
correct sound and honest in their feelings intensions, and principles
and I have no doubt that all their sympathies are in my favor
will not calumniate them even in my thoughts by believing otherwise</p>

<p>In my letter of the <date_mentioned n="01-17-1834">17th January</date_mentioned> from <location_mentioned>Monterrey</location_mentioned>, I requested them
not to suffer themselves to be excited on act. of my imprisonment
I did this to serve them, for all kinds of excitements in <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>are
injurious to the farming and laboring classes and to the 
improvement of that country. They complied with my request and I than
them for having done so. I also requested them to be obedient to
the <location_mentioned>state of Coahuila and Texas</location_mentioned>—they have been so, and for this
also thank them—God knows when I shall be at liberty—I hope
soon—a mild and respectful representation of facts from the 
<person_mentioned>Ayuntamientos of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> stating the situation of that country and of
public opinion when I left them In <date_mentioned n="04-xx-1833">April last year</date_mentioned>, as <person_mentioned>agent</person_mentioned>, the
position above stated taken by those people which it was my duty
as their <person_mentioned>agent </person_mentioned>to sustain, and my general character, conduct and
services in favor of good order, of the integrity of the <location_mentioned>mexican 
territory</location_mentioned> and of the welfare and improvement of my <location_mentioned>adopted country</location_mentioned>
such a representation especialy from <location_mentioned>Bexar </location_mentioned>would open my <location_mentioned>dungeon</location_mentioned>
at any time and would do it now. But perhaps this is to much to be
done for <person_mentioned>S. F. Austin</person_mentioned>, I did not think that I was doing too much
for those people when I risked everything for them.</p>

<p>I understand that the main charge against me is an attempt to
separate <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>from the <location_mentioned>mexican Republic</location_mentioned>, this charge is false as all
<location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>can testify, however I do not know what the charge is for
up to this day no copy of charges or accusation of any kind has
been furnished—neither do I know whether I am to be judged by a
<person_mentioned>military or civil tribunal</person_mentioned> when informed of the charges against me
(and God knows when that will [be] perhaps many months hence)
it may be necessary for me to send to <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>for evidence, so that I
may linger away years here—the <person_mentioned>Ayuntamientos of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> might
have saved me all this,   I did not ask it but I confess that I ex-<barker_pb n="1059"/>
pected it would have been done. If I am calumniated I consider
that it is a duty of the people there to defend me by a statement of
facts—an able and clear but short exposition to the public.</p>

<p>I hear from rumor that the <person_mentioned>state legislature</person_mentioned> have past a law to
sell the vacant lands—such a law is necessary—public sales is the
best, and only true basis for a land law, It will benefit the <location_mentioned>state of
Coahuila and Texas</location_mentioned> greatly and fill its treasury and also benefit
<location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>—I recommend this system to the <person_mentioned>ministers </person_mentioned>here and the 
establishment of the trial by <person_mentioned>jury </person_mentioned>and the <person_mentioned>minister of relations</person_mentioned> informed
me that he had recommended both to the <person_mentioned>Government of the state</person_mentioned>
by order of the <person_mentioned>Vice president</person_mentioned>.</p>

<p>The aspect of things here indicates a great change or a civil war
of some kind, But God knows what, the<person_mentioned> people of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>, in my
opinion ought to have nothing to do with their family political 
quarrels and I hope they will not. All you need in <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>is peace, a
dead calm, and to make good crops. Remember me to all who
remember me, Show this to <person_mentioned>Capt. Martin</person_mentioned>, to <person_mentioned>D. G. Burnett</person_mentioned> and to
<person_mentioned>Miller</person_mentioned>—</p>                                                                          <p><person_mentioned>S. F. Austin</person_mentioned></p>

<p><date_mentioned n="06-02-1834">June 2nd</date_mentioned> I have just heard of the laws past by the <location_mentioned>state </location_mentioned>in favor
of the <person_mentioned>local government</person_mentioned> in <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>the establishment of three 
departments; <person_mentioned>judges</person_mentioned>, trial by <person_mentioned>jury</person_mentioned>, land law etc. In short every evil 
complained of has been remedied—this fully compensates me for all I
have suffered I do not regret it; I think it is the duty of the <person_mentioned>people
of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>, to return thanks to the <person_mentioned>State Govt</person_mentioned>, in a public manner
through the <person_mentioned>Ayuntamientos </person_mentioned>for these laws, and to make a most
positive and clear declaration of their attachment and firm adhesion
and union to the <location_mentioned>state of Coahuila and Texas</location_mentioned> and to the <location_mentioned>Mexican
confederation</location_mentioned>. This ought to be done—it is due to the <location_mentioned>state</location_mentioned>—and
it ought to be published in the <location_mentioned>news papers of the U. S.</location_mentioned> in order to
correct the erroneous opinions, that have existed there as to the
intentions or <hi rend="italic">objects </hi>of the<person_mentioned> people of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>,—they have been sound—
they asked for a competant organization of their <person_mentioned>local government</person_mentioned>
and nothing else, and they never had any other object, It was for
this I came to <location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned>and for this I am suffering—all this might be
embodied in the document above mentioned And the <person_mentioned>people of
<location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> would thus do justice to the State, themselves, and to me all
at the same time. Some of the <person_mentioned>enemies of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> are beginning to
snear at those people by reporting in this <location_mentioned>city </location_mentioned>that they have 
abandoned me and wished me sacrifised—such an idea is injurious to the
character of those people and totally false, and ought to be refuted
by a plain, frank, and public statement of facts</p>

<p><person_mentioned>S. F. Austin</person_mentioned></p>
<p><person_mentioned>Mr. James F. Perry</person_mentioned></p>

<p>Sir I send you the above letter which arrived here on the <date_mentioned n="05-09-1834">9th inst</date_mentioned>
I have receive[d] your letter, as also <person_mentioned>Guy</person_mentioned>'s  nothing new, there will<barker_pb n="1060"/>
be something done for <person_mentioned>Uncle </person_mentioned>to day as there is a colecton [?] of
people in town to day   <person_mentioned>Clayton </person_mentioned>is to be tried for his life</p>

<p><person_mentioned>M. Austin Bryan</person_mentioned></p>
<p>In a letter to <person_mentioned>Sam Williams</person_mentioned> of similar import to this he used
these words " I was <hi rend="italic">incommunicado regororisimo</hi> from the <date_mentioned n="02-13-1834">13th Feby</date_mentioned>
to <date_mentioned n="05-09-1834">9 May</date_mentioned>—no book or writing materials & very little light—dreary
enough but the idea that <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>&c " Dated <person_mentioned>ex inquisición</person_mentioned>—<date_mentioned n="06-03-1834">June
3rd '34</date_mentioned></p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
