
<TEI.2 id="APB1123">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>04-29-1826</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1310- 1315</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Juan Francicso Buchetti</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Stephen F. Austin</document_recipient>
<document_title>Juan Francicso Buchetti to Stephen F. Austin, 04-29-1826</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Parish of Lampazzos, State of Leon</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Juan Francisco Buchetti to Austin, April 29, 1826. Instructing Austin to make preparation for his residence in the colony as priest. Reports are that there are few Catholics in the colony and that Austin does not require 
certificates from his colonists showing that they are Catholics.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes></barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1310-1315</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>06-10-2010</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>


<text id="APB1123T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Juan Francisco Buchetti to Austin, April 29, 1826. Instructing Austin to make preparation for his residence in the colony as priest. Reports are that there are few Catholics in the colony and that Austin does not require 
certificates from his colonists showing that they are Catholics.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><location_mentioned>State of Leon</location_mentioned>, <location_mentioned>Parish of Lampazzos</location_mentioned>,<date_mentioned n="04-29-826"> April 29th 1826</date_mentioned></p>
<p>Dear Sir,</p>

<p>I have already sent you a few lines from <location_mentioned>Laredo </location_mentioned>giving you notice
of my purposes and intentions of going to your <location_mentioned>Colony</location_mentioned>, the which, I
hope, you have received.</p>

<p>I now think advisable to inform you of my posterior Relations with
the <person_mentioned>President of the venerable Ecclesiastic Chapter</person_mentioned> of this See of
<location_mentioned>New Leon</location_mentioned>, <hi rend="italic">Episcopali Sede vacante</hi>, the <person_mentioned>reverend Doctor, D. Jose
Leon Lobo</person_mentioned>, on the subject of my being sent thither.</p>

<p>After having made known to him my intentions etc by letters
from this <location_mentioned>place </location_mentioned>(not having been able, as yet, on account of sickness,
to go and appear before him; but I hope I shall soon do so) I have
received his answer in a letter, writen in Chapter, which not only 
approuves my purposes, praizes my motives; but also encourages me to
go amongst you with the <person_mentioned>Curate</person_mentioned>, who is shortly to be sent thither,
(he defines not the precise time when) in the capacity of his <person_mentioned>assistant</person_mentioned>
to wit: 1o in lictis, as his <person_mentioned>lawfull interpreter for church affairs</person_mentioned>, 2° as
the sacristan a <hi rend="italic">Secretis</hi>, which implies steward, or clerk, of the 
depending Branch there of this <location_mentioned>Episcopal church</location_mentioned>—3° as the <person_mentioned>public
teacher of the roman catholic Doctrine and Dogmas</person_mentioned> in favour of the<barker_pb n="1311"/>
<person_mentioned>Anglo-americans catholic</person_mentioned> of your <location_mentioned>colony </location_mentioned>and, pro tempore, of those
of its <location_mentioned>vicinity</location_mentioned>.</p>

<p>Credential Letters patent of Licentiated commission are not only
promised me, but I am even requested to accept of them to enable me
to discharge legally those 3 <person_mentioned>offices</person_mentioned>. As for my maintenance, or 
Salary, as well as that of the <person_mentioned>Curate</person_mentioned>, I know not as yet how much it will
be agread upon or from whom it will be afforded; whither from the 
<location_mentioned>Colony </location_mentioned>or from the See? But for my part, I will try to make my 
arrangements with the See on that point. Our <person_mentioned>Curate</person_mentioned>, I understand, is
a <person_mentioned>man </person_mentioned>of very amiable manners and of a Strict Discipline, you will
have a good and vigilant <person_mentioned>Pastor </person_mentioned>of him.</p>

<p>I will not neglect to exert myself in praying as decent set as 
possible of Church Necessaries, of ministerial ornamental implements;
if they are to be sent from this place, or, ad interim, borrowed from
some of the <location_mentioned>missions </location_mentioned>in <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>.</p>

<p>The<person_mentioned> President of the Chapter</person_mentioned> in writing to me adverts rather with
displeasure in one of his letters that he has understood and knows
well that a good many <person_mentioned>heretics </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>protestants </person_mentioned>have introduced 
themselves into those new <location_mentioned>colonies </location_mentioned>etc. etc. and says that he will omit
nothing in his power in order to quickly prevent and effectually 
impeach the further dissemination of their anticatholic principles either
by words or Books within his jurisdiction and to that effect (he does
intimate) he will call upon the assistence of the secular Power of
these <location_mentioned>States</location_mentioned>, if necessary ? ? ? Maybe that <person_mentioned>Ulyo George Nixon</person_mentioned> or <person_mentioned>Dr
John B. Long</person_mentioned>, who has been at the <location_mentioned>Brassos </location_mentioned>and who lately went to
<location_mentioned>Monterrey </location_mentioned>to see him to be Baptized or some other <person_mentioned>americans </person_mentioned>have
informed him, as they have also told me, that they beleaved that
there are not 10 <person_mentioned>souls </person_mentioned>of real Roman Catholic in all your <location_mentioned>Colony </location_mentioned>and
that you, without exacting credentials of Catholicity, as duly bound,
indiscriminately protect and admit into it <person_mentioned>families </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>individuals</person_mentioned>
too well known to be pertinacious <person_mentioned>members of various heretical Sects</person_mentioned>?
But I hope that they have been mistaken.</p>

<p>I understand also that the <person_mentioned>president of the Chapter</person_mentioned>, in order to
avoid abusive impositions and deceptions on their part, will insert,
amongst other matters, in our orders of instructions that we should
recognize, refer, and admit nobody as <person_mentioned>roman Catholics</person_mentioned> but those
who can individually produce to us their regular, sealed church
Dimissorial Letters especifying which of the 7 sacraments they have
received, from the several <person_mentioned>R. C. episcopal authorities </person_mentioned>of the <location_mentioned>countries</location_mentioned>
from whence they come, according to the canonical laws of the
<location_mentioned>R. C. church</location_mentioned> in such cases. And all those who can not produce the
same, shall be, casually, considered as <person_mentioned>heretics</person_mentioned>, <person_mentioned>protestants </person_mentioned>or, at the
best, as mere <person_mentioned>Deists</person_mentioned>, to be refered and proceaded with according to
<barker_pb n="1312"/>
the further orders of the <person_mentioned>Ecclesiastical Authorities</person_mentioned>, as their several
cases might require ? ?—</p>

<p>Consequently, Dear sir, you will perceive the propriety of timely
advising all your <person_mentioned>catholic people</person_mentioned>, who might have forgotten or
neglected to furnish themselves with the sd regular Credentials, to
have immediate recourse to their original Records, by writing to their
respective <person_mentioned>Bishops</person_mentioned>, or <person_mentioned>grand vicaries, </person_mentioned>in order that they may be
sent to them and above all, their several individual Extracts of
<hi rend="italic">Baptism Confirmation</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Matrimony</hi>; for they will be the very
first things demanded, and, as <hi rend="italic">ex-officio</hi> exacted by us as a Sine quo
non:, so that this department of <location_mentioned>R. C. church</location_mentioned> may officially know
whither they have individually received the first Sacrament of
Baptism and which of the <person_mentioned>others </person_mentioned>besides, in order that we may 
procead to confer legally and validly the <person_mentioned>others </person_mentioned>not already confered,
as and when the case might individually require. No superiour
<person_mentioned>authorities</person_mentioned>, either Civil or Ecclesiastical can dispense anybody with
this. And we at our arrival thither, without that very first requisit
could not canonically and in good conscience proceed to officiate,
chiefly in the cases of Matrimony etc. etc. in order to confirm Lands
Titles etc etc. in gratiam talium) in favour of all such and even of
the pure nomináis, or self styled <person_mentioned>Roman Catholics </person_mentioned>? ?—</p>

<p>if there be, in realty, any <person_mentioned>protestants</person_mentioned>, or <person_mentioned>sectarians </person_mentioned>in your <location_mentioned>colony</location_mentioned>
who might wish, for approved motives, after being instructed in
the Catholic Dogmas, bonafide to abjure solemnly their erroneous
ways of thinking in matters of Faith and morals, they shall be upon
trial admited. Whom, I in pity of their ignorance of our holy
Dogmas etc, etc, and of their once maliciously preached and deaply
rooted prejudices against our holy<location_mentioned> R. C. church</location_mentioned>, I will for my own
part use my utmost endeavour to instruct them rightly by catechizing
them preparatorely to their being admited and do all that Charity
and prudence will dictate, so that by mild means they may become
incorporated with us in the <location_mentioned>Church </location_mentioned>and consequently be made thereby
the lawful civil <person_mentioned>members </person_mentioned>of this <location_mentioned>Confederated Catholic Republic</location_mentioned>, for
their own individual good and that of the <location_mentioned>Colony</location_mentioned>.
</p>
<p>I hope that they will all, without murmur, gladly and obediently
submit, and confirm themselves in every things to the established
rules and customs of this <location_mentioned>Diócesis</location_mentioned>—</p>

<p>And as for you, Dear Sir, you will evidently perceave that it would
be among other things, very conductive to your own and to your
<person_mentioned>peoples </person_mentioned>interests that you should not only [not] put any impediments
or obstacles to our future proceedings and exertions, but as duty
bound, it is hoped you would gladly second our plans, help and
protect us in effecting all those desirable things, so that your first
planted <location_mentioned>Colony </location_mentioned>of <person_mentioned>anglo-americans</person_mentioned>, being well moralized may not
only prouve a delightfull consolation in your old days but might<barker_pb n="1313"/>
also serve, to your own credit and honour as a patern of Moralty for
the others which are about to be formed in its vicinity—</p>

<p>But not to fatigue too much your attention, Dear Sir, renewing
my respects to you and to your <person_mentioned>secretary, Mr Williams</person_mentioned> and sending
my compliments to all and in particular to some of my own 
acquaintances in the <location_mentioned>colony</location_mentioned>, till I shall have the satisfaction of seeing you all
personally I remain your very humble and devoted servant</p>

<p><person_mentioned>John Francis Buohetti</person_mentioned></p>

<p>P. S. In case you should desire me to receive your commands on
any subject, you will direct your letters to me reccomended to the
cares of <person_mentioned>Dr. D. Jose Leon Lobo, Canónigo Doctoral, vicario capitular
y Gobernador</person_mentioned> de este obispado de <location_mentioned>Nuevo Leon</location_mentioned>, etc., etc., <location_mentioned>Monterrey</location_mentioned>,
so that through him I might receive the same</p>

<p>Yours &c                                                          <person_mentioned>J. F. Buchetti</person_mentioned></p>

<p>But, Dear Sir, I was forgetting to observe to you that it would be
very proper (if you have not already thought of it) for you to 
procure a Small Assortment of english Roman catholic approved Books,
for the use of the <person_mentioned>people </person_mentioned>of your <location_mentioned>Colony </location_mentioned>and of those of its vicinity,
for every <person_mentioned>families </person_mentioned>besides the schools will be obliged to have more
or less of them.</p>

<p>I thought advisable to enclose you the anexed List of those I think
the most necessary and usefull in the several cases of the people of
your own and of the other <location_mentioned>colonies</location_mentioned>; you may easesly obtain them
from the several <location_mentioned>R. Catholic libraries</location_mentioned> of the <location_mentioned>U. S.</location_mentioned> by addressing 
yourself on that subject to the <person_mentioned>Rvd Mr Dubourg R. Catholic Bishop of
the State of <location_mentioned>Louisiana</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>—or to the <person_mentioned>R. C. Archbishop of <location_mentioned>Baltimore</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> or
to some others, who upon application will (as duty bound) gladly
assist you, or <person_mentioned>agents </person_mentioned>in making a genuine Selection, at least in 
substance, of the s'd neaded religious and Moral Books, so that you may
not be mistaken in the collection but they would also indicate you
from whence they may be had at a reasonable price. For it is 
already too well known that not a few of Moral and religious Books
of a great many of those new <person_mentioned>colonists </person_mentioned>are anti-catholic both in name
and in substance, they being composed by various <person_mentioned>heretical authors</person_mentioned>,
enemies declared of the<location_mentioned> román C. Church</location_mentioned>— ? which Books all the
<person_mentioned>colonists </person_mentioned>who shall wish to commune with our holy román C. Church
will not and can not be allowed or suffered either to <hi rend="italic">Read</hi>, to <hi rend="italic">Keep</hi>,
or to <hi rend="italic">Sell</hi>,?? but they must be delivered up to us?— as orders will
be given to that effect by the <person_mentioned>superior (ecclesiastic) authorities </person_mentioned>of
these states.</p>

<p>But, may be it would be better not to tell them anything of it for
the present, so that they may not, being alarmed, abscond or hide
them.</p>

<p>And also a small collection of Spanish-English et vice versa, 
Dictionnaries and gramars for the <location_mentioned>schools </location_mentioned>among which if you procure<barker_pb n="1314"/>
me <hi rend="italic">Ainesworth's </hi>Latin and english Dictionary, I will at my arrival,
pay you well for it. etc and with some others roman Catholic 
approuved religious books as one of the s'd <person_mentioned>Bishops </person_mentioned>or some other roman
Ecclesiastic <person_mentioned>authority </person_mentioned>would recommend as very sellable and usefull
in favour of the <person_mentioned>angio-american settlers </person_mentioned>of those new <location_mentioned>colonies</location_mentioned>, 
Observing that, in order to their being lawfull, all moral or religious
book's to be introduced into this <location_mentioned>Episcopal Jurisdiction </location_mentioned>must be
purely and strictly canonical according to the several Pontifical
Bulas and the Decrees of the holy Councils and of this <location_mentioned>Diócesis</location_mentioned>.</p>
<p>Sir, I remain yours &c.</p>

<p><person_mentioned>J Feis Buchetti</person_mentioned></p>

<p>An indefinite List of the Roman English Catholic Religious and
Moral Books neaded altho their several exact titles and the <person_mentioned>Authors</person_mentioned>'
names of many of them are not recollected; but are desired to 
beprocured to answer, in substance, to their several, here especified.
intents and purposes.</p>

<p>Io The Minor, or small abreaged Roman Catholic Catechism, for
<person_mentioned>young people</person_mentioned>.    So many grosses &c</p>

<p>2° The Large or larger historical Ditto for <person_mentioned>adults</person_mentioned>; or such a one
as would be in favour of <person_mentioned>sectarians </person_mentioned>wishing to be instructed in the
R. C. Doctrine preparatorelly to their admission into the <location_mentioned>Church</location_mentioned>,
or some otherwayse styled approuved Doctrinal work to that effect,
one gross or so many dozens—</p>

<p>3° The vade-mecum, or Roman Catholic Guide 1 Gross or so
many dzens—</p>

<p>4° The R. C Missal being latin and english    1 gross &—</p>

<p>5° R. C. approuved English hymns, R. C. spiritual songs, with
or without notes, or some small Books conteining them or some of
them    1. gross etc</p>

<p>6° The history of the <location_mentioned>R. C. Church</location_mentioned> (in English) by . . . (not
recollected) but a well known and acknowledged roman C. Author.
A few Dozens</p>

<p>7° <person_mentioned>Bossuet </person_mentioned>on heresies (in english) or his history of the origin of
Lutheranism, Calvinism and of the <location_mentioned>Church of England </location_mentioned>1 gross or
so many—</p>

<p>8° Defence of the <location_mentioned>Roman C. Church</location_mentioned> by detecting and confuting
the Errors and prejudices of the <person_mentioned>Sectarians</person_mentioned>, or some otherwayse
styled works on that subject   1 Gross etc</p>

<p>9° An abreaged history of the R. C. Ecclesiastical hierarchy in
favour of Catecumens, or some otherwyse styled English works on
that subject, if to be had,    a few volumes</p>

<p>10° The Natural Eights and Privileges of the <location_mentioned>R. C Church</location_mentioned> by
I beleave and <person_mentioned>Irish R. C. Clergiman</person_mentioned>, or other approuved work of
that import, if to be had.   a few Dozens</p>.<barker_pb n="1315"/>

<p>11  The Private or secret correspondential Letters or answers from
a <person_mentioned>R Catholic Clergyman </person_mentioned>to another of the <location_mentioned>Church of England</location_mentioned>
by   a few Dozens</p>

<p>12  The R. C. Ministerial Ceremonial, or a work explaining the
Church service (in english) if to be had.   A few Dozens
</p>
<p>13  Ancient Canons or Discipline of the <location_mentioned>R. C. Church</location_mentioned>. A few
volumes.</p>

<p>14  The Martirology or some small abreaged histories of the
<person_mentioned>Martyrs </person_mentioned>if to be had   A few Dozens</p>.

<p>15  Some few abreaged Lives of the <person_mentioned>Saints   </person_mentioned>So many Dozens</p>

<p>16  The approuved roman Catholic english Bible with the 
appocripha and New testaments, both of the Roman vulgate. of the big
or small size, so many Grosses etc —</p>

<p>and with some others R. C. religious Books as some of the 
<person_mentioned>anglo-american roman  C.  Ecclesiastical authority</person_mentioned>  would  recommend—
ut supra jam dictum est, as above said—</p>
<p>Yours &c</p>
<p>
<person_mentioned>Juan Francisco Buchetti</person_mentioned>
</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
