
<TEI.2 id="APB4359">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>06-24-1832</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 792-798</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Stephen F Austin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>[Edward Livingston?]</document_recipient>
<document_title>Stephen F Austin to [Edward Livingston?], 06-24-1832</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Matamoros, Tamaulipas</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Austin to [Edward Livingston?], Matamoros, June 24, 1832. General description of Texas; population; political condition. People do not want to separate from Mexico. This partly due to suspicions of the United States aroused by
Poinsett. Looking to the time when Texas may be a separate state of the
Mexican Republic, he wants Livingston's opinion of a law providing that debts
shall not be secured by property and coercively collected. Most of his colonists
have suffered severely from the credit system, which such laws would abolish.
Sees many disadvantages and difficult points.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes></barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 792-798</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>09-26-2010</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>


<text id="APB4359T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Austin to [Edward Livingston?], Matamoros, June 24, 1832. General description of Texas; population; political condition. People do not want to separate from Mexico. This partly due to suspicions of the United States aroused by
Poinsett. Looking to the time when Texas may be a separate state of the
Mexican Republic, he wants Livingston's opinion of a law providing that debts
shall not be secured by property and coercively collected. Most of his colonists
have suffered severely from the credit system, which such laws would abolish.
Sees many disadvantages and difficult points.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><location_mentioned>Matamoras </location_mentioned><date_mentioned n="06-24-1832">June 24. 1832</date_mentioned></p>

<p>You stand before the <person_mentioned>public </person_mentioned>in the character of a <person_mentioned>philanthopist</person_mentioned>.
By your labors to ameliorate the condition of your fellow <location_mentioned>citizens</location_mentioned>
in their various relations with each other through the medium of
the <person_mentioned>tribunal of justice</person_mentioned>—your codes designed for the particular use
of <location_mentioned>Louisiana </location_mentioned>but embracing genl, principles applicable to all <location_mentioned>civilized
communities</location_mentioned> you seem to have given to the <person_mentioned>people of all countries
</person_mentioned>a species of tacit claim upon the richly stored treasures of your
mind in relation to the political organization of society and the
general principles of jurisprudence.</p>

<p>Should this view of the subject be correct, it will serve as my
apology for this letter—but should you deem it incorrect, I must
then solicit your kind indulgence for having intruded upon your
valuable time—hoping that the great interest I feel in the subject
will be viewed by you as an excuse for what might be deemd.
presumption in me.</p>

<p>It may perhaps not be entirely unknown to you that I have been
engaged since <date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1821">1821 </date_mentioned>in establishing <location_mentioned>colonies </location_mentioned>of <person_mentioned>foreign emigrants</person_mentioned> in
<location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>. I have spent the prime of my life trying to redeem that 
<location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>from the <location_mentioned>wilderness </location_mentioned>and feel the greatest solicitude for its future
prosperity. When I commenced there it was entirely uninhabited
by <person_mentioned>civilized man</person_mentioned> except the <person_mentioned>small villages</person_mentioned> of <location_mentioned>Bexar </location_mentioned>and <location_mentioned>LaBahia
on the San Antonio river</location_mentioned>, and a few scattering <person_mentioned>families </person_mentioned><location_mentioned>on and
near the right bank of the Sabine just over the boundary line</location_mentioned>-
since then the <location_mentioned>colonies </location_mentioned>settled by me on the <location_mentioned>Brazos </location_mentioned>and <location_mentioned>Colorado</location_mentioned>
rivers have progressed considerably and now contain a population
of about <person_mentioned>8,000 souls</person_mentioned> principally all <person_mentioned>natives of the<location_mentioned> U. S. of the
north</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>—other parts of <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>have also been populated by the same
kind of <person_mentioned>emigrants</person_mentioned>, and a sufficiency of the <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>has been redeem'd
from the <location_mentioned>wilderness </location_mentioned>to form a <hi rend="italic">basis </hi>for the future rapid population
and progress of the whole. The <person_mentioned>native Mexican</person_mentioned> population has
also augmented some, tho not in proportion to the <person_mentioned>foreign</person_mentioned>.</p>

<p>I have stated this much merely to show the fact, that the principle
difficulties those arising from the <location_mentioned>wilderness state of the country</location_mentioned>.<barker_pb n="793"/>
against settleing <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>are surmounted, and that its progress in
future will probably be rapid. <hi rend="italic">There will he population</hi>—which
of course forms a basis for political and social institutions</p>

<p><location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, under the <person_mentioned>Spanish Govt</person_mentioned>, was a <location_mentioned>separate province </location_mentioned>and after
the independence it was annexed to the <location_mentioned>former province of Coahuila
</location_mentioned>which together now form the <location_mentioned>state of C. & T.</location_mentioned> The act of <person_mentioned>congress</person_mentioned>
establishing this <location_mentioned>state </location_mentioned>expressly says that they are thus united untill
<location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>possesses the necessary elements to form a state of itself of
which fact the <person_mentioned>national congress</person_mentioned> are to judge. The formation of a
<person_mentioned>seperate state govt</person_mentioned>, may be more distant than the sanguine expect,
tho in all probability it will not be very remote. In anticipation of
this important event, many of the <person_mentioned>first emigrants</person_mentioned>, who have acquired
a <hi rend="italic"><location_mentioned>home </location_mentioned></hi>in this <location_mentioned>wilderness </location_mentioned>by means of toil and privations which have
learned them to appreciate its value—have anxiously turned their
thoughts to the subject of their <hi rend="italic">local laws</hi> their social regulations—
their state constitution—</p>

<p>The general basis which they have adopted and will most rigidly
adhere to, is to form <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>into a <location_mentioned>state of the Mexican confederation.</location_mentioned>
They do not wish to seperate from <location_mentioned>Mexico</location_mentioned>—and of their own accord
never will seperate. If such an unfortunate event should ever occur,
its causes will originate in the mistaken policy of the <person_mentioned>national Govt</person_mentioned>,
of <location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned>in relation to <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, and <hi rend="italic">not </hi>in the desire or in the true
interests of the <person_mentioned>people of that <location_mentioned>country</location_mentioned>.</person_mentioned> I state this as a positive and
permanent rule of action with the <person_mentioned>people of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> from which
nothing but the most aggrivated injustice can ever cause them to
deviate in the slightest degree. I deem it necessary to be the more
positive on this point, because opinions of a very different nature
have heretofore prevailed amongst some of the <person_mentioned>Mexicans </person_mentioned>and even
with many persons elsewhere. Those opinions are very unjust and
have had a fatal effect—they produced the 11 article of the law of
<date_mentioned n="04-06-1830">6 April 1830</date_mentioned> by which <person_mentioned>natives of the<location_mentioned> U. S</location_mentioned>.</person_mentioned> are prohibited from 
emigrating to <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, and caused the <person_mentioned>colonists </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>North Americans
</person_mentioned>generally to be viewed with jealousy which seemed at one time to
have extended to the<person_mentioned> Govt, of the north</person_mentioned> who were suspected of
having designs on <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>. Those ideas were all erroneous—they have
however pretty much passed away and I think have no weight at
this time with any intelligent or thinking <person_mentioned>man</person_mentioned>.</p>

<p>[Deleted by Austin: It is the firm belief of many that the real
objects of the plan of <location_mentioned>Jalapa</location_mentioned>, by which the <person_mentioned>Guerrero administration</person_mentioned>
was overthrown, was to centralize and aristrocracise the Govt, and
perhaps to monarchise it—whether that was the object or not I do
not pretend to say—<person_mentioned>Mr. Alaman</person_mentioned>, the soul of the <person_mentioned>Bustamante 
administration</person_mentioned>, personally hated <person_mentioned>Mr. Poinsett</person_mentioned> and a portion of his hate may
possibly have extended to his <person_mentioned>countrymen </person_mentioned>in general—he is said to<barker_pb n="794"/>
have been the author of the law of<date_mentioned n="04-06-1830"> 6 April</date_mentioned> before mentioned. It is the
opinion of many very good and impartial <person_mentioned>men</person_mentioned>, that the intreagues,
speculations  and  general deportment  of  <person_mentioned>Mr.  P------ </person_mentioned> would  have
caused any people or any Govt to loose confidence in the purity of
his intentions and even to doubt the good faith of the Govt, which he
represented—he was certainly an <person_mentioned>unfortunate minister</person_mentioned> for he has left
a prejudice against his <person_mentioned>countrymen </person_mentioned>in the minds of some which
nothing but time can remove.]</p>

<p>No, sir, the <person_mentioned>people of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> do not wish to seperate, and it is not
and will not be their interest to do so, unless they should be kicked
off. They will do their duty to this govt, but they will also have
an eye to the duty which every man in all communities, owes to
himself.</p>

<p>But to return to our future state consitution we have some few
<person_mentioned>settlers </person_mentioned>in <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, now bending under the weight of years, whose
youth was spent in building up a home in the wilds of <location_mentioned>Kentucky </location_mentioned>and
<location_mentioned>other parts of the west</location_mentioned>. The <person_mentioned>indians</person_mentioned>, the Buffalo, the cane breaks
and the forests gradually disappeared—population and <hi rend="italic">civilization</hi>
soon changed the face of everything. They rejoiced and looked 
forward to the enjoyment of a quiet old age in their once <location_mentioned>forest homes</location_mentioned>,
surrounded by their <person_mentioned>children</person_mentioned>, and by peace and plenty. It was all
a delusion—there was nothing real but the pleasure of dreaming that
thus it would be—civilization brought with it the <hi rend="italic">monied mania.</hi>
The hostile <person_mentioned>indians </person_mentioned>were replaced by <person_mentioned>civilized savages</person_mentioned> of a more
brutal and dangerous character, cold hearted unprincipled 
<person_mentioned>speculators</person_mentioned>, men who considered that to make a fortune, was the great
and paramount and only object of human life—<hi rend="italic">Lawyers</hi>, who found
in the labyrinths and abstruse sections of the common law, 
unexhausted and unexhaustable arms for the protection of tergifersation
quibbling and injustice, and for the ruin of unsuspecting and ignorant
honesty.</p>

<p>The <location_mentioned>forest homes</location_mentioned> of the <person_mentioned>first settlers</person_mentioned> were converted into scenes
of legal discord and contention—the <person_mentioned>first emigrants</person_mentioned> whose enterprise
had opened the road for the easy entrance of land and law harpies
were dragged by them into court and after years of ruinous 
suspence were finally told that they might live in their <hi rend="italic"><location_mentioned>homes </location_mentioned></hi>as tenants
or if that did not suit them they might go penniless farther west
and seek new ones. We have a few of another class who have been
reared in affluence, and were content with their situation—they 
enjoyed in a prudent manner what they possessed without jeopardising
it by grasping after more—their prudence and systematic mode of
living availed them nothing—it ruined them, for it gave them credit.
Their <person_mentioned>neighbors </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>friends </person_mentioned>needed endorsers, ruin, beggary, and the
total loss of <person_mentioned>friends </person_mentioned>was the result.</p><barker_pb n="795"/>

<p>We have a No. of another class-—able bodied <person_mentioned>men</person_mentioned>, capable of
earning an honest and competent living by labor—but having been
raised in a <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>where the <hi rend="italic">credit </hi>system prevails to such an extent
that everything is regulated by it where men of empty pockets and
emptier heads with a little credit to begin with, disdain to work,
and live by their wits, upon the earnings of honest <person_mentioned>laborers</person_mentioned>, they
have acquired habits of cunning and the art of imposing by 
appearances and fictions, which renders them nuisances to society.</p>

<p>We have some <person_mentioned>southern men</person_mentioned> who are longing after <person_mentioned>negros </person_mentioned>to make
cotton to <hi rend="italic">buy more</hi> negros—it is in vain to tell them of the 
demoralizing influence of slavery, of its ruinous effect upon the physical
energies and enterprise of the <location_mentioned>community</location_mentioned>—or to lead forward their
imaginations to the period (perhaps not very distant) when the
natural increase of the <person_mentioned>slaves </person_mentioned>will enable them to masacre their
masters and desolate the <location_mentioned>country</location_mentioned>—all stuff—the future will take
care of itself, and as to the present, nothing is wanted but money,
and <person_mentioned>negros </person_mentioned>are necessary to make it. The mass of the <person_mentioned>settlers </person_mentioned>are
plain honest <person_mentioned>farmers</person_mentioned>, working men—untill within a short time
past they have had no <person_mentioned>lawyers </person_mentioned>amongst them, and consequently very
little litigation. The <hi rend="italic"><person_mentioned>monied mania</person_mentioned></hi> did not disturb the repose of
the <location_mentioned>wilderness</location_mentioned>—it enters not the temple of nature they have had
time to contemplate from the peaceful solitudes of their new <location_mentioned>homes</location_mentioned>
the war of <person_mentioned>lawyers </person_mentioned>the intreagues of <person_mentioned>speculators</person_mentioned>, in short the
agonizing th[r]oes of <location_mentioned>neighborhoods </location_mentioned><location_mentioned>counties </location_mentioned>and <location_mentioned>states</location_mentioned>, under the
high pressure of the credit system. Having enjoyed a few years
of quietness they dread a change and [wish to] shield themselves
from the evils of the <person_mentioned>monied mania</person_mentioned> and the expensive labarinths of
the old law systems but how prevent it ? Here sir is the great 
question which we all wish to have solved. Many very wise and good
men have raised their voices for centuries past against the mal
organization of society, the rottenness of the old systems etc.</p>

<p>Books have been written and <person_mentioned>Rob. Owen</person_mentioned> undertook to teach 
mankind how to govern themselves. He expected to distroy the <person_mentioned>monied
mania</person_mentioned>, by making everything common. This distroyed man's 
individuality it confounded him with a common herd, character was
therefore of no consequence to him. Would not the reverse of <person_mentioned>Mr
Owens </person_mentioned>basis be a better one? The old systems recognize the 
individuality of property—to this let us add that of <hi rend="italic">character </hi>but
entirely divested of the weight which property gives to it—
character based upon intrinsic moral worth good faith and virtue without
any regard whatever to wealth. How is this to be effected? By
changing the old laws so as to base the credit system upon moral
character alone, and not upon wealth and coersive means—or in
other words to place the whole credit system upon good faith, and<barker_pb n="796"/>
annul all laws, (avoiding unjust retroactive effects) for the coersive
collection of debts all landed or personal securities, all 
imprisonment or process against the person or property for debts.</p>

<p>Under the present system the enquiry that is made when a person
applies for credit is what is he worth or who is his security? Under
the new basis it would be what is his character for good faith, 
honesty, and industry. The <person_mentioned>monied mania</person_mentioned> seems to be inherent in man
or perhaps I should say in <person_mentioned>civilized man</person_mentioned> it belongs to his nature
and never can be distroyed. It is and always will be the general
moving principle to all his actions. I speak in the general for there
are no doubt some exceptions.</p>

<p>If then our social systems were so organised that the never tireing
propensities of this mania could only be gratified by establishing a
solid character for morality, good faith, industry, and honesty would
it not have a powerful and regenerating influence on society? A
young <person_mentioned>man </person_mentioned>begins the world poor, and wishes to get rich—to do
so he must establish a <hi rend="italic">character </hi>for industry, and virtue <hi rend="italic">this </hi>gives
him credit? and constitutes his capital—during the first years of his
exertions his <hi rend="italic">interest </hi>keeps his bad passions in check for fear of
injuring his credit—it finally becomes <hi rend="italic">habitual </hi>for him to watch
and restrain himself and to be honest. Man is supposed by many
to be the perfect creature of habit. If so we have a guarantee for the
good conduct of the same person after he has made a fortune—the
guarantee of habit—to this also may be added that which naturally
proceeds from the love of virtue and a belief in religion, this latter
I think is absolutely <hi rend="italic">indispensable </hi>for the well being, and sound
organization of all societies.</p>

<p>I am well aware that the total abolition of the credit system as
it now exists will to a certain extent cramp the progress of 
improvement for a time. It would not only be impracticable in a <location_mentioned>country</location_mentioned>
that did not abound in natural resources or that depended 
principally on commerce but this would not apply to <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>.</p>

<p>It has become a matter of very solicitous inquiry with me to know
how far this system is practicable. What would be its probable
effect upon the advancement of the <location_mentioned>country</location_mentioned>, and upon the morals
harmony and character of the people. It would evidently be a very
bold and perhaps a dangerous experiment it would effect more or
less all the relations of society. My greatest doubt arises from the
fear that <person_mentioned>men </person_mentioned>who were injured by misplaced confidence would 
endeavor to seek redress by <hi rend="italic">personal violence</hi>—in fact this fear has
sometimes caused me to abandon the idea as visionary and hopeless.
Some of my <person_mentioned>friends </person_mentioned>however in <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>have full faith in its 
practicability and utility—they are very sanguine on the subject and wish
to see the experiment made.   They think it cannot cause as many<barker_pb n="796"/>
personal quarrels as the present system does. Some doubts of a
constitutional character have also occured to me. The genl, 
principles of the <location_mentioned>Mexican </location_mentioned>constitution are similar to those of the <location_mentioned>U. S.
</location_mentioned>How will it affect the <person_mentioned>citizens of <location_mentioned>other states</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> who have dealings in
<location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>to prohibit the coersive collection of debts there—how will it
affect debts contracted by <person_mentioned>citizens of that <location_mentioned>state</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>, in <location_mentioned>other states,</location_mentioned> or in
<location_mentioned>foreign countries </location_mentioned>who have treaties with this <location_mentioned>nation</location_mentioned>? Those debts
would of course be contracted with the knowledge by both the 
contracting parties, that they could not be coersively collected in <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>.
There would have to be an exception in favor of debts due to the
Genl, or State govt.—ought there not to be some others ? for example
in favor of <person_mentioned>mechanics </person_mentioned>or <person_mentioned>laborers </person_mentioned>for their wages—or of <person_mentioned>minors </person_mentioned>or
<person_mentioned>widows </person_mentioned>for <location_mentioned>property </location_mentioned>sold on credit to settle an estate etc.—of <person_mentioned>carriers</person_mentioned>
and <person_mentioned>freighters</person_mentioned>—how far ought the exceptions to extend or ought
there to be any? This system would probably greatly reduce the
number of lawsuits about 99/100 which would of course greatly 
diminish the number of <person_mentioned>lawyers</person_mentioned>—this would be an important point gained.
I wish you to understand that I have no prejudices against <person_mentioned>lawyers</person_mentioned>
merely because they belong to that profession. My objections are
to the system of laws that renders such a swarm of <person_mentioned>agents </person_mentioned>necessary
to administer them. [Deleted by Austin: if justice ought to be
prompt plain simple and not expensive—to be so the laws must be
plain, as few as possible, and accessible to the understanding of
everyone—not loaded down by a labarinth of forms, nor by the 
precedents and decissions of centuries past, which no one but a very well
read <person_mentioned>lawyer </person_mentioned>can comprehend]</p>

<p>The situation of <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>is peculiarly fortunate in some respects,
with reference to its future political organization, As a member
of the <location_mentioned>Mexican confederation</location_mentioned> its weight will be respectable—it is a
new <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>untrammeled by old and fixed habits customs or local
laws—a vergen soil ready to receive any seed that is sown upon it.
But few such opportunities have occurred of perfecting the local
organization of a <location_mentioned>community </location_mentioned>[such] as <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>will present.</p>

<p>I have no doubts as to slavery, it is now prohibited in <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>by
the constitution and I hope always will be.</p>

<p>I have trespassed greatly upon your time and cannot hope that
you will answer this letter to the extent that the subject with all its
bearings and details admits of, but I should esteem it as a favor to
have the benifit of your experience and of any other learned and
experienced man so far as the expression of an opinion, whether a
system based on the general principle that debts should not be
coercively collected, would be benificial in practice as applicable to
<location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>and what would be its probable influence upon <person_mentioned>society</person_mentioned>, and its
effect on human happiness.   I think it is a question worthy of the<barker_pb n="798"/>
discussion of <person_mentioned>Philanthropists</person_mentioned>. It is not entirely a new one, but it
needs anilizing—in fact the sifting and critical examination of a
public discussion. My object is to get all the information I can that
will be useful to the <person_mentioned>people of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>, and with this view you are at
liberty to show this letter or make any use of it you may think best
calculated to affect that object. The learned and pious in the<location_mentioned> U. S.</location_mentioned>
have devotd much of their time to the discussion of the merits or
demerits of the systems of other <location_mentioned>countries</location_mentioned>, with a view to enlighten
public opinion generally. Why not also take some interest in the
happiness of a new and rising <location_mentioned>country</location_mentioned>, their close <person_mentioned>neighbor </person_mentioned>and a
<location_mentioned>sister republic</location_mentioned> a <person_mentioned>friend</person_mentioned>.</p>

<p>I am now on my way to <location_mentioned>Saltillo the capital of our State</location_mentioned> to attend
the <person_mentioned>Legislature </person_mentioned>of which I am a member from <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, and shall not
return home untill <date_mentioned n="10-xx-1832">October </date_mentioned>or <date_mentioned n="11-xx-1832">November </date_mentioned>next. Should you think
proper to answer this letter it would be best to send the answer
through some person in <location_mentioned>New Orleans </location_mentioned>who would attend to 
forwarding it to me at <location_mentioned>San felipe de Austin</location_mentioned>, by some vessel bound to <location_mentioned>Brasoria</location_mentioned>.</p>

<p>[Stephen F. Austin.]</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
