
<TEI.2 id="APB4063">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>10-27-1830</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1922: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1928), 3 vols., Vol 2, pp. 522-524</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>James F Perry</document_author>
<document_sender>Mr. Hunter</document_sender>
<document_recipient>Stephen F Austin</document_recipient>
<document_title>James F Perry to Stephen F Austin, 10-27-1830</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>New York, New York</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>James F. Perry to Austin, New York, October 27, 1830. Merchandise for Texas, Galveston Bay, & Texas Land Co.   Books and magazines for Austin.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes>Original in possession of Mrs. E. L. Perry</barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 522-524</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>08-31-2010</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>


<text id="APB4063T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>James F. Perry to Austin, New York, October 27, 1830. Merchandise for Texas, Galveston Bay, & Texas Land Co.   Books and magazines for Austin.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><location_mentioned>New York</location_mentioned><date_mentioned n="10-27-1830"> Oct—27th 1830</date_mentioned></p>
<p>Dear <person_mentioned>Brother</person_mentioned></p>

<p>I have been here <date_mentioned n="10-22-1830">five days</date_mentioned> waiting on my Goods shiped from <location_mentioned>Phila</location_mentioned>
here to ship per Schooner Nelson they have at length arrived and
I hope to be ready to start—homeward <date_mentioned n="10-27-1830">this afternoon</date_mentioned>. The Nelson
is now owned by <person_mentioned>Messrs Wade and Sayer </person_mentioned>of this place and 
commanded by <person_mentioned>Capt. Fuller</person_mentioned> apparently a very clever man. The Nelson
will sail on <date_mentioned n="10-29-1830">Friday </date_mentioned>or <date_mentioned n="10-30-1830">Saturday </date_mentioned>and is intended to run regularly
between <location_mentioned>New Orleans</location_mentioned> and the <location_mentioned>Brazos</location_mentioned>. There is a number of 
<person_mentioned>passengers </person_mentioned>going in her among them is <person_mentioned>Mr. Wm T. Austin</person_mentioned> his <person_mentioned>Lady</person_mentioned>
and <person_mentioned>child </person_mentioned>(he is a <person_mentioned>brother of John Austin</person_mentioned> of <location_mentioned>Brazoria</location_mentioned>) <person_mentioned>Col. 
Woodburry</person_mentioned> and two of his <person_mentioned>Sons </person_mentioned>is also expected. I have seen <person_mentioned>Archibald
</person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>John Austin,</person_mentioned> <person_mentioned>brothers of Captn Henry Austin</person_mentioned> since I arrived
here they both are very much interested in your sucksess and are
very clever men they have treated me with a great deal of kindness
since I have been here. I have purchased between 4 & 5 thousand
"Dollars worth of Goods in <location_mentioned>Phila </location_mentioned>and will have about 3thd to send
from home which with some groceries from <location_mentioned>New Orleans</location_mentioned> will make<barker_pb n="523"/>
a very good assortment enough I think to make a tryal on. <person_mentioned>Mr.
Hunter</person_mentioned> will be in readiness to start as soon as I return from 
<location_mentioned>Missouri </location_mentioned>I will consigne our goods to <person_mentioned>McKinstrey </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>Austin </person_mentioned>at
<person_mentioned>Brazoria</person_mentioned>, part of the articles you wrote for is packed among the
goods viz Holsters Bridle Martingale Spurs and Boots and Vattel's
Laws of Nations in <person_mentioned>English</person_mentioned>. I could not get it in <person_mentioned>Spanish </person_mentioned>neither
in <location_mentioned>Phila </location_mentioned>nor in this place, the other <person_mentioned>Spanish </person_mentioned>Book you wrote for
is not to be found I have made every inquiry I could both in
<location_mentioned>Phila </location_mentioned>and here. Your other cloths was not finished when I left
<location_mentioned>Phila </location_mentioned>the undress suit was partly finished but, the uniform could
not be made for want of information how to make it Since I
arrived here <person_mentioned>Mr. James Treat the Mexican Consul </person_mentioned>gave me a
letter of introduction to <person_mentioned>Col [Mexia's] Ladey</person_mentioned> She shewed me her
<person_mentioned>husband</person_mentioned>s uniform and with the assistance of the <person_mentioned>Messrs Austin</person_mentioned>, I
have got a <person_mentioned>Taylor </person_mentioned>here to take a particular description of it and
when I return to <location_mentioned>Phila </location_mentioned>I will have it made and forwarded together
with the other coat vest Pantaloons Sword Sash appailetts and
belt by the way of <location_mentioned>New Orleans.</location_mentioned></p>

<p>I bought a poartable writing desk here for you had your name
engraved on it and put in the charge of <person_mentioned>Mr. Wm Austin</person_mentioned> for you I
have not procured the Book Case and Secretary for you my funds
run out but will buy and bring you one from<location_mentioned> New Orleans</location_mentioned>— I saw
<person_mentioned>Mr Learning</person_mentioned> in <location_mentioned>Phila</location_mentioned>. he has sent you some <location_mentioned>maps </location_mentioned>they will be put
in the care of <person_mentioned>Mr W. Austin</person_mentioned> for you the law suit with <person_mentioned>Fox </person_mentioned>does not
come to issue untill <date_mentioned n="12-xx-1830">december </date_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>Mr. Learning</person_mentioned> says it is very 
probable that it may be 12 or 18 months before there is anything recovered
from that <location_mentioned>quarter </location_mentioned>he was absent from the <location_mentioned>city </location_mentioned>most of the time I
was there and had not the Geonogical account which you requested
him to send you ready but he promised he wuld prepare it soon and
send it to you<person_mentioned> Messrs Gill, Ferguson & Co</person_mentioned> has promised me to
forward to you the <location_mentioned>Gazette </location_mentioned>and the <location_mentioned>Quarterly Review </location_mentioned>I have not
got the paper that the advertisements you mentioned was in I expect
to get the one that yours was in but the one <person_mentioned>Smith</person_mentioned>s was in I am
afraid I will not find but I will try and if I can find them will send
them by <person_mentioned>Mr Hunter</person_mentioned>. I have recd letters from <location_mentioned>home</location_mentioned>. They were all
well. I am afraid <person_mentioned>Woodbury </person_mentioned>will have trouble about his <location_mentioned>colony</location_mentioned>,
as I am told that <person_mentioned>Prentice </person_mentioned>(the same that broke the <person_mentioned>Kentucky 
Insurance Company</person_mentioned>) and <person_mentioned>Col Mexar [Mexia]</person_mentioned> has claims to it. What the
nature of these claims is I know not— <person_mentioned>Col Mexhas Lady</person_mentioned> told me
her <person_mentioned>husband </person_mentioned>was going to <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned><date_mentioned n="Spring-1831">next Spring</date_mentioned> to Settle that <location_mentioned>colony</location_mentioned>
and they say <person_mentioned>Woodbury </person_mentioned>has no claim to it, that he is merely an <person_mentioned>agent</person_mentioned>
for the others. It will be impossible for me to move my <person_mentioned>family</person_mentioned>
before <date_mentioned n="03-xx-1831">March </date_mentioned>and if you are elected to the Legislature it is possible<barker_pb n="524"/>
that you will be home against the time we get there   adieu   may
God bless and preserve you</p>

<p><person_mentioned>James F. Perry</person_mentioned></p>

<p>I will send you the <location_mentioned>Quarterly Review</location_mentioned> by <person_mentioned>Mr. Hunter</person_mentioned> I expect
he will be there nearly as soon as the Nelson as he will be in readiness
as soon as I get <location_mentioned>home</location_mentioned></p>.

<p>I have failed in procuring the necessary description of the uniform
Coat the <person_mentioned>Taylor </person_mentioned>could not describe it so that it could be made by
the description, as I have procured the cloth in <location_mentioned>Phila</location_mentioned>. I will send
it on my return to our mutial friends <person_mentioned>Austin </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>Taylor </person_mentioned>who have
prepared to attend to having it made here and forward to <location_mentioned>New
Orleans</location_mentioned> by the first opportunity and will probably be there against
<person_mentioned>Mr. W. M. Hunter</person_mentioned> arrives at <location_mentioned>New Orleans</location_mentioned></p>

<p><person_mentioned>J. F. P.</person_mentioned></p>


</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
