
<TEI.2 id="1686">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>03-04-1829</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1922: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1928), 3 vols., Vol 2, pp. 177-179</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Stephen F Austin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>W C Carr</document_recipient>
<document_title>Stephen F Austin to W C Carr, 03-04-1829</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>San Felipe de Austin, Texas</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Hazelwood, Missouri</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Austin to W. C. Carr, March 4, 1829. Sends him for record receipts for $2,000 from Anthony Butler on account of Moses Austin's debts. Progress of Texas and difficulties which he has overcome. Personal items. Interpretation of Jackson's election.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes></barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 177-179</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>08-10-2010</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>


<text id="1686T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Austin to W. C. Carr, March 4, 1829. Sends him for record receipts for $2,000 from Anthony Butler on account of Moses Austin's debts. Progress of Texas and difficulties which he has overcome. Personal items. Interpretation of Jackson's election.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><location_mentioned>San Felipe de Austin</location_mentioned><date_mentioned n="03-04-1829"> 4 March 1829</date_mentioned></p>

<p>Copy to <person_mentioned>W. C. Carr<</person_mentioned>/p>
<p>My dear Sir,</p>

<p>Since my last, which I beleive was in <date_mentioned n="10-xx-1828">October</date_mentioned>, I have had a final
settlement of accounts with <person_mentioned>A. Butler</person_mentioned> and have paid him upwards
of two thousand dollars, and arranged the balance in three 
payments in <date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1831">1831</date_mentioned>. <date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1832">32</date_mentioned>. and <date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1833">33</date_mentioned>.— The interest was all exacted to a cent
and in some instances compounded, which has caused the debt to
accumulate very much. I still owe considerably over four 
thousand dollars on it— this has been a cruel affair and has harrassed
me very much, more than any event of my life ever did, I hope
it is done with— Enclosed I send you an order to the <person_mentioned>clerk of
<location_mentioned>Jefferson county</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> to enter satisfaction on the judgement against
<person_mentioned>Bryan </person_mentioned>and My <person_mentioned>Father </person_mentioned>which I wish done, provided it cannot in any
manner be construed as implicating me, by construction, as having
assumed the payment of debts generally due by <person_mentioned>Bryan </person_mentioned>and My
<person_mentioned>Father </person_mentioned>unless where I am individually bound as was the case in
this debt—</p>

<p>The prospects of this <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>are brightening very rapidly and
<person_mentioned>emigrants </person_mentioned>of the most respectable character are flocking to it.</p>

<p>Perseverance and time have removed the obstacles that impeded
the settlement of <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>when I commenced. It was then a total
<location_mentioned>wilderness</location_mentioned>, destitute of resources, infested by hostile <person_mentioned>Indians </person_mentioned>and
without an organised Government and the real value of the 
<location_mentioned>Country </location_mentioned>unknown, or very generally doubted. When I look back at the
substantial impediments, that were calculated to retard or totally<barker_pb n="178"/>
defeat my progress in planting a new <location_mentioned>settlement </location_mentioned>in this <location_mentioned>wilderness</location_mentioned>,
I find abundant cause of surprise that it should have advanced at
all. I was of the opinion that perseverance and time would 
surmount them. The event proves that I was right—A few more years
and the prosperity of <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>will astonish many. I am bold to say,
that as a <location_mentioned>Country</location_mentioned>, taken in the general average, it is unequaled by
any portion of <location_mentioned>North America</location_mentioned>. You will recollect that I have had
<hi rend="italic">some opportunity </hi>of forming an opinion on this matter, for I have
seen this <location_mentioned>continent </location_mentioned><location_mentioned>from Connecticut to the City of Mexico</location_mentioned>, and
have generally been a close observer of localities, soil, climate, etc.
Apart from the peculiar value of the <location_mentioned>Mississippi river</location_mentioned> and the
<location_mentioned>harbors</location_mentioned>, I deem <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>to be of more intrinsic value as a <location_mentioned>country</location_mentioned>,
than all the<location_mentioned> States of Louisiana</location_mentioned> <location_mentioned>Mississippi</location_mentioned>, <location_mentioned>Alabama </location_mentioned>and <location_mentioned>Georgia</location_mentioned>
and the <location_mentioned>territories of Florida </location_mentioned>and <location_mentioned>Arkansas</location_mentioned></p>

<p>Our Govt gets on very well, <hi rend="italic">All things considered</hi> the federal
system was an experiment and a very dangerous one for <location_mentioned>Mexico</location_mentioned>
because their former habits and ideas as to political subjects, had
not prepaired the <person_mentioned>people </person_mentioned>for such a System, there must be some
collisions for a while, but good will grow out of them; for they tend
to elicit discussion and to diffuse knowledge. I may perhaps at some
leisure time write you a long and rather speculative letter on the
formation, progress and probable future advancement of this new
born <location_mentioned>republic</location_mentioned>, and notice some variations from their Model the
<location_mentioned>U. S</location_mentioned>—</p>

<p>This day belongs, most emphatically, to the history of <location_mentioned>North
America</location_mentioned>, I may indeed say to the history of the <location_mentioned>civilized world</location_mentioned>—the
<date_mentioned n="03-04-1828">4 of March</date_mentioned>, the inauguration of the <person_mentioned>President </person_mentioned>of a <location_mentioned>republic </location_mentioned>whose
comercial ramifications have penitrated every <location_mentioned>inhabitable corner of
the Globe</location_mentioned>, and whose moral influence has cheered every heart that
loves freedom, and thrown a gloom around the thrones of despotism.</p>

<person_mentioned>Jackson </person_mentioned>goes into office with the advantage of an overwhelming
<person_mentioned>majority</person_mentioned>, and should his <person_mentioned>cabinet </person_mentioned>possess talents and <hi rend="italic">" Management"</hi>
to retain their popularity he cannot fail to get through hapily and
prosperously— I am of opinion that his <person_mentioned>administration </person_mentioned>will in the
general be very popular, and very advantageous to the <location_mentioned>nation</location_mentioned>, for
I think that the experiments which have been made of the Tariff
Systim has clearly demonstrated the course that ought to be adopted,
and I think it will be adopted—Popular opinion will give this 
administration <hi rend="italic">all the credit</hi>, altho they may be governed by lights elicited
by others—I have taken no great interest in the election, tho I have
no objection to see <person_mentioned>Jackson President</person_mentioned>—Your Govt is founded on the
popular will—and agreeably to the principles on which it is based,
whatever the people will, <hi rend="italic">is right</hi><barker_pb n="179"/>

<p>I recd your kind letter of <date_mentioned n="11-08-1828">8 novr </date_mentioned><date_mentioned n="03-03-1829">yesterday </date_mentioned>and thank you for the
sentiments it contains— the dificulty I mentioned in a former letter
is all settled whether it will ever occur again I know not—</p>

<p>Please remember me very particularly to your <person_mentioned>daughters</person_mentioned>. <person_mentioned>Ann
Maria</person_mentioned> I expect will hardly recollect me. I do " long " to see you all
and to see <location_mentioned>Missouri </location_mentioned>once more, and I <hi rend="italic">will </hi>see you as soon as I can
arrange my affairs to leave this <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>so as to be absent one year—
when you go to <location_mentioned>Potosi </location_mentioned>remember me to them all there.</p>

<p><person_mentioned>Brother James</person_mentioned> has a <person_mentioned>son </person_mentioned>a few weeks since, he lives at a new <location_mentioned>town</location_mentioned>
we have laid off on the <location_mentioned>Brasos river</location_mentioned> <location_mentioned>15 miles from its mouth</location_mentioned> called
<hi rend="italic"><location_mentioned>Brasoria</location_mentioned></hi>, a name which I gave it for the single reason that I know
of none like it in the world. I shall remove below myself as soon
as I can get a divorce from colonizing perplexities, and I do assure
you <hi rend="italic">they are many</hi>—I am weary of them, a <location_mentioned>Small farm</location_mentioned> a moderate
independence and a <person_mentioned>wife </person_mentioned>would render my life much happier than
it is or has been lately—but I am too poor as yet (as to active capital)
to think of those matters— <person_mentioned>Brother </person_mentioned>has denounced me as an old
bachelor confirmed and hopeless and has undertaken to fit up a
fruit garden for me to growl away old age in. I shall disapoint
him I hope tho am in favor of the fruit and therefore remind you
of your promise to send seeds and roots to <person_mentioned>Mr. Cox</person_mentioned> of<location_mentioned> N. Orleans</location_mentioned></p>

<p><person_mentioned>Stephen F. Austin</person_mentioned></p>

<p>[W. C. Carr, Hazelwood, Missouri.]</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
