
<TEI.2 id="APB4242">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>07-23-1831</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 677-681</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter </document_type>
<document_author>Stephen F Austin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Thomas F Leaming</document_recipient>
<document_title>Stephen F Austin to Thomas F Leaming, 07-23-1831</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Unknown</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Philadelphia, Pennsylvannia</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Austin lo Thomas F. Learning, July 23, 1831. Estimate of leading Mexican
statesmen and forecast of election troubles of 1832. Gratitude and obligation
to Mexico for generosity and his duty toward his colonists. His methods
contrasted with those of other contractors. The plan of the Galveston Bay &
Texas Land Co.   Suggestions for publication.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes></barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 677-681</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>09-12-2010</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>


<text id="APB4242T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Austin lo Thomas F. Learning, July 23, 1831. Estimate of leading Mexican
statesmen and forecast of election troubles of 1832. Gratitude and obligation
to Mexico for generosity and his duty toward his colonists. His methods
contrasted with those of other contractors. The plan of the Galveston Bay &
Texas Land Co.   Suggestions for publication.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><date_mentioned n="07-23-1831">July 23. 1831</date_mentioned></p>
<p>I have recd your kind favr of <date_mentioned n="03-17-1831">March 17</date_mentioned>. and thank you for the
information relative to my <person_mentioned>mothers family</person_mentioned>— the embarrassments
in bringing the suit with <person_mentioned>Fox </person_mentioned>to a close are to be regretted, but the
law must take its course altho it be that of the slothes If <person_mentioned>Perry </person_mentioned>has
not sent you the 50 Dolls, you wrote for I will remit it, immediately
on receiving information that you have not recd it— I hope that the
suit will soon be terminated under the able direction of <person_mentioned>Mr. 
Southard</person_mentioned> for whose character I have always had the highest respect—</p>

<p>Things in this <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>are very quiet, the <person_mentioned>Mexican Govt</person_mentioned>, appears
to be settling down upon a more solid basis than heretofore— at
least there is peace all over the <location_mentioned>nation</location_mentioned>,—the civil dissentions have 
disappeared—   the administration of <person_mentioned>Bustamte </person_mentioned>has acquird the public<barker_pb n="678"/>
confidence to a great degree, and the probability is that there will be
no more convulsiones untill the next presidential election, which takes
place in <date_mentioned n="09-xx-1832">September 1832</date_mentioned>. How we shall get through that God knows,
but we hope for the best— The <person_mentioned>candidates </person_mentioned>are not yet fairly before
the public I expect however that <person_mentioned>Alaman, present Minister of state.</person_mentioned>
Generals <person_mentioned>Teran</person_mentioned>, <person_mentioned>Bravo </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>Santana</person_mentioned>, will probably be of the 
number The first never was a <person_mentioned>military man</person_mentioned> and is believed to be the
most able <person_mentioned>statesman </person_mentioned>of the <location_mentioned>nation</location_mentioned>, the second the most <person_mentioned>scientific
man</person_mentioned> that belongs to the <person_mentioned>army</person_mentioned>, the third is not much celebrated for
common sence, and the last is a sort of <person_mentioned>Mad Cap</person_mentioned> difficult to class—
The two first and the present <person_mentioned>vice president Genl. Bustamante</person_mentioned> have
befriended me, and protected my <location_mentioned>colony </location_mentioned>in many instances—- They
belong to that class of <person_mentioned>mexican politicians</person_mentioned> who wish to improve,
populate and civilize the <location_mentioned>nation </location_mentioned>so far as they dare attempt it 
particularly <person_mentioned>Alaman </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>Teran</person_mentioned>— It is quite doubtfull whether 
<person_mentioned>Bustamante </person_mentioned>will be a <person_mentioned>canditate </person_mentioned>for reelection, some doubt his eligibility
on the ground that the <person_mentioned>president </person_mentioned>cannot be reelected to a second term
untill after an interval of 4 years—others say that he is only <person_mentioned><hi rend="italic">vice
president </hi></person_mentioned>and the disability therefore does not apply to him— There
is no doubt of his being a very amiable man in his private character—
The same may be said with truth of <person_mentioned>Alaman</person_mentioned>, and <person_mentioned>Teran</person_mentioned></p>

<p>In this <location_mentioned>colony </location_mentioned>matters are getting on very well. The intentions
of the Govt, as to the <location_mentioned>colonies </location_mentioned>established by me are clearly developed
and publically manifested—that is to afford them every aid and
protection posible</p>

<p>The principles which have uniformly governed me since I began
colonizing in this <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>in <date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1821">1821</date_mentioned> are so different from those which
appear to have influenced others who have attempted colonization
in <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>that neither this <location_mentioned>colony</location_mentioned>, nor myself ought to be confounded
with the others— My object, the sole and only desire of my 
ambition since I first saw <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, was to redeem it from the 
<location_mentioned>wilderness</location_mentioned>—to settle it with an intelligent honorable and inter prising
people. To make a fortune, a great pecuniary speculation for 
myself, was and always has been and now is, a secondary consideration
with me, When I left my<person_mentioned> native Govt</person_mentioned>, and became a <person_mentioned>citizen </person_mentioned>of this
I considerd that all and every kind of political obligation ceased as
to the first, and became fully as binding as to the second, as if this
had been my <location_mentioned>native country</location_mentioned>.</p>

<p>More than this, I consider that the liberality and confidence with
which this Govt, treated the <person_mentioned>emigrants </person_mentioned>who came here in good faith,
and who conducted themselves with any thing like ordinary decency
or common sence, imposed a moral obligation on them to give in
return, at least common gratitude— in short my mottoes have
been—-   <hi rend="italic">The redemption of <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>from the <location_mentioned>wilderness</location_mentioned>, Fidelity and <barker_pb n="679"/>
gratitude to my <location_mentioned>adopted country</location_mentioned>—and to he inflexibly true to the
interests and just rights of my <person_mentioned>settlers</person_mentioned>.</hi> It is my boast to say, that I
have never deviated from these general principles, and it is a matter
of proud gratification to me that my <location_mentioned>colony </location_mentioned>has always possessed the
confidence of this Govt.</p>

<p>A fortune I have not made, on the contrary except my <location_mentioned>land </location_mentioned>I am
poor, but am satisfied, for I have fully succeeded in the main 
object— If speculation had been my object I should now have been
dashing in wealth in <location_mentioned>Europe </location_mentioned>or where I pleased, worshipd by the
thousands and dispised by the two's or three's (two or three out
of a 1000 is perhaps a low estimate of those who would be govd
by principle <hi rend="italic">alone </hi>when placed in opposition to wealth) <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>would
have remaind to this day, what I found it, a <location_mentioned>wilderness </location_mentioned>and many
of the <person_mentioned>Capitalists</person_mentioned> of the <location_mentioned>U. S.</location_mentioned> and of <location_mentioned>England </location_mentioned>would have been
gulled out of their money</p>

<p><person_mentioned>Others </person_mentioned>who have attempted colonization here have wished to make
a matter of great and speedy speculation of it. No one who starts
on that plan will succeed in doing any thing except to injure this
<location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>and throw it back many years. They have faild so far, and
strange to say, some of them have wished to throw the blame of
their failure on me, and have suspected me of an unfriendly 
disposition towards them, or towards their interprises, on the ground that
competition was disagreeable to me— such a suspicion displays a
total want of all correct knowledge of the subject. There can be
no competition to my injury with any <person_mentioned>others </person_mentioned>who have attempted,
or ever may attempt colonizing in <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>. The plan of the <person_mentioned>New
York company</person_mentioned> for instance is to send out <person_mentioned>families </person_mentioned>get the title of
a <location_mentioned>league of land</location_mentioned> made to each of them, and then bind each one to
convey to the <person_mentioned>company </person_mentioned>all but a few hundred acres, thus expecting
to monopolise the whole <location_mentioned>country</location_mentioned>. All of which is illegal and 
inadmissable—their misconception of the law defeats them, and they
attribute their defeat to the interference of <person_mentioned>others </person_mentioned>against them. In
this <location_mentioned>colony </location_mentioned>the <person_mentioned>settler </person_mentioned>gets the full amt. of land which the law
allows—the expences are light, and a long credit is given to pay the
most of them and then they can be payed in part in cattle or other
produce of the <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>which the <person_mentioned>settler </person_mentioned>can make off the land he
gets before it is due under this system how could the <person_mentioned>New York
company </person_mentioned>or any <person_mentioned>others </person_mentioned>take my <person_mentioned>settlers </person_mentioned>from me?— what injury
could competition do me?— They do not understand the matter at
all for the result would be that all their <person_mentioned>settlers </person_mentioned>who could get away
would leave them on their arrival here and come to me— besides,
most of the <person_mentioned>emigrants </person_mentioned>to my colony are <person_mentioned>men of capital</person_mentioned>, who bring
numbers of indented <person_mentioned>servants </person_mentioned>as <person_mentioned>laborers </person_mentioned>or a considerable cash
capital—</p><barker_pb n="680"/>

<p>It has been my policy to slide along without any noise. I 
discoverd on examining <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, that in point of soil, climate, and
natural advantages it was greatly superior to any other part of
<location_mentioned>North America</location_mentioned> that I had seen, or had any knowledge of. I saw
that its value was unknown to this govt, or to any body else. I
knew that I would be sufferd to go on undisturbed, because no one
believd that there was anything here worthy of attention and I
should thus lay a foundation, which could not be broken up by the
hungry swarms of <person_mentioned>speculators </person_mentioned>who would inundate the <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>as
soon as its value was known. Had all others followed my system
and kept <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>out of the<location_mentioned> newspapers</location_mentioned> the law of<date_mentioned n="04-06-1830"> 6 april 1830
</date_mentioned>would not have been passed prohibiting emigration from the <location_mentioned>United
States</location_mentioned>. My <person_mentioned>friends </person_mentioned>in that <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>have blamed me for keeping
so quiet, and for not adopting the bellows system so much the stile
in the <location_mentioned>north</location_mentioned>, and making a great blow—by so doing I should have
blown away my own <location_mentioned>foundation </location_mentioned>as others have done. But the time
for keeping quiet as to my <location_mentioned>colony </location_mentioned>has now passed, and I shall be
benefited by some publications and judicious paragrafs not too long
to go the rounds noticing the prosperous and happy situation [of]
my <location_mentioned>colony </location_mentioned>and its uniformly warm decided and inflexible 
attachment and adherence to the <person_mentioned>Mexican Govt,</person_mentioned> etc, etc.</p>

<p>[Intended by Austin for publication:] It is perhaps a matter of
some surprise that the only <location_mentioned>colony </location_mentioned>which has fully succeeded in
<location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, and which is now in a <location_mentioned>State </location_mentioned>of almost unparalelld progressive
prosperity should have made so little noise that its existence is
scarcely known, to the <person_mentioned>people of the <location_mentioned>U. S.</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> we allude to <location_mentioned><person_mentioned>Austin</person_mentioned>'s
colony.</location_mentioned> This probably proceeds from the character of <person_mentioned>S. F Austin
</person_mentioned>its <person_mentioned>founder</person_mentioned>, which is said to [be] naturally retireing and modest,
we are informed that when he commenced his <location_mentioned>settlement </location_mentioned>in <date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1821">1821</date_mentioned>,
he adopted certain leading principles from which he has never 
deviated—which were Fidelity and Gratitude to his adopted Govt.</p>

<p>That his labors should be directed to redeem <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>from the
<location_mentioned>wilderness</location_mentioned>, rather than to make a fortune for himself—that he
would be true to the interests and just rights of his <person_mentioned>settlers</person_mentioned>, and
never hold out any deceptive or imposing allurements to draw 
emigration, least many might emigrate without a sufficient previous
enquiry as to the <location_mentioned>country</location_mentioned>, and afterwards be dissatisfied, and thus
greatly injurd</p>

<p>Hence it is that he has slided along silently for ten years and has
founded one of the most prosperous <location_mentioned>settlements </location_mentioned>perhaps ever known
for its age in any <location_mentioned>country</location_mentioned>— we are assured by an intelligent 
<person_mentioned>gentleman </person_mentioned>lately from <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, that this <location_mentioned>colony </location_mentioned>is in the highest degree
prosperous—-that the <person_mentioned>emigrants </person_mentioned>to it in general of the most 
respectable class the society good—the greatest good order and 
subordination to the laws prevails, and the people are happy and satisfied<barker_pb n="681"/>
with their situation, so much so that they would oppose any change
of Govt, and they consider it an honor of which they proudly boast,
that they have always deservd and always possessed the confidence of
the <person_mentioned>Mexican Govt</person_mentioned></p>.

<p>[Stephen F. Austin.]</p>
<p>[To Thomas F. Learning, Philadelphia, Pa.]</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
