
<TEI.2 id="APB1847">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>01-29-1830</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1922: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1928), 3 vols., Vol 2, pp. 327-328</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Henry Austin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Stephen F Austin</document_recipient>
<document_title>Henry Austin to Stephen F Austin, 01-29-1830</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Matamoros,Tamaulipas</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Henry Austin to Austin, Matamoros, January 29, 1830. Discussion of transfer of Texas to United States. Mexicans jealous of Texas. Reports of revoluationary movement in Texas caused by Guerrero's emancipation decree.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes></barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 327-328</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>08-18-2010</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>


<text id="APB1847T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Henry Austin to Austin, Matamoros, January 29, 1830. Discussion of transfer of Texas to United States. Mexicans jealous of Texas. Reports of revoluationary movement in Texas caused by Guerrero's emancipation decree.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><location_mentioned>Matamoros </location_mentioned><date_mentioned n="01-29-1830">Jany 29, 1830</date_mentioned></p>

<p><person_mentioned>Col S. F. Austin</person_mentioned></p>

<p>My dear Sir I avail myself of an opportunity to your place to
send you a <location_mentioned>pamphlet </location_mentioned>on the transfer of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>.</p>

<p>Both <person_mentioned>governments </person_mentioned>were intent upon the measure, but I am 
fearfull the late revolution may retard if it do not defeat the project
altogether.</p>

<p>I send by the same conveyance a letter for <person_mentioned>T J Chambers</person_mentioned> 
surveyer General</person_mentioned> . Should he be in your <location_mentioned>neighbourhood </location_mentioned>do me the
favor to receive the letter from <person_mentioned>Mr Renolds</person_mentioned> and send it to <person_mentioned>Mr
Chambers</person_mentioned>. The object of the letter is to request payment for a set
of <person_mentioned>surveyors </person_mentioned>instruments which I brought out at his request and
have had here more than <date_mentioned n="07-xx-1829">six months</date_mentioned>.</p>

<p>The last season has been extremely sickly here. My operations
have been suspended more than three months by the sickness of all<barker_pb n="323"/>
my <person_mentioned>men</person_mentioned>. I am now endeavouring to close my business with a view
to leave this as soon as I can but it will take me some months at
best to get away.</p>

<p>The <location_mentioned>cotton gins</location_mentioned> sent you by<person_mentioned> Mr Coit</person_mentioned> were sent by my request
under the supposition they would be useful to you. You will please
have them sold for whatever they will fetch.</p>

<p>My <person_mentioned>Mexican </person_mentioned>operations have all proved very unfortunate and if
I should be so fortunate as to extricate myself from the present one
without loss to my <person_mentioned>friends </person_mentioned>I shall hardly engage in any others.
There is such an inveterate jealousy of <person_mentioned>strangers </person_mentioned>and so much perfidy
in the <person_mentioned>Mexican people</person_mentioned> that nothing conducted by a <person_mentioned>stranger </person_mentioned>can
succeed if they can prevent it. When I leave this I shall shape my
course for <location_mentioned>New Orleans </location_mentioned>and if circumstances permit will visit you
Our <person_mentioned>family </person_mentioned>has been truly unfortunate for many years past. You
are I believe the only <person_mentioned>member </person_mentioned>of it who has been successfull and
your success has been dearly purchased. Should a transfer of the
<location_mentioned>province </location_mentioned>take place you cannot fail to realize a splendid fortune
from your exertions.</p>

<p>We have had many rumors here of a revolutionary disposition in
the <person_mentioned>people of <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned></person_mentioned>on account of the decree freeing all <person_mentioned>slaves </person_mentioned>in
the <location_mentioned>Republic</location_mentioned>, the <person_mentioned>Mexicans </person_mentioned>appear to be very jealous of your 
encreasing strength and I think the conviction that <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>cannot long
remain theirs may determine them to sell to the<location_mentioned> U S</location_mentioned> now they have
an opportunity. <person_mentioned>Major Butler</person_mentioned> who is now in <location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned>as charge des
affairs has undoubtedly instructions to make the purchase if it can
be done on reasonable terms. Do me the favor to inform me at
what price a square league lands with a perfected title can be had
in the <location_mentioned>Colony</location_mentioned>. The acquisition by settlement is too tedious a 
process for me to undertake besides I detest every thing that brings me
in contact with <person_mentioned>Mexican authority</person_mentioned>.</p>

<p>your <person_mentioned>friend </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>cousin </person_mentioned><person_mentioned>Henry Austin</person_mentioned>-</p>

<p>PS, I have a <location_mentioned>printing press</location_mentioned>, and types, is it wanted in <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>It will not sell here as the <person_mentioned>people </person_mentioned>cannot read,   the value is 1500$</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
