
<TEI.2 id="APB4267">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>10-10-1831</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 696-698</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>John P Austin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Stephen F Austin</document_recipient>
<document_title>John P Austin to Stephen F Austin, 10-10-1831</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>New York, New York</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>John P. Austin to Austin, New York, October 10, 1831. Acknowledging commission to obtain dress and mantila and dressed dolls. Purchasers of scrip of the Galveston Bay & Texas Land Co. are suing for lecovery of the money.
Three schooners in port destined for Austin's colony; another leaving next week.   Presents for Mexican ladies.
</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes></barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 696-698</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>09-16-2010</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>


<text id="APB4267T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>John P. Austin to Austin, New York, October 10, 1831. Acknowledging commission to obtain dress and mantila and dressed dolls. Purchasers of scrip of the Galveston Bay & Texas Land Co. are suing for lecovery of the money. Three schooners in port destined for Austin's colony; another leaving nextweek.   Presents for Mexican ladies.
</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">


<p><location_mentioned>New York </location_mentioned><date_mentioned n="10-10-1831">October 10. 1831</date_mentioned></p>
<p>My dear <person_mentioned>Cousin </person_mentioned>;</p>

<p>referring to my last report I have now the pleasure to 
acknowledge the receipt of your much esteemed favor of the <date_mentioned n="07-27-1831">27th July</date_mentioned> pr
<person_mentioned>Mr. Sayre</person_mentioned>. Contents duly noted and will receive my particular
attention, and beg you will not hereafter hesitate commanding my
services whenever can be found useful to you.—The things ordered
will be sent by <person_mentioned>Mr. Sayre</person_mentioned>, or <person_mentioned>brother Henrys wife—</person_mentioned>whose <person_mentioned>family</person_mentioned>
goes out in the Nelson, to sail on or before the <date_mentioned n="10-20-1831">20th inst</date_mentioned> and trust
will reach you in due time and prove satisfactory— I can but think
you must have got the Uniform Coat I sent you—it went by such -
good hands—<person_mentioned>Mr. Treats</person_mentioned>—although you do not name it, and should
be pleased to know how it Suited. The Jacket will be made after
the same measure, and pattern of one lent me by<person_mentioned> Mr. Treat—
Mexican-Vice Consul</person_mentioned>—. I am to have the advice of a<person_mentioned> Mexican Lady</person_mentioned> as
to the Dress and Mantillio, and my <person_mentioned>wife </person_mentioned>will take a pleasure in
seeing to having than made as also to the dressing of the Dolls in
the latest and best fashions—</p>

<p>I hope you may not be disappointed in the expected Visit from
<person_mentioned>Genl. Teran—</person_mentioned>although a <person_mentioned>Gentleman </person_mentioned>who arrived here a Short time
since from <location_mentioned>Matamoras</location_mentioned>, says he had given up the idea of going—As
I should be much pleased to know his Views as to the <person_mentioned>Galveston Bay</person_mentioned>
and <person_mentioned>Texas land Company</person_mentioned>, and <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>in general, and I can assure you
any information you may give me on the subject, would be most
acceptable to said <person_mentioned>Company</person_mentioned>—</p>

<p>I have never doubted your friendly feelings towards the <person_mentioned>company</person_mentioned>,
as I have ever expressed myself when Called upon, as far as
might be consistent with your duty to yourself and <location_mentioned>Colony</location_mentioned>, which
could but be benefited by <person_mentioned>Settlers </person_mentioned>anywhere in its <location_mentioned>neighborhood </location_mentioned>if
properly conducted.—I understand several who have purchased
Scrip of the <person_mentioned>Company </person_mentioned>have commenced suits for the recovery back
of their money, after having been out and disappointed, in finding
no <location_mentioned>land </location_mentioned>of the <person_mentioned>compy </person_mentioned>to locate on. Say the <person_mentioned>Company </person_mentioned>have no <location_mentioned>lands</location_mentioned>
therefore a false sale. As each <person_mentioned>purchaser </person_mentioned>is supposed to have been
made acquainted with the terms of purchase I do not see how they
ere to recover, except it be by a point of law, for it was all a 
speculation between the <person_mentioned>parties</person_mentioned>— I am happy to learn of the continued
friendly disposition of the <person_mentioned>Mexican Government</person_mentioned> towards your 
<location_mentioned>Colony</location_mentioned>, which I believe has ever been the Case, and that it is prospering
equal to your expectation—<person_mentioned> Mr. Sayre</person_mentioned> is delighted with it and
takes his <person_mentioned>wife </person_mentioned>out with him. He is beset on all sides with inquiries—
Many men of respectability and Capital have been waiting to hear
his report, before going out, which they will find most favourable.
<person_mentioned>Mr, S,</person_mentioned> is considered a man of handsome property,   Some estimate<barker_pb n="697"/>
it at 20 to 30,000$—from what I have seen of him, I have been most
pleased and look upon him as Very correct and worthy of Confidence
and a great acquisition to your <location_mentioned>Colony</location_mentioned>—.</p>

<p><person_mentioned>Henry </person_mentioned>was most unfortunate in being sick, at same time fortunate
in being in such good hands.—He is now where I wished him to go,
years ago, and hope he may succeed, this much I am confident, he
will not want for a friend in You, and that you will aid him in his
plans as far as may be practicable—He has a large <person_mentioned>family</person_mentioned>—<person_mentioned>wife</person_mentioned>
and six <person_mentioned>children</person_mentioned>—but remarkably well Governed, and I think will
prove acceptable to the <location_mentioned>Colony</location_mentioned>—there are now three Vessels up for
your <location_mentioned>Colony</location_mentioned>, and a pleasing Sight it is to me to see their Sign
boards and to read them as I pass. Viz. Sch. Nelson, for <location_mentioned>Brazoria—
Austin's Colony.</location_mentioned>—Sch. Boston Packet, for<location_mentioned> Matagorda—Austin's
Colony</location_mentioned>.—Sch. Glide, for <location_mentioned>Anahuac Galveston Bay—Austin's 
Colony.</location_mentioned>—now quite a novelty here but will not probably be So long, for
I expect the trade will ere long rapidly increase—there is also a 
Vessel building to Sail from here about the <date_mentioned n="11-15-1831">15th next Month</date_mentioned> for
<location_mentioned>Brazoria</location_mentioned>, I presume by the <person_mentioned>friends of Mr Williams</person_mentioned>, for the 
Conversation I had with his<person_mentioned> brother-in law Mr. Sam1 St. John</person_mentioned>, a short
time since—<person_mentioned>Mr. St. John</person_mentioned> is a man of very hansome property and
much of a Gentleman. He is to leave this in a Short time for <location_mentioned>Mobile</location_mentioned>
and intends paying <location_mentioned>San Felipe</location_mentioned> a Visit in the Course of the <date_mentioned n="Winter - 1831">Winter</date_mentioned>,
at which time you will probably be at <location_mentioned>Satillo</location_mentioned>, as I am informed
thro my <person_mentioned>Sister Mary Holly</person_mentioned>, that you are to be absent some time
from your <location_mentioned>Colony</location_mentioned>, and will therefore miss seeing him.—This goes
by the Sch. Boston Packet, direct for <location_mentioned>Matagorda</location_mentioned>. She is loaded
with ready made Houses, Materials for d° Some Crates, Goods etc,
and is intended as a regular <person_mentioned>trader </person_mentioned><location_mentioned>between there and New Orleans—
</location_mentioned>A <person_mentioned>Mr. George C. Hale</person_mentioned>—I am told goes out in her with a View of
Establishing himself at <location_mentioned>Matagorda</location_mentioned>, and that he will proceed direct
to <location_mentioned>San Felipe</location_mentioned> on arrival, too good an opportunity not to write— I
also write <person_mentioned>Henry</person_mentioned>, from whom I am Very anxiously looking for
later dates, as well as from your good self—I shall do myself this
pleasure pr Nelson, to which I refer and remain</p>

<p><person_mentioned>J. P. Austin  </person_mentioned>  [Rubric]</p>

<p><location_mentioned>New York </location_mentioned><date_mentioned n="10-21-1831">Oct. 21. 1831</date_mentioned></p>
<p>My dear <person_mentioned>Cousin</person_mentioned></p>

<p>refering to annexed duplicate I have now the pleasure to add a
few lines by my<person_mentioned> brother Henrys wife</person_mentioned>, who with the rest of his
<person_mentioned>family </person_mentioned>take passage in the Nelson to sail in the <date_mentioned n="10-22-1831">Morning</date_mentioned>—I have all
of the things you ordered ready to send (except the Hat and that
was finished, but a mistake in the Color, being black, which am so
well Convinced would not suit, altho you name no Color, and an<barker_pb n="698"/>
opportunity offering next week pr Sch. Elizabeth which thinking
would be in time, I ordered an other made in place of it) and to my
no little surprise and disappointment there is not room in the Nelson
for them, or even for the <person_mentioned>passenger</person_mentioned>s baggage—<person_mentioned>Mrs Austin</person_mentioned> being
obliged to leave the most of her Trunks, furniture etc. I however
do not regret the disappointment so much as the above Vessel follows
so soon after and by which shall take good Care to forward them
and trust will reach you in time—The Dress and Dolls occupy quite
a large box, being necessary to be packed with great Care, not to
injure them—I have Sent <person_mentioned>Henry </person_mentioned>for you . . . , extra size 
Manifold writer, with extra Copying and Coloring paper. The Jacket
and Cord for pantaloons I shall send by<person_mentioned> Mrs. Austin</person_mentioned>, the other
things must remain for the Elizabeth. You will please accept from
me a Small box of Very Superior Shaving Soap, by<person_mentioned> Mrs. A</person_mentioned>—also
from my <person_mentioned>wife </person_mentioned>a Dozen of Shirt Collars and a Stock, made by herself
which, from having made some of same pattern for me, and found to
fit better than any Collars I ever wore She thought might prove
acceptable to You, particularly so when traveling as I think they
will at all times—false Collars are very much worn here. It was my
intention to have wrote you more fully by <person_mentioned>Mrs. A.</person_mentioned> but my time has
been so much taken up for the last few days in preparing for her
departure that I must close in haste and refer you to my next, which
I do the more willingly as an opportunity offers so soon again—
and run on—</p>

<p><person_mentioned>Jno. P. Austin</person_mentioned>.</p>

<p>P. S. I would refer you to a file of papers Sent <person_mentioned>Henry</person_mentioned>.—I enclose
a bill for the articles ordered—altho not able to send them pr
Nelson . . . which you will notice has been paid by <person_mentioned>Mr. Sayre</person_mentioned>— I
doubt not the cost far exceeds your expectations for I can assure you
it does mine—but we cannot be aware in ordering them, particularly
the fashions and dress, no price can be fixed—I think however can
best please the<person_mentioned> Mexican Ladies</person_mentioned>—which as you say is all important-
being so much admired here—the fashions are of the latest and most
admired, and by one of the first mantua makers in the city in her best
stile—I have letters from <person_mentioned>Henry </person_mentioned>as late as <date_mentioned n="09-19-1831">19th September</date_mentioned> but not
favored with any from you since the arrival of the Nelson but daily
looking for that pleasure</p>

<p>Must close in haste</p>

<p>Yours truly </p>  

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
