
<TEI.2 id="APB1320">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>11-05-1826</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1490-1493</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>James F. Perry</document_author>
<document_sender>Jared Cable</document_sender>
<document_recipient>Stephen F. Austin</document_recipient>
<document_title>James F. Perry to Stephen F. Austin, 11-05-1826</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Potosi, Mossouri</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Natchitoces, Louisiana</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>James F. Perry to Austin, November 5, 1826. Title to Mine a Burton tract. Biographical.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes>Original in possession of Mrs. Emmett L. Perry</barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1490-1493</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>07-17-2010</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>


<text id="APB1320T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>James F. Perry to Austin, November 5, 1826. Title to Mine a Burton tract. Biographical.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><location_mentioned>Potosi Mo</location_mentioned> <date_mentioned n="11-05-1826">Nov 5th 1826</date_mentioned></p>
<p><person_mentioned>Mesrs S. F and J. B Austin</person_mentioned></p>

<p>Gentln You have several times expresed a wish to know the 
prospect of recovering the<location_mentioned> Mine A Burton tract of Land</location_mentioned>. I long since
spoke to <person_mentioned>John Scott</person_mentioned> and his <person_mentioned>partner </person_mentioned>a <person_mentioned>Mr Alen</person_mentioned> on the Subject 
beleaving they could give as good an oppinion on the subject as any of the
<person_mentioned>atternies </person_mentioned>at the bar they being at that time imployed in a case <person_mentioned>R Price
</person_mentioned>vs <person_mentioned>Marten</person_mentioned> . . . and <person_mentioned>W M and S Perry</person_mentioned> where the tital of this
<location_mentioned>tract of land</location_mentioned> was to be tryed.   They [delayed] giving me there op-<barker_pb n="1491"/>
penion untill there would be a desition in that [case] which has been
had, and a few days since, they handed me there opinion in writing,
a copy of which will give you more information on the Subject than
any thing I can say which is as follows</p>

<p>We have considered the proposetion submitted for our 
examination with due deliberation. In whom the title of the <location_mentioned>Mine A Burton
Tract of Land</location_mentioned> is, and whether the <person_mentioned>heirs of Austin </person_mentioned>could under any
circumstances recover the property.</p>

<p>We are not perfectly satisfyed, that the title to the <location_mentioned>Mine A
Burton tract of Land</location_mentioned> from the <person_mentioned>Spanish Government</person_mentioned> to <person_mentioned>Moses Austin
</person_mentioned>was complete, But such Title as he had seems to have been disposed
of either by the process of Law, or by his own consent. It appears
that <person_mentioned>Moses Austin</person_mentioned> stood actually Indebted to the <person_mentioned>bank of <location_mentioned>St Louis</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>
in a Large Sum of money, to secure the payment of which he 
mortgaged a portion of the <location_mentioned>Mine A Burton tract of Land </location_mentioned>the <person_mentioned>Bank </person_mentioned>not
satisfied to close the mortgage alone to secure the debt proceded on
<person_mentioned>Austin</person_mentioned>s Notes, obtained a Judgement issued execution and Sold
the <hi rend="italic">whole </hi>of <person_mentioned>M Austin</person_mentioned>'s Interest to the <hi rend="italic">whole </hi>of the <location_mentioned>Mine A Burton
Tract</location_mentioned> the <person_mentioned>Bank of <location_mentioned>St Louis</location_mentioned> </person_mentioned>by there <person_mentioned>agent </person_mentioned>Become the <person_mentioned>purchasers</person_mentioned>,
and a deed was executed by the <person_mentioned>Sheriff </person_mentioned>for the same, this deed to
the <person_mentioned>Bank </person_mentioned>by the <person_mentioned>Sheriff </person_mentioned>though Incomplete for want of proper
acknowledgment and Seal we think gave to the <person_mentioned>Bank </person_mentioned>an Equitable
title to the property, which equitable title the <person_mentioned>Bank </person_mentioned>in circuitous
manner pretended to convey to <person_mentioned>R H Price</person_mentioned>. It appears that this
Incomplete title acquired by the <person_mentioned>Bank </person_mentioned>under the <person_mentioned>Sheriff</person_mentioned>s deed was
Subsequently Ratified by <person_mentioned>Moses Austin</person_mentioned> in his settlement with the
<person_mentioned>Bank </person_mentioned>and whether this Ratifecation amounted to a new deed or a
new acknowledgement of the sale under the <person_mentioned>Sheriff </person_mentioned>makes no 
difference so far as the equitable Interest created in the <person_mentioned>Bank </person_mentioned>was
concerned. If the amount of money for which the special <location_mentioned>tract
of Land</location_mentioned> was Mortgaged for [was] paid Independent of the General
sale of the whole property, then the <person_mentioned>Heirs of Moses Austin</location_mentioned> would
be entitled to the tract that was mortgaged, if the debt due by
<person_mentioned>Austin </person_mentioned>to the <person_mentioned>Bank </person_mentioned>was satisfied it was done by the sale of the <location_mentioned>Mine
A Burton Tract</location_mentioned>. If not satisfied the debt still exists against the
<person_mentioned>Estate of Austin</person_mentioned>. It appears that <person_mentioned>Price </person_mentioned>for and in consideration of
this property Released the<person_mentioned> Bank of <location_mentioned>St Louis</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> from a large debt
due by the <person_mentioned>bank </person_mentioned>of <location_mentioned>St Louis</location_mentioned> to the <person_mentioned>Bank of <location_mentioned>Edwardsville </location_mentioned></person_mentioned>and 
became liable to the <person_mentioned>Bank of <location_mentioned>Edwardsville </location_mentioned></person_mentioned>for the debt due the <person_mentioned>Bank
of <location_mentioned>Edwardsville </location_mentioned></person_mentioned>from the <person_mentioned>Bank of <location_mentioned>St Louis</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>, the whole of the 
proceedings appear to have had much notoriety. Now if the <person_mentioned>heirs of
Austin </person_mentioned>were to pursue and acquire that <location_mentioned>property </location_mentioned>they would appear
to be in the situation of <person_mentioned>purchasers </person_mentioned>with notice of the Equitable
title of the <person_mentioned>Bank of <location_mentioned>St Louis</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> or of <person_mentioned>Price </person_mentioned>under the <person_mentioned>Bank</person_mentioned>, <person_mentioned>heirs </person_mentioned>can
not inherit while their are debts due by the <person_mentioned>Estate </person_mentioned>and if the <person_mentioned>heirs</person_mentioned><barker_pb n="1492"/>
were to acquire this <location_mentioned>property </location_mentioned>we think they would take it subject
to either the <person_mentioned>Bank </person_mentioned>debt if unsatisfied or subject to the equitable title
of the <person_mentioned>Bank </person_mentioned>if the title still remains in the <person_mentioned>Bank </person_mentioned>or the equitable
title of <person_mentioned>Price </person_mentioned>under the Bank. If <person_mentioned>Price </person_mentioned>has regularly acquired an
equitable title it is then a question of some moment if the <location_mentioned>property</location_mentioned>
is worth pursuing under those clogs, which we consider incident to
success the debt with the accumalated Interest will be great nor are
we sure that the proceeds of the property would be decreed equal
to the accruing Interest of the debt</p>

<p>We have not been favoured with a view of the second opinion
of the <person_mentioned>Supreme Court</person_mentioned> as regards this title but the Law of the
Land protects Equitable titles against <person_mentioned>heirs </person_mentioned>or <person_mentioned>purchasers </person_mentioned>with
Notice and are inclined to think to pursue this case would be
incuring Cost expense and trouble that even success would not
remunerate</p>

<p>Signed           <person_mentioned>John Scott</person_mentioned> and <person_mentioned>Beverly Allin</person_mentioned></p>

<p><date_mentioned n="10-23-1826">Oct 23d 1826 </date_mentioned></p>                                                        

<p>from the above oppenion there is but a poor prospect of ever 
receving anything from that <person_mentioned>Estate</person_mentioned>. I have wrote to<person_mentioned> Edward Bates
</person_mentioned>for his oppinion as he stands now next to the head of the Bar and
has been employed in the above mentiond case [he] has had an
opertunity of becoming acquanted with the [title] of that 
<location_mentioned>property </location_mentioned>but he has not answered my letter yet. [My] opinion is 
different from <person_mentioned>Scott </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>Allins </person_mentioned>I will write [of it later ?] We received
<person_mentioned>Stephens </person_mentioned>letter of <date_mentioned n="08-21-1826">21st August</date_mentioned> forwarded by <person_mentioned>[Co1] Matson</person_mentioned> although
that letter was very full We are [sorry] <person_mentioned>Co1 Matson</person_mentioned> did not call
on us as he could have [given] more minute information than the
Bounds of a letter would admit of. Your <person_mentioned>acquantances </person_mentioned>in this
<location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>are I beleave quite well. You will have heard of the
death of <person_mentioned>Mrs. Wm C Carr</person_mentioned> and his only <person_mentioned>son </person_mentioned>before this reaches you
they both died in a short time of each other. <person_mentioned>Mr Carr</person_mentioned> is our <person_mentioned>Circuit
Judge</person_mentioned> he was here not long since he enquired very particularly
after you both. Now for <person_mentioned>Famaly </person_mentioned>matters We have added since
our marage two to our <person_mentioned>famaly </person_mentioned>a <person_mentioned>son </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>daughter </person_mentioned>prety well in
two years. <person_mentioned>Stephen </person_mentioned>is a fine healthy child and <person_mentioned>Emily Rosannah</person_mentioned> is
a fine girl six weeks old if we keep on as we have begun we will
soon have to retreat to the west for land to occupie the rest of the
<person_mentioned>children </person_mentioned>are all very well. <person_mentioned>Joel </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>Austin </person_mentioned>goes to <location_mentioned>school </location_mentioned>and are
improving some under <person_mentioned>Mr Brickey</person_mentioned>['s] direction though not so fast as
I think they might under a better teacher Write to us often as we
are allways anxious to hear from you</p>

<p><person_mentioned>Jas. F. Perry</person_mentioned></p>

<p>[In Margins:] <person_mentioned>S.</person_mentioned> your old flame <person_mentioned>Miss Isabella Hord</person_mentioned> [has turned]
<person_mentioned>methodist </person_mentioned>and is going to heaven as fast as possible.   <person_mentioned> Mrs. John<barker_pb n="1493"/>
[Bri]ckey</person_mentioned> is dead she died <date_mentioned n="Spring - 1826">last spring</date_mentioned>. <person_mentioned>Abraham Brinker Esq
</person_mentioned>after twelve years electioneering [he has] been elected to the 
<person_mentioned>Legislature</person_mentioned>. <person_mentioned>Thompson H Ficklin</person_mentioned> is our other <person_mentioned>representative </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>Edward
Bates</person_mentioned> was elected to <person_mentioned>congress </person_mentioned>in [the place] of <person_mentioned>Scott</person_mentioned>. <person_mentioned>Scott </person_mentioned>and
<person_mentioned>Benton </person_mentioned>are now condi dates for the <person_mentioned>United States Senate</person_mentioned>. [It is
thought?] by many <person_mentioned>Scott </person_mentioned>will oust <person_mentioned>Benton</person_mentioned></p>

<p><person_mentioned>Emily </person_mentioned>is anxious to remove to your <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>but unless the 
prospects are very flattering I think it is verry doutfull whether ever
we remove there</p>

<p>[Addressed] <person_mentioned>Co1. Stepehn F Austin</person_mentioned> <location_mentioned>San Philip D Austin Rio
Brases Provance of Texas</location_mentioned></p>

<p>To the Care of <person_mentioned>Jared Cable Esq</person_mentioned> <location_mentioned>Natchetoches</location_mentioned></p>


</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
