
<TEI.2 id="APB4395">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>08-02-1832</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 829-831</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>James Whiteside</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Anthony Butler</document_recipient>
<document_title>James Whiteside to Anthony Butler, 08-02-1832</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Coles Settlement, Texas</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Mexico</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>James Whitesides to Anthony Butler, August 2,1832. Butler's business interests in Texas.   Political conditions.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes>Original in possession of Mrs. E. L. Perry</barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 829-831</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>09-29-2010</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>


<text id="APB4395T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>James Whitesides to Anthony Butler, August 2,1832. Butler's business interests in Texas.   Political conditions.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><location_mentioned>Coles Settlement</location_mentioned> <date_mentioned n="08-02-1832">2nd, August 1832</date_mentioned></p>
<p><person_mentioned>Col A Butler</person_mentioned></p>

<p>Dear Sir When you was here last we had a conversation 
Respecting the debts that <person_mentioned>Mr. Peyton</person_mentioned> was Owing in this <location_mentioned>Colony</location_mentioned>, you
Remarked to me that if <person_mentioned>Peyton </person_mentioned>would mortgage his property to you
that you would lend him the money to pay his debts, I told <person_mentioned>Peyton</person_mentioned>
of the talk that we had, and since that Time he has requested me to
write you on the Subject, he owns 12 likely <person_mentioned>negroes</person_mentioned>, 6 of them
likely <person_mentioned>fellows</person_mentioned>, 4 <person_mentioned>women </person_mentioned>and 2 <person_mentioned>children </person_mentioned>60 acres of land under good
fence and in cultivation a <location_mentioned>horse mill</location_mentioned> that grinds for the <location_mentioned>Town </location_mentioned>and
Country Round about it, all of which he will mortgage to you for the
use of twenty five hundred dollars, and to give you a good 
interest, he has either to sell some of his <person_mentioned>negroes </person_mentioned>and land or Mortgage
his property. I had forgot to mention his <location_mentioned>Town property</location_mentioned>, it is
worth fifteen Hundred Dollars he has heretofore been offered that
sum for it, he has to pay a good sum of money this fall and if he
dont succeed in some way, his property will suffer, he is willing to
give you any interest you may think proper to ask. You will please
to give an immediate answer to this matter if you think proper to
accomodate him I will get <person_mentioned>Col Thos J Chambers </person_mentioned>to do the writing
between you and him, <person_mentioned>Mr. John R Jones</person_mentioned> has got two <person_mentioned>men </person_mentioned>at work
at the <location_mentioned>well</location_mentioned>, but has only got about 30 feet deep in about 3 weaks
<location_mentioned>work Pit</location_mentioned> has Caved in all Round & fild up half-way with sand, has
got Timber to build a very large <location_mentioned>stable </location_mentioned>that will hold 30 horses has
entered into a writen contract with a <person_mentioned>Mr Bartlet</person_mentioned> to put the <location_mentioned>stable</location_mentioned>
on the lots at his own expense for $600, he has got the most of the
lumber for building the <location_mentioned>Dining Room</location_mentioned>, and is agoing to have it a
<location_mentioned>two Story House</location_mentioned>, I think it will cost at least $1200—it will take
about Ten thousand Bricks to wall the <location_mentioned>well</location_mentioned>, <person_mentioned>Jones </person_mentioned>says the <location_mentioned>well </location_mentioned>will
cost about $300 he says he must have a new post and plank fence
made round the lots the Bricks are made for all the chimneys and
I have a waggon going to <location_mentioned>Harrisburg </location_mentioned>after shells to make lime,
I told <person_mentioned>Jones </person_mentioned>that I thought that the improvement he was puting
on would cost $2500 I wanted to know of him what he would be
Willing to give for the Rent, he said he had offered you $400 pr
year after the improvements was compleated, I told him that you
had no idea that him <person_mentioned>Jones </person_mentioned>was going to put such costly improve-<barker_pb n="830"/>
ments on the lots, I told <person_mentioned>Jones </person_mentioned>that you was drawing 10 pr cent
on your money and to lay it out on building or anything else that
would Decay it would not be Seasonable to suppose that you would
take the interest of your money and be satisfied, he wants me to
say to you that he should like to know the least you will take, he
Requested me to tel you that times were very Dull, and that is a
fact, no imigration at all everything here has been in confusion,
<person_mentioned>Col Bradburn</person_mentioned> at <location_mentioned>Anahuac </location_mentioned>Calaboosed some of our <person_mentioned>citizens </person_mentioned><person_mentioned>Patrick
Jack</person_mentioned> <person_mentioned>Monroe Edwards</person_mentioned> and a man by the name of <person_mentioned>Travis a Lawyer</person_mentioned>,
<person_mentioned>Bradburn </person_mentioned>kept them there fifty days, and until he was himself 
arrested, the <person_mentioned>prinsoners </person_mentioned>was then Turned out, but not till after there
had been many lives lost on both sides, since that time <person_mentioned>Wm H. Jack
</person_mentioned>has undertaken to <person_mentioned>Cain Majr Lewis</person_mentioned>, he give <person_mentioned>Lewis </person_mentioned>a couple of
Blows with a stick, <person_mentioned>Lewis </person_mentioned>drew a pistol on him, <person_mentioned>Jack </person_mentioned>retreated pretty
fast <person_mentioned>Lewis </person_mentioned>challenged him the next morning and <person_mentioned>Jack </person_mentioned>accepted,
they have choose their <person_mentioned>seconds</person_mentioned>, <person_mentioned>McQueen </person_mentioned>for<person_mentioned> Lewis </person_mentioned><person_mentioned>McKinney </person_mentioned>for
<person_mentioned>Jack</person_mentioned>, I do not know when they will fight.—</p>

<p>I wrote you in my last I had sent <person_mentioned>Mr Jerard </person_mentioned>after the Mares and
on his way he met <person_mentioned>James Kerr</person_mentioned> coming to <location_mentioned>San Felipe</location_mentioned>, <person_mentioned>Jerard </person_mentioned>went to
<location_mentioned>Gonzales </location_mentioned>to wait untill <person_mentioned>Kerr </person_mentioned>would Return he remained so long at
<location_mentioned>San Felipe</location_mentioned> that <person_mentioned>Jerard </person_mentioned>would not wait any longer, <person_mentioned>Kerr </person_mentioned>has now
started home, I had a goodeal of talk with him I give him your
letter, he Read it and said he could prove that<person_mentioned> Albert Pettus</person_mentioned> was not
in company with him when the Mares was purchased, him and <person_mentioned>Albert</person_mentioned>
had some sort of falling out and parted, I told him that you thought
very Strang that there was no increece on the 10 mares <date_mentioned n="1829-1831">from 1829 to
1831</date_mentioned> he said that he had told <person_mentioned>Col Pettus</person_mentioned> that he intended to put in 7
yearlings he thought that was about right I told him I was directed
to Receive Just what he delivered to me and ask no questions, I have
now got <person_mentioned>Joshua Parker</person_mentioned> to go out and bring thim in and I will write
you again, I inquired of <person_mentioned>Kerr </person_mentioned>what sort of a Jack he had got he
said he was not first Rate tho he said he was only four years old,</p>

<p>I wrote to <person_mentioned>David Tally</person_mentioned> to come and see me, he has never done so
nor even answered my letter, I have made all sorts of inquiry 
concerning his circumstance and find he has not Cattle nor very little of
any thing else, besides his land, you must now Tell me what I shall
do next,<person_mentioned> Robert M. Williamson</person_mentioned> gives me fair promises Respecting the
nine Cows and Calves, <person_mentioned>Col Austin</person_mentioned> arrived here a few days since
from <location_mentioned>Matemoris </location_mentioned>but could [not] stay long enough to do any business,
he is now gone to <location_mentioned>Anahuac </location_mentioned>and will not Return under ten days, I
Rode with him about two miles and I had [a talk?] with him. I
showed him my instructions from you, he was pleased to hear that
Cows and Calves were wanted, he said he Could always get Cows and<barker_pb n="831"/>
Calves, but money was out of the question he has to be at <location_mentioned>Matemoria</location_mentioned>
by the <date_mentioned n="08-20-1832">20th instant</date_mentioned> so that I cannot make any settlement with him
untill after he Returns from the <date_mentioned n="Fall-1832">fall </date_mentioned>Session at <location_mentioned>Saltillo</location_mentioned>, I must now
tell you a little more about <person_mentioned>Jack </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>Lewis </person_mentioned>there was what is called
the <person_mentioned>San Felipe Club</person_mentioned> five or six men <person_mentioned>O Jones at the head of them,</person_mentioned>
<person_mentioned>F. W. Johnson</person_mentioned> <person_mentioned>E. M. Williamson</person_mentioned> <person_mentioned>Doctor Miller</person_mentioned><person_mentioned> Col Pettus</person_mentioned> <person_mentioned>Thos
Gay</person_mentioned> and <person_mentioned>Wm H Jack</person_mentioned> they intended to Brake down <person_mentioned>Lewis </person_mentioned>and
<person_mentioned>Chambers </person_mentioned>because they were Reather taking the lead, the club put it
on <person_mentioned>Jack </person_mentioned>to bring on the quarrel he brought it on Reather too Rough,
They find that they are Compelled [to] fight and now they all left
<person_mentioned>Jack </person_mentioned>to fight by himself Except <person_mentioned>Wmson </person_mentioned>he stays, the balance is
gone to the <location_mentioned>Buffello Grange</location_mentioned> <person_mentioned>Lewis </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>Chambers </person_mentioned>says they shall all
fight or knock under,</p>

<p>You mentioned in your letter that <person_mentioned>Tom </person_mentioned>was blind of an eye, that
you presumed I did not know it, or I would unquestionably have
mentioned it, I never did know he was blind, he got one of his
hurt and there come a sort of phelm on it, I had some glass pounded
up very fine and blew it in his eye and it took it all off in one
night and I never discovered anything the matter afterwards,</p>

<p>As soon as <person_mentioned>Col Austin</person_mentioned> returns from <location_mentioned>Anahuac </location_mentioned>I shall make 
arrangements to get the Cows and Calves and do the best I can
with the mares and colts and as soon as the Dueling scrape is
over I will write you again or anything else that I think will be
of any interest for you to hear of my <person_mentioned>wife </person_mentioned>sends her best 
complements to you and says if you ever come to <location_mentioned>San Felipe </location_mentioned>again you
must take time to come and see her</p>

<p><person_mentioned>James Whiteside</person_mentioned></p>

<p>P. S. everybody in this country has declared in favor of the
plan of <person_mentioned>Genl Santa Ana</person_mentioned> and the<person_mentioned> Mexican troops</person_mentioned> is all to be taken
from this <location_mentioned>country</location_mentioned>,</p>

<p><person_mentioned>JW</person_mentioned></p>

<p>[Addressed:] Al <person_mentioned>Señor Coronel D Antonio Butler Ministro de
los <location_mentioned>Estados Unidos de America</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> <location_mentioned>Mexico</location_mentioned></p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
