
<TEI.2 id="APB4170">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>03-15-1831</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 613</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Henry Austin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Stephen F Austin</document_recipient>
<document_title>Henry Austin to Stephen F Austin, 03-15-1831</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>New Orleans, Louisiana</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Saltillo, Coahuila</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Henry Austin to Austin, New Orleans, March 15, 1831. Cotton mills for Texas. Emigrants rapidly filling Austin's contracts. Galveston Bay & Texas Land Co. carrying on frenzied speculation, and will attract too much attention to Texas on part of the Government.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes></barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 613</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>09-08-2010</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>


<text id="APB4170T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Henry Austin to Austin, New Orleans, March 15, 1831. Cotton mills for Texas. Emigrants rapidly filling Austin's contracts. Galveston Bay & Texas Land Co. carrying on frenzied speculation, and will attract too much attention to Texas on part of the Government.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><location_mentioned>New Orleans</location_mentioned><date_mentioned n="03-15-1831"> March 15th 1831</date_mentioned></p>
<p><person_mentioned>Col S F Austin</person_mentioned></p>

<p><hi rend="italic"><location_mentioned>Saltillo</location_mentioned></hi></p>
<p>My Dear Sir</p>

<p>I wrote you by the Surprize for <location_mentioned>Matamoros </location_mentioned>on the subject of
<person_mentioned>Mr Wares</person_mentioned> proposal to establish a<location_mentioned> cotton factory</location_mentioned> in the <location_mentioned>colony</location_mentioned>. The
matter appears to me of so much moment, and the chance of letters
reaching <person_mentioned>Saltillo </person_mentioned>so small I think it advisable to repeat the sub-<barker_pb n="614"/>
stance of that letter. The immediate establishment of a <location_mentioned>manufactory</location_mentioned>
of a 1000 spindles with a capital of 40,000$ would not only 
encourage the cultivation of cotton in the <person_mentioned>interior </person_mentioned>but promptly produce
a specie circulating medium by furnishing a comodity for 
legitimate trade with the <location_mentioned>interior of Mexico</location_mentioned>, and the establishment would
be rapidly encreased if suscessful, which appears to me certain
unless political disturbances should occur. <person_mentioned>Mr Ware</person_mentioned> has not only a
large cash capital of his own but ability to command any amount
that can be securely and profitably invested. He proposes as I wrote
you to embark 40.000$ in the establishment of a <location_mentioned>Cotton manufactory
</location_mentioned>in the <location_mentioned>Colony</location_mentioned>, provided he can have permission so to do, and your
protection and support, that is if he can be assured no 
impediments will be thrown in his way to defeat the object. Such as
priveleges to others, denied to him, excessive taxes etc. I have told
him as my opinion that as the establishment of <location_mentioned>cotton manufactorys
</location_mentioned>is a favorite project with the <person_mentioned>Govt </person_mentioned>and the location of one in the
<location_mentioned>colony </location_mentioned>obviously calculated to promote the permanent interests of
the <location_mentioned>State </location_mentioned>and people he might safely calculate on your giving the
project all the encouragement in your power consistently with your
public duty and that I had but little doubt you would obtain for his
benefit an increased <location_mentioned>grant of land</location_mentioned> in consideration of the project
being carried into immediate effect, perhaps <location_mentioned>five possibly eleven
leagues</location_mentioned>. He then said if you would do so he would allow you a
share of the profits for getting him the land, but on my observing I
had doubts whether you would allow your private interest to 
influence your public duty he observed then that in case of obtaining
<location_mentioned>eleven leagues</location_mentioned> as an encouragement to establish the <location_mentioned>factory </location_mentioned>he
would consider <location_mentioned>half of the land</location_mentioned> as mine for my agency in making
the arrangement or it might be estimated as so much capital on my
acct and you might particípale in the benefits or not as you might
judge proper. He also wishes to engage me in the operation, and
on my telling him I had no capital to embark in it offered to consider
my attention to the business as equivalent to Capital</p>

<p>It is very doubtful whether I can join in this operation, were
my solicitation granted, I might be induced to do so as the
most secure mode of establishing myself in the <location_mentioned>colony </location_mentioned>to secure my
<location_mentioned>lands</location_mentioned>, but altho two months and an half have elapsed since your
arrival in <location_mentioned>Saltillo</location_mentioned>, I have not recd a line from you and give up all
expectation of getting the land, I have therefore declined entering
into any arrangements on the subject until I hear from you. <person_mentioned>Mr
Ware</person_mentioned> will also wait your reply, before he moves in the matter.
Would it not be practicable to get the Govts sanction to a<location_mentioned> grant of 11
leagues </location_mentioned>for the encouragement of the establishment of the first <location_mentioned>fac-<barker_pb n="615"/>
tory</location_mentioned> of not <hi rend="italic">less than one thousand spindles</hi> With authority to
warrant that encouragement I could ensure the establishment of the
<location_mentioned>manufactory </location_mentioned>at once. I should think both the <person_mentioned>Govt </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>Genl
Teran</person_mentioned> would be favorable to this enterprise. Perhaps it would be
judicious to apply to <person_mentioned>Teran </person_mentioned>for pecuniary aid for the object as he
has funds expressly for such purposes and it might add to the
security of the property if some Govt funds were at hazard as a loan
for encouragement—yet it would not be well to be entangled with
the Govt in the matter any further than policy might require to make
him believe such establishments require encouragement.<person_mentioned> Mr Ware
</person_mentioned>wishes you to write him on the subject as we may not be here when
your reply comes I give you his address on the envelope. I shall
wait here doing nothing until I hear from you.</p>

<p>My <person_mentioned>Sister Mrs Holley</person_mentioned> now here with the family of <person_mentioned>Mr La Branch</person_mentioned>,
wrote you some time ago on the subject of getting <location_mentioned>land </location_mentioned>for herself
and son Her intention is to accompany my <person_mentioned>family </person_mentioned>in case I locate
in the <location_mentioned>colony </location_mentioned>and her object is to secure some ultimate provision for
her <person_mentioned>son</person_mentioned>. She has a few thousand dollars which would enable her
to make the needful improvements. She is full of the project of
reuniting the members of our dispersed and reduced <person_mentioned>family </person_mentioned>and
forming a society of our own, it is not probable her letter has reaehd
you. Cannot some arrangement be made to connect the<location_mentioned> U. S.</location_mentioned> with
the <location_mentioned>Mexican </location_mentioned>mail? Correspondence with the <location_mentioned>Colony </location_mentioned>is now very
uncertain.</p>

<p>The <person_mentioned>Galveston Bay land company in <location_mentioned>New York</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>  are running wild
in their operations. Selling land by hundreds of thousands of acres
a 5 cents pr acre, etc. Sending out steam machinery for <location_mentioned>mills </location_mentioned>boats
etc. I fear they will do much harm by calling the attention of Govt
too much to that <location_mentioned>quarter</location_mentioned>. I have not recd a line from the <location_mentioned>colony</location_mentioned>
since I left and know not how matters are going on. <person_mentioned>Mr Pollet of
<location_mentioned>Nacogdoches </location_mentioned></person_mentioned>told me the other day that the <person_mentioned>emigrants </person_mentioned>going in by
land had great difficulty there for want of passports. Some for 
<location_mentioned>Dewits colony </location_mentioned>had been turned back. He had passd some through 
destined to your <location_mentioned>colony </location_mentioned>by engaging to procure passports for them from
the <person_mentioned>Consul </person_mentioned>here, which the <person_mentioned>authority </person_mentioned>said was indispensable This
will cause much disappointment and injury if persisted in. The
great numbers of people going into the <location_mentioned>colony </location_mentioned>will soon fill up your
contracts I beg you will let me know when your power to grant lands
will probably cease, because if I do go in I may want to provide for
some I may take with me. I should be glad also to know, (if you can
ascertain <hi rend="italic">without calling the attention of Govt to the subject</hi>)when
the privelege of taking goods into the <location_mentioned>colony </location_mentioned>duty free will cease.
I see the law of <date_mentioned n="04-06-1830">April</date_mentioned> speaks only of provisions and lumber, and 
expect that in ease I go in I shall be caught with the whole length of<barker_pb n="616"/>
the tariff on what I take with me according to my usual luck.   I am
told they already collect the duty in<location_mentioned> Matagorda bay.</location_mentioned></p>
<p>Respectfully and cordially, your friend and Serv</p>

<p><person_mentioned>H Austin </person_mentioned>  [Rubric]</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
