
<TEI.2 id="APB1724">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>09-08-1829</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1922: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1928), 3 vols., Vol 2, pp. 220-221</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Stephen F Austin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Commodore David Porte(</document_recipient>
<document_title>Stephen F Austin to Commodore David Porter, 09-08-1829</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Unknown</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Austin to Commodore David Porter, June 8, 1829. Welcomes Porter's
application for a grant of land, which he forwards to the governor. Suggests
study of State colonization law. Texas needs admission of slavery and 
extension of tariff exemption for six years after 1830, when present exemption
expires.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes></barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 220-221</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>08-12-2010</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>


<text id="APB1724T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Austin to Commodore David Porter, June 8, 1829. Welcomes Porter's
application for a grant of land, which he forwards to the governor. Suggests
study of State colonization law. Texas needs admission of slavery and 
extension of tariff exemption for six years after 1830, when present exemption
expires.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><location_mentioned>St Felepe</location_mentioned></p>

<p>Your esteemed favr of the <date_mentioned n="04-10-1829">10 April</date_mentioned> came by the last mail and I
rece'd it <date_mentioned n="06-07-1829">yesterday </date_mentioned>at this place together with the copy of your
memorial to the <person_mentioned>President </person_mentioned>on the subject of a grant for seteling a
<location_mentioned>colony </location_mentioned>in <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, and meeting with <person_mentioned>Cap Pettet</person_mentioned> here in the <location_mentioned>Schooner
Santana</location_mentioned> I improve the oppertunity to reply.</p>

<p>I will enclose the memorial to the <person_mentioned>Govr of the <location_mentioned>State </location_mentioned></person_mentioned>by the next
mail accompanied with a letter strongly recommending your 
application, and and I think there will be no difficulty provided the 
memorial to the <person_mentioned>President </person_mentioned>is granted so far as he has the power to grant
it, I also recommend that you procure a letter from <person_mentioned>L. Z. [Lorenzo
de Zavala]</person_mentioned> to the <person_mentioned>Govr </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>Lieut Govr</person_mentioned> of this <location_mentioned>State</location_mentioned>, I have 
understood, indirectly, that <person_mentioned>Z.</person_mentioned> once had an idea of applying himself for
the same section of <location_mentioned>country</location_mentioned>, wheither the information was correct
or not I am unable to say, I believe that his standing with the
<person_mentioned>authorities </person_mentioned>of this <location_mentioned>State </location_mentioned>is very good— a private or unofficial letter
from <person_mentioned>Guerrero </person_mentioned>if such a thing could be procured would effectually
secure the matter— The <person_mentioned>Senater Agustin viesca</person_mentioned> is a <person_mentioned>brother </person_mentioned>of the
<person_mentioned>Govr </person_mentioned>Also the <person_mentioned>Deputy from this <location_mentioned>State</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> <person_mentioned>vicente Campos</person_mentioned> stands very
well with the Govr. it perhaps might be well to cultivate their
acquaintance etc.</p>

<p>It will be necessary for you to examine the colonization law of this
<location_mentioned>State </location_mentioned>passed <date_mentioned n="03-25-1825">25. March 1825</date_mentioned> in order to comprehend the nature of
the system which this <person_mentioned>Govt </person_mentioned>have adopted in regard to the 
colonization of the <location_mentioned>vacant lands in the State</location_mentioned>, and as you can easily procure
that in <location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned>by applying to <person_mentioned>Z</person_mentioned>. I do not now explain it at length—
the law was published in the <location_mentioned>?guila </location_mentioned>about two years ago 
Agreeably to the law and the system which the Govt have pursued your
memorial ought to have stated the number of <person_mentioned>families </person_mentioned>you offered
to introduce and settle within the limits applied for the law allows
to the <person_mentioned>Empresario </person_mentioned><location_mentioned>five Leagues and three labors</location_mentioned> for each 100 <person_mentioned>families</person_mentioned>
not exceeding 800.</p>

<p>Should it be practicable for you [to] visit this <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>and 
examine it particularly yourself before commencing the settlement of the
<location_mentioned>colony </location_mentioned>I think it would be advantageous Capital can be profitably
employed here, and perhaps a company might be formed which
could command capital, and tend greatly to the advancemt of the
<location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>as well as being profitable to those concerned—</p><barker_pb n="221"/>

<p>The colonizing business has been in the highest degree laborious
perplexing and harrassing to me and not profitable but I commenced
in an entire <location_mentioned>wilderness </location_mentioned>and have had difficulties to work through
which do not now exist— My object was to settle the <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>and I
have kept that object in view much more steadily than the 
advancement of my own fortune, I think that a sufficient foundation is now
laid for the profitable investment of capital in various ways</p>

<p>The <person_mentioned>Govt </person_mentioned>may easily make <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>a very flourishing and 
advantageous <location_mentioned>member of the confederation</location_mentioned> it is now a dead weight— <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>
once settled and the <location_mentioned>whole of the frontier of the Rio Grande from
New Mexico to Matamoros</location_mentioned> would be effectually protected from the
<person_mentioned>indians </person_mentioned>which would be an incalcutable advantage, The revenue
which the commerce of this <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>could yield in ten years would
be a very great object to the <location_mentioned>nation</location_mentioned>—</p>

<p>There are some leading points of policy necessary for <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>.— Such
as the admission of slavery and such a system of revenue and
commercial regulations as will leave our trade free of duty for <date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1835">five
years after </date_mentioned><date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1830">1830 </date_mentioned>when the present law of exemption expires. Should
the restrictive system be continued in the<location_mentioned> U. S.</location_mentioned> <location_mentioned>England </location_mentioned>will no doubt
receive <person_mentioned>Mexican </person_mentioned>cotton on advantagious terms</p>

<p>Much might be said on this subject-— I think it is the true policy
of this <location_mentioned>nation </location_mentioned>to have the most of their <location_mentioned>work shops</location_mentioned> in <location_mentioned>Europe </location_mentioned>for
some years to come, and in the mean time give existence to the
agricultural and planting interest for as yet it can scarely be said
to exist except so far as is necessary for domestic use—</p>

<p>[Stephen F. Austin.]</p>

<p><date_mentioned n="06-08-1829">8 june 1829</date_mentioned></p>

<p>[Austin to Governor Viesca:] Tengo el honor de elevar a V. E.
la solicitud del <person_mentioned>comodoro Daniel [David] Porter</person_mentioned> en qe solicita se
le concede una <location_mentioned>colonia en Texas</location_mentioned>, El <person_mentioned>Sor Porter</person_mentioned> es bien conocido y no
cabe duda que adquirirle por <person_mentioned>ciudadano Cuahuiltejano</person_mentioned> sera de mucha
ventaja al <location_mentioned>Estado </location_mentioned>y contribuirá touchissimo al fomento de la 
población de los <location_mentioned>desiertos de Texas</location_mentioned>, en este concepto tomo la libertad de
recomendar su solicitud con mucho interés y empeño—</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
