
<TEI.2 id="APB1332">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>02-17-1827</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1602-1604</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Burril J. Thompson</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Stephen F. Austin</document_recipient>
<document_title>Burril J. Thompson to Stephen F. Austin, 02-17-1827</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Natchitoches, Louisiana</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Nacogdoches, Texas</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Burril J. Thompson to Austin, February 17, 1827. Conditions at Nacogdoches which caused the uprising there.   Desires to make his peace and return.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes></barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1602-1604</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>07-17-2010</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>


<text id="APB1332T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Burril J. Thompson to Austin, February 17, 1827. Conditions at Nacogdoches which caused the uprising there.   Desires to make his peace and return.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><location_mentioned>Parrish of Natchitoches</location_mentioned> <date_mentioned n="02-17-1827">17 Feby 1827</date_mentioned></p>
<p>Dr. Sir</p>

<p>It is with Regret I see so much confushion and Trouble in the
<location_mentioned>Spanish Provences</location_mentioned> But It can only a lone be attributed to The
Imperfect manner of the organization of the <person_mentioned>government</person_mentioned>—The 
<location_mentioned>Districk of Nacogdoches</location_mentioned> had Been Left Intirely to the management of
a few Ignorant Designing <person_mentioned>men </person_mentioned>without Principle and with out laws,
men who wished to show their Power and acted with more Tyranny
Then Ever was, Excersised under the <person_mentioned>king of spain</person_mentioned>. Love of change
and an Idia that Land could be obtained for a mear Trifle, and
others for crimes Done Caused a considerable Imigration To that
<location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>Expecting or thinking It a <location_mentioned>Republick </location_mentioned>similar to the one they
had left and finding no Laws nor Regulation orthised by the 
<person_mentioned>government</person_mentioned>, and all Those that Pretended to act from orthority, without
Principle or Justice no wonder, that <person_mentioned>americans </person_mentioned>Eight from the<location_mentioned> Land
of Liberty</location_mentioned>, should wish a change Letters and addresses to the
<person_mentioned>government </person_mentioned>was never attended to, the mail Robed and no 
communication through that Depart could be Depended on, with a<barker_pb n="1603"/>
thousand other causes, has led the Independent <person_mentioned>americans </person_mentioned>to Deeds
of violence That they would heave abhord, Provided the 
<person_mentioned>government </person_mentioned>could heave been properly organised so that they could heave
In joyed Peace and asshir anees for their Property—I Sir Removed
to that <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>from choice, and heave as much wright to complaine
as almost any other Person—I sir fell under the Displeasure of the
<person_mentioned>Petty Tayrant</person_mentioned> for Raising a <person_mentioned>company of volunteers</person_mentioned> by his own
Request to go to the assistance of your <location_mentioned>Colony</location_mentioned>, I was Denyed the
Priviledge of Taking oath of Eligence to the <person_mentioned>government</person_mentioned>, and when
I Purchesed <location_mentioned>land </location_mentioned>denyed the Right to hold land and could not heave
a Deed acnoledged, without any cause shewn I considered Those
Ingerys unorthised by the <person_mentioned>government </person_mentioned>and, was one of the Leading
causes of Puting the <person_mentioned>Rascal </person_mentioned>Down and appointing an other in his
Place that I thought would Do Justice—But as to Raising the Flag
I was opposed to It, and Done Every thing I could to git It Down—
I Refare you to my friend <person_mentioned>Capn Joseph Dust</person_mentioned> for Infermation as
he alone in that <location_mentioned>Town </location_mentioned>knew my Polocy and we acted togather—</p>

<p>as Respects the <person_mentioned>Prisnors </person_mentioned>they never Took an active Part against
The government they were in opposition to <person_mentioned>Norris & Co—</person_mentioned> <person_mentioned>W.
Wilson</person_mentioned> in Particular is my friend (and a more manly Independant
man is not in that <location_mentioned>Provence</location_mentioned>) and he I assure you never approbated
the Raising the Flag nor would Ever Serve under It, and I hope
my <person_mentioned>friend </person_mentioned>you will Do Every thing you can for him as well as all
the Rest for should the <person_mentioned>Prisners </person_mentioned>be Put To Death there will be
Troubles In the <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>that you can heave but little Idea off</p>

<p>when the <person_mentioned>coms </person_mentioned>ware sent to make Peace The <person_mentioned>People </person_mentioned>on the <location_mentioned>Aish
Bayou,</location_mentioned> would gladly heave Imbraced the oppertunity with out, the
Trouble and Dappredations that has Been committed there by men
I fear without Principles or Honesty and whose Friendship or honor
can not be Relyed on I Proposed sending on a <person_mentioned>man </person_mentioned>to the 
government to Represent our situation, which would heave Ben done, If
the times had not heave changed as soon as they Did.</p>

<p>I left the <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>because I say that Peace could not be 
Established, untill the <person_mentioned>Troops </person_mentioned>would arrive and heave Rented Land for
this crop, with the Intention of Returning to the <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>as soon
as Times would Become Better—But hearing I am threatened as
one of the <person_mentioned>Promoters of the Rebellion</person_mentioned>, I shall not Return, untill
times can be Better Regulated,</p>

<p>I should be glad to see you and Think if I could or was orthised
That I could Bring the <person_mentioned>Party </person_mentioned>That is on this side to a compromise,
Provided They could be Pardoned for their offence, and I think all
But the <person_mentioned>Edwards </person_mentioned>would be glad to Return to that <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>Provided
they could Do It in Peace—I am settled  <location_mentioned>20 miles from thesabine</location_mentioned>
But would meet you There at any Time [desired] and I Do not Hesi-<barker_pb n="1604"/>
tate in saying that [I can] Bring all the <person_mentioned>Party</person_mentioned>, (and There is near
30 men) to Terms of Peace Provided It is by your Request and
that of the <person_mentioned>officers of the army</person_mentioned> I should be glad you and your <person_mentioned>Brother</person_mentioned>
could come and spend a few Days with us. I could give you Every
Information on the subject and I Do assure will Do Every thing in
my Power to Establish Peace</p>

<p>Be assured I new you ay an old and particuler friend I wish you
helth and Hapiness</p>

<p><person_mentioned>B. J. Thompson</person_mentioned></p>

<p><person_mentioned>Col S F Austin</person_mentioned></p>

<p>[Addressed:] <person_mentioned>Col Stephen F. Austin</person_mentioned> <location_mentioned>Nacogdoches Texes</location_mentioned></p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
