
<TEI.2 id="APB4393">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>07-28-1832</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 825-828</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Stephen F Austin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Ramon Musquiz</document_recipient>
<document_title>Stephen F Austin to Ramon Musquiz, 07-28-1832</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>San Felipe de Austin, Texas</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Austin to Ramon Musquiz, July 28, 1832. Explaining why his colonists declared for Santa Anna—primarily because he represents the liberal, republican, and constitutional party. Previous troubles due to Bradburn and Fisher. No
one desires separation from Mexico; convinced, on the other hand, that that would ruin Texas, All wish to form a separate state of the Mexican federation. For this population is needed, and therefore the eleventh article of the law of April 6, 1830, must be repealed, Hopes that Bexar will declare for Santa Anna and petition for reforms.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes>A translation from the Nacogdoches Archives, Texas State Library.
</barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 825-828</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>09-29-2010</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>


<text id="APB4393T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Austin to Ramon Musquiz, July 28, 1832. Explaining why his colonists declared for Santa Anna—primarily because he represents the liberal, republican, and constitutional party. Previous troubles due to Bradburn and Fisher. No
one desires separation from Mexico; convinced, on the other hand, that that would ruin Texas, All wish to form a separate state of the Mexican federation. For this population is needed, and therefore the eleventh article of the law of April 6, 1830, must be repealed, Hopes that Bexar will declare for Santa Anna and petition for reforms.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">
<p><location_mentioned>San Felipe de Austin</location_mentioned> <date_mentioned n="07-28-1832">July 28th 1832</date_mentioned></p>
<p>Most esteemed chief and friend</p>

<p>I suppose that you have received the few lines that I wrote to you
hurriedly from <location_mentioned>Brazoria</location_mentioned>. In that letter I manifested the opinion
that under the actual circumstances it was very important for us
all to join the plan of <person_mentioned>Santa Anna</person_mentioned>: I will in this letter explain that
idea, and expose the reasons on which I ground it. In the first
place, in regard to this <location_mentioned>Colony</location_mentioned>. On my arrival at <location_mentioned>Brazoria</location_mentioned>, I met
the whole <person_mentioned>people </person_mentioned>unanimous and enthusiastic in favor of the plan
of <person_mentioned>Santa Anna</person_mentioned>. They welcomed <person_mentioned>General Mejia</person_mentioned> with such rejoicing
and enthusiasm as I had never witnessed in this <location_mentioned>country</location_mentioned>. On the
day before in a large meeting they had resolved to persevere in their
adhesion to the plan of <location_mentioned>Veracruz</location_mentioned>, and that previous to having heard
of the arrival of <person_mentioned>Mejia</person_mentioned>. Under such circumstances, and observing
that the personal feelings against the <person_mentioned>inhabitants </person_mentioned>who had not given
their adhesion, and more particularly against the <person_mentioned>Ayuntamiento</person_mentioned>
were rather violent, and even gave rise to strong excitement against
some <person_mentioned>individuals</person_mentioned>; considering also the situation in which the <location_mentioned>colony</location_mentioned>
would be in regard to the division command by Col. Mejia if they
did not pronounce themselves; and finally taking into consideration
that the <person_mentioned>party of Santa Anna</person_mentioned> is truly the <person_mentioned>liberal republican</person_mentioned>, and
<person_mentioned>constitutional party</person_mentioned>, and that it is proper that a strong manifesta-<barker_pb n="826"/>
tion of opinion should be made throughout the <location_mentioned>Republic </location_mentioned>in favor
of the plan of <location_mentioned>Veracruz</location_mentioned>, as the only means to bring civil war to an
end, and to secure peace and the constitutional liberty of the 
<location_mentioned>Nation</location_mentioned>. I expressed my opinion to the <person_mentioned>Ayuntamiento</person_mentioned>, advising them
to pronounce themselves in order to avoid evils and local 
misunderstandings which prove always fatal. A meeting of the 
<person_mentioned>Ayuntamiento </person_mentioned>took place the <date_mentioned n="7-26-1832">day before yesterday</date_mentioned>, and another <date_mentioned n="7-27-1832">yesterday</date_mentioned>,
of the <person_mentioned>people</person_mentioned>, which was well attended, and in which the plan of
<location_mentioned>Veracruz </location_mentioned>was unanimously adhered to, the most perfect unison and
harmony prevailing in that expression of the public will. The 
resolutions and their preamble contain a true manifestation of the
causes and origin of the difficulties at <location_mentioned>Anahuac</location_mentioned>, and of the objects
of those who went to attack <person_mentioned>Bradburn</person_mentioned>, in short they offer a 
concise history of the whole transaction. It was said by the <person_mentioned>partizans</person_mentioned>
of the <person_mentioned>Cabinet at <location_mentioned>Matamoras</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>, that the <person_mentioned>colonists </person_mentioned>had risen against
the integrity of the <location_mentioned>territory</location_mentioned>, and a thousand other false and
imaginary versions.</p>

<p>You may in your visit here have formed a correct idea of the
whole affair, and I am convinced that there was no other object
in view, but to show to the despot<person_mentioned> John Davis Bradburn</person_mentioned>, that
there is such a thing as the constitution and <location_mentioned>State of Coahuila and
Texas</location_mentioned>. That man was the cause of the whole evil, loss of life, and
misfortune. I assure you most solemnly, that I have not heard,
even from the mouth of the most exasperated, one word against
any <person_mentioned>Mexican </person_mentioned>holding an important command, or in office in these
<location_mentioned>colonies</location_mentioned>: The complaints are against <person_mentioned>Davis </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>Fisher</person_mentioned>, and most
particularly against the despotic procedings of the first, always
supported by <person_mentioned>General Teran</person_mentioned>. <person_mentioned>Fisher </person_mentioned>told me at <location_mentioned>Matamoras</location_mentioned>, that
the untimely, impolitic, and impracticable order issued by him on
the <date_mentioned n="11-24-1831">24th of November last</date_mentioned>, in relation to the Navigation of the
<location_mentioned>Brazos River</location_mentioned> was dictated by <person_mentioned>General Teran</person_mentioned> himself, and cannot
be charged to him, as he did but obey: In such case he has been
very unfortunate, because the whole odium fell on his head. I
assure you also, with the same solemnity, that I have not heard
one single word, that might countenance insinuations, often made
by <person_mentioned>friends </person_mentioned>of the <person_mentioned>Cabinet </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>enemies </person_mentioned>of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, that the <person_mentioned>colonists</person_mentioned>
wished to secede and to declare their independence from the 
<location_mentioned>Mexican Federation</location_mentioned>. On the contrary, the most intelligent among them,
told me that the late difficulties have convinced them more than
ever, that to think of such a thing would be the ruin of all. My
own and the general wish is, to see <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>forming by itself a <location_mentioned>State
of the Federation</location_mentioned>, and as long as it is not so, we can expect no
peace, progress nor government, and in fact nothing</p>.<barker_pb n="827"/>

<p>In answer to the question, what are the causes of the 
convulsions in <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, and why did they declare themselves in favor of
the plan of <location_mentioned>Veracruz</location_mentioned>, You may say; that in <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, there is a 
<person_mentioned>military government</person_mentioned>, more or less despotic according to the character
and disposition of the<person_mentioned> commanding officers</person_mentioned>: that there is a <person_mentioned>civil
government</person_mentioned> more or less strong, according to the disposition and
intelligence of the <person_mentioned>Alcaldes</person_mentioned>, and <person_mentioned>Ayuntamientos</person_mentioned>, and their distance
from a <location_mentioned>military post</location_mentioned>, and thus there is no government at all in
several points, excepting that which originates in a mutual 
agreement on the part of the people to submit to the decisions of some
persons elected by them: But at the same time, all acknowledge
the authority and laws of the <location_mentioned>Nation </location_mentioned>and <location_mentioned>State</location_mentioned>: There is not
throughout <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, one single "<person_mentioned>Juez de Letras,</person_mentioned>" nor one 
"<person_mentioned>Licenciado</person_mentioned>." The <person_mentioned>supreme tribunal of Justice</person_mentioned> is at <location_mentioned>Saltillo</location_mentioned>, a distance
of 300 leagues. The <person_mentioned>legislature </person_mentioned>understands neither the situation
nor the wants of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, nor can it understand them. The <person_mentioned>military
powers</person_mentioned> under the anti-republican anti-liberal administration of
<person_mentioned>Guerrero's assassins</person_mentioned> who have extended their iron sceptre over the
<location_mentioned>nation</location_mentioned>, since the <person_mentioned><hi rend="italic">black cloud of </hi>Jalapa</person_mentioned> appeared, have treated the
government and constitution of the <location_mentioned>State of Coahuila and Texas
</location_mentioned>with a complete contempt. If the <person_mentioned>authorities </person_mentioned>of the <location_mentioned>State </location_mentioned>have
borne such insults, there is no reason why the people should do so.
In short, you may say that <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>needs a <hi rend="italic">government</hi>, and that
the best she can have, is to be created a <location_mentioned>State </location_mentioned>in the <location_mentioned>Mexican 
Federation</location_mentioned>. For which we want more population, and to obtain it,
the Article 11th of the law of <date_mentioned n="04-06-1830">April 6th 1830</date_mentioned> must be abrogated.</p>

<p>The <person_mentioned>inhabitants </person_mentioned>of <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>have always had their eyes and hopes
fixed on the <person_mentioned>authority </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>Ayuntamiento of the Capital of <location_mentioned>Bexar</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>,
they with that City, would take the lead in advocating and defending
the interests and rights of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>. It is the <location_mentioned>oldest settlement</location_mentioned>: the
<person_mentioned>fathers </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>forefathers </person_mentioned>of its <person_mentioned>inhabitants</person_mentioned>, have conquered the 
<location_mentioned>wilderness </location_mentioned>and struggled against the <person_mentioned>Indians</person_mentioned>. In the years <date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1820">1820</date_mentioned>-<date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1821">1821</date_mentioned>-<date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1822">1822</date_mentioned>
and <date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1823">1823</date_mentioned>, they were reduced to almost the last stage of decline and
suffering, and the whole of <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>was in danger of returning to its
primitive state, to be untrodden by <person_mentioned>civilized people</person_mentioned>. The 
<person_mentioned>immigrants </person_mentioned>did not, and do not believe that <location_mentioned>Bexar </location_mentioned>would shut its eyes
to the evils that affect the <location_mentioned>Country</location_mentioned>, or would remain contented and
silent, without even representing against the measures that prevent
emigration, and paralyze the progress of the <location_mentioned>land of their <person_mentioned>ancestors</person_mentioned>.</location_mentioned>
It is now time for it to meet the expectation of the people. <location_mentioned>Bexar</location_mentioned>
must speak in a respectful, but firm and decided tone and voice,
fearless of commanding <person_mentioned>generals</person_mentioned>, bayonets, <person_mentioned>ministers</person_mentioned>, or any body.
Let it adhere to the pronounciamento of <location_mentioned>Veracruz</location_mentioned>, urge the whole
of <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>to do the same, and thus unite us under the flag of the<barker_pb n="828"/>
Constitution. Let it represent against the laws preventing 
imigration from other <location_mentioned>countries</location_mentioned>, request that the above be flung open to
all <location_mentioned>nations </location_mentioned>at peace with the <location_mentioned>Republic</location_mentioned>. Let it complain of the
maratime tariff, a barbarous contrivance ruinous to agriculture; let
it expose clearly the abuses of the <person_mentioned>military power</person_mentioned>, and above all, let
it be the first to urge a separation from <location_mentioned>Coahuila </location_mentioned>and the formation
of a <location_mentioned>seperate State</location_mentioned>. The character of the <person_mentioned>people of <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned></person_mentioned>is 
interprizing and decided, they scorn dangers and laugh at obstacles;
therefore if <location_mentioned>Bexar </location_mentioned>wishes to be at the head of these people, it must
be decided in its course, it must be <location_mentioned><hi rend="italic">Mexico-Texan</hi></location_mentioned>.</p>

<p>If <location_mentioned>Bexar </location_mentioned>will pronounce itself, <location_mentioned>Nacogdoches </location_mentioned>will follow, but 
otherwise the people of that district will do what they have done here;
they will attack <person_mentioned>Colonel Piedras</person_mentioned>, and the whole population will be
up again, and <location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned>overflowed with rumors and lies about the
<hi rend="italic">rebellion of the <person_mentioned>colonists</person_mentioned></hi> of Texas: All this may be avoided if <location_mentioned>Bexar</location_mentioned>
follows the example given by this town and <location_mentioned>LaBahia</location_mentioned> Things have
now come to such a pass, that lukewarm measures are ruinous, it
is necessary to adopt a <person_mentioned>party</person_mentioned>, and to declare it publicly, otherwise I
apprehend that it would be difficult to avoid difficulties, divisions,
and local ill feeling throughout <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>.</p>

<p><person_mentioned>Señor Mejia</person_mentioned> left the<location_mentioned> mouth of the Brazos </location_mentioned>for <location_mentioned>Anahuac</location_mentioned>, and may
thence proceed to <location_mentioned>Nacogdoches</location_mentioned>, in which case, the people will join
him in mass. All this may be avoided if <location_mentioned>Bexar </location_mentioned>and <location_mentioned>Nacogdoches</location_mentioned>
pronounce themselves, and the whole of <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>unites in mass under
the same banner—that of <person_mentioned>Santa Anna</person_mentioned>. I have expressed my opinion
to the<person_mentioned> government of the Nation</person_mentioned> and that of the <location_mentioned>State</location_mentioned>, as well as
to <person_mentioned>General Santa Anna </person_mentioned>from <location_mentioned>Matamoras</location_mentioned>, with a particular notice
of the slanderous, unjust and Machiavellian lie, of that imaginary
ghost raised by the <person_mentioned>aristocratic and designing enemies</person_mentioned> of the 
immigration of <person_mentioned>republican settlers</person_mentioned>—that the <person_mentioned>inhabitants </person_mentioned>of <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>wish
to secede from <location_mentioned>Mexico</location_mentioned>. I have also declared that it is impossible
to rule <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, militarily, and that its peace would be endangered
in proportion to the increase of regular <person_mentioned>troops</person_mentioned>, above the sufficient
number for the protection of the <person_mentioned>frontier </person_mentioned>from the <person_mentioned>Indians</person_mentioned>. Some
<person_mentioned>friends of the liberal party</person_mentioned>, asked me at <location_mentioned>Monterey</location_mentioned>: What are the
<person_mentioned>Ayuntamiento </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>People of <location_mentioned>Bexar</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> about that they do not manifest
to the <location_mentioned>nation</location_mentioned>, the true state of affairs in <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>? Why do they not
represent against article 11th of the law of <date_mentioned n="04-06-1830">April 6, 1830</date_mentioned>, which
opposes so many obstacles to emigration? I write to you with my
accustomed candor, and with the most sincere wishes for the 
prosperity and peace of my <location_mentioned>country</location_mentioned>, and in these terms I avail myself
of this occasion to give you the assurance of the respect and cordial
friendship of your fellow citizen and friend &c.</p>

<p><person_mentioned>Stephen F. Austin</person_mentioned></p>


</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
