
<TEI.2 id="APB4343">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>04-28-1832</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 766-769</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>letter</document_type>
<document_author>Stephen F Austin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Samuel M Williams</document_recipient>
<document_title>Stephen F Austin to Samuel M Williams, 04-28-1832</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Saltillo, Coahuila</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Austin, Texas</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Austin to Samuel M. Williams, Saltillo, April 28, 1832. New colonization law passed. Texans must be mere spectators in national politics. Nothing io fear If all are patient and quiet.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes>Decree No. 190, Gáname!, Laws of Texas, I   193</barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 766-769</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>09-22-2010</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>


<text id="APB4343T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Austin to Samuel M. Williams, Saltillo, April 28, 1832. New colonization law passed. Texans must be mere spectators in national politics. Nothing io fear If all are patient and quiet.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p>[From Williams Papers, Rosenberg Library, Galveston, Tex.]</p>

<p><location_mentioned>Saltillo </location_mentioned><date_mentioned n="04-28-1832">April 28 1832</date_mentioned></p>
<p>Dr Sir,</p>

<p>The <person_mentioned>legislature</person_mentioned>'s labors closed <date_mentioned n="04-28-1832">today</date_mentioned> (Saturday) for altho there
will be one more sitting, on <date_mentioned n="04-30-1832">Monday</date_mentioned>, nothing more will be done on
that day than to go through the formalities of closing the session etc.</p><barker_pb n="767"/>

<p>The new colonization law has passed—it had progressed 
considerably before my arrival and is as favorable as could be obtained
or expected at present. A law has passed reducing the Alcabala one
half in the <location_mentioned>departments of Bejar and Monclova</location_mentioned>—another stating that
the <person_mentioned>military </person_mentioned>in service have not, and never have had, any right to
vote at elections, except the p<person_mentioned>residial companies</person_mentioned> in the <location_mentioned>towns </location_mentioned>where
they belong—another establishing the <location_mentioned>municipality of Brazoria</location_mentioned>.
Three years more have been granted to <person_mentioned>Powers</person_mentioned>, <person_mentioned>Cameron</person_mentioned>, <person_mentioned>Beales</person_mentioned>,
<person_mentioned>Viehlien </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>Burnet </person_mentioned>to settle their <location_mentioned>colonies</location_mentioned>.</p>

<p>Upon the whole this legislature have done no harm except the
retail law, and some good.</p>

<p>The States of <location_mentioned>Jalisco </location_mentioned>and <location_mentioned>Zacatecas </location_mentioned>have formally <hi rend="italic">demanded </hi>the
dismissal of the <person_mentioned>ministers</person_mentioned>. <location_mentioned>Tamaulipas </location_mentioned>is all at sixes and sevens—
the <person_mentioned>Legislature </person_mentioned>have annulled the decree of the junta Legislativa
of <date_mentioned n="03-19-1832">19 March last</date_mentioned>, and asked pardon of the general Government, etc.
The <person_mentioned>Governor of that State, Vital Fernandez,</person_mentioned> refused to sanction
this last act of the legislature and mustering all the <person_mentioned>troops </person_mentioned>and
<person_mentioned>militia </person_mentioned>he could marched towards <location_mentioned>Tampico </location_mentioned>in the <date_mentioned n="04-20-1832">night of the 20
April</date_mentioned>. <person_mentioned>General Teran</person_mentioned> it is said was <location_mentioned>within six leagues of him on
the pursuit,</location_mentioned> but I doubt this, for I have a letter from <person_mentioned>Teran </person_mentioned><date_mentioned n="04-14-1832">14 April
</date_mentioned>from <location_mentioned>Matamoros</location_mentioned>, he was then starting for <location_mentioned>Victoria</location_mentioned>. <person_mentioned>Santana </person_mentioned>is
already besieged in <location_mentioned>Vera Cruz.</location_mentioned></p>

<p>It is impossible to form any definite opinion as to how this matter
will end, but I think the most probable conjecture is that the <person_mentioned>ministers</person_mentioned>
will retire soon, and that a general amisty will follow and a total
cessacion of all hostility. I must confess that I doubt very much
whether the <location_mentioned>nation </location_mentioned>will gain anything by a change of <person_mentioned>ministers</person_mentioned>—our
<hi rend="italic">Congresito</hi>, very wisely I think, have adopted the turtle sistem,
<hi rend="italic">callado</hi>.</p>

<p>So much for general matters—now for <hi rend="italic"><location_mentioned>home </location_mentioned></hi>affairs. The removal
of <person_mentioned>Fisher</person_mentioned>, and the establishment of a <location_mentioned>custom house office at Brazoria
</location_mentioned>I presume has satisfied everybody, and of course you have peace and
harmony in the <location_mentioned>colony</location_mentioned>. The prospect of getting the law of <date_mentioned n="04-06-1830">6 April
</date_mentioned>modified is much better than I expected. If the whole of <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>and
that <location_mentioned>colony </location_mentioned>in particular are quiet, prudent and obedient, and can
keep all the <person_mentioned>local officers</person_mentioned> and especially the <person_mentioned>Military </person_mentioned>in a good
humor, and well satisfied, I will almost insure a repeal of the 11
article of the law of <date_mentioned n="04-06-1830">6 April,</date_mentioned> but there must be no more such
violent excitements as that at <location_mentioned>Brazoria </location_mentioned>in <date_mentioned n="12-xx-1831">December</date_mentioned>—no more such
illegal and even <hi rend="italic">piratical </hi>conduct as the <person_mentioned>Boston Packet</person_mentioned>,—No more
speeches. How silly and imprudent the best of us will talk and act
sometimes when under excitement. Those who were abusing me at
<location_mentioned>Brazoria </location_mentioned>and in <location_mentioned>San Felipe</location_mentioned> because I insisted that <person_mentioned>Teran </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>Brad-<barker_pb n="768"/>
burn</person_mentioned> were not the <person_mentioned>enemies </person_mentioned>of the <location_mentioned>colony </location_mentioned>[as] some charged them to be,
and who even ridiculed me for believing that <person_mentioned>Fisher </person_mentioned>would be 
removed and an <person_mentioned>officer of the <location_mentioned>custom house</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> sent to <location_mentioned>Brazoria</location_mentioned>, ought now
to be convinced that I knew more of the subject than they did. I can
assure the whole <location_mentioned>colony </location_mentioned>and all <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>that nothing but the outragious
imprudence of the people themselves will bring trouble on that 
<location_mentioned>country</location_mentioned>. If the whole of the <person_mentioned>Settlers </person_mentioned>will adopt my motto <hi rend="italic">Fidelity to
<location_mentioned>Mexico</location_mentioned></hi>—and act and talk in conformity they will flourish beyond
their own expectations, and every favor will be granted to them, they
could expect in reason. The <person_mentioned>legislature </person_mentioned>of the <location_mentioned>State </location_mentioned>are favorably
disposed towards colonization, as the new law will shew. The 
<person_mentioned>Governor </person_mentioned>is also friendly, and if a <hi rend="italic">dead calm</hi> has been, and can be 
preserved, all will end well—very well. I rely on the old standards, the
<person_mentioned>first settlers</person_mentioned>. They have known me for years. They now know that
their destiny was almost entirely in my hands—nay I might say 
completely in my hands for several years, for my legal authority over
them was very nearly absolute. They can now look back and see
that I have taken them safely through all difficulties, and that so
long as their affairs were exclusively under my own control, they
progressed in peace and harmony with the <person_mentioned>Govt</person_mentioned>. These things ought
to give them full confidence in me, and I say to them, as I have often
said, that they have more to fear from the imprudence of <person_mentioned>drunkards</person_mentioned>
and talking <person_mentioned>demagogues </person_mentioned>amongst themselves, than from the <person_mentioned>Govt</person_mentioned>.
I recommend my motto to them, and those who have any influence
ought to exert it to have that motto used as a popular toast in the
place of some others that I have been told were drank.</p>

<p>It would be a good thing for the <person_mentioned>people of <location_mentioned>Brazoria</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> to make a
present to the <location_mentioned>new custom house office</location_mentioned> of the<hi rend="italic"> two guns.</hi> If they will
do so and the expense is any obstacle, I will pay for them myself.
Shew this to <person_mentioned>Cap. John Austin</person_mentioned> and any others you please and tell
<person_mentioned>John </person_mentioned>that the <person_mentioned>assesor </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>judges </person_mentioned>say that if he has had a <location_mentioned>court at
Brazoria </location_mentioned>it is <hi rend="italic">illegal </hi>and his acts void and himself liable to 
punishment. Many <location_mentioned>papers </location_mentioned>have been, or will be sent into <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>from
<location_mentioned>Tampico </location_mentioned>and <location_mentioned>Vera Cruz</location_mentioned> and <hi rend="italic">perhaps </hi>some <person_mentioned>agents of that party</person_mentioned>,
if so, treat them all <hi rend="italic">politely</hi>. That is read the <location_mentioned>papers</location_mentioned>—and feed
and lodge the <person_mentioned>agents </person_mentioned>while they stay—but nothing more. No matter
which party gains, it would ruin the </person_mentioned>people of the <location_mentioned>colony </location_mentioned>to take
any part in any way. They must be mere spectators, and silent
ones, hear and see everything they can, but without taking any part
or expressing any opinion. Try and get them to adopt this idea all
over the <location_mentioned>colony </location_mentioned>and especially at <location_mentioned>Brazoria</location_mentioned>.</p>

<p>I think I shall go to <location_mentioned>Monterry</location_mentioned>, and perhaps to <location_mentioned>Victoria</location_mentioned>. <person_mentioned>Genl
Mason</person_mentioned> wishes to see <person_mentioned>Genl Teran</person_mentioned>, and so do I. I do not see any
necessity for my immediate return to the <location_mentioned>colony</location_mentioned>, and am as yet<barker_pb n="769"/>
undetermined whether I shall return untill after the <date_mentioned n="09-xx-1832">September</date_mentioned>
session—tho I do not know how you are getting on for I have not
heard a word from <location_mentioned>San Felipe</location_mentioned> since the <date_mentioned n="03-08-1832">8th day of March</date_mentioned>, which
was the day I left there, the last mail brought nothing.</p>

<p>Tell <person_mentioned>Sister Emily</person_mentioned> that <person_mentioned>Austin </person_mentioned>is well—has a <person_mentioned>Mexicanita 
Sweetheart</person_mentioned> and begins to hablar.</p>

<p>The session of <date_mentioned n="04-28-1832">today </date_mentioned>continued untill 4 P. M. so I have not time
to write to the <person_mentioned>Ayuntamto</person_mentioned>, and therefor request you to read this
letter to the <person_mentioned>members</person_mentioned>—and to present my respects to each of them
individually—also to <person_mentioned>Sarah </person_mentioned>and all <person_mentioned>friends</person_mentioned>—y al <person_mentioned>Padre</person_mentioned>.</p>

<p><person_mentioned>S. F. Austin</person_mentioned></p>

<p>Reservado: Tell <person_mentioned>John Austin</person_mentioned> not to dispose of any <location_mentioned>lots in the new
part of Brazoria</location_mentioned> untill my return, not one to any person nor on any
account. I particularly request and charge you to attend to this—I
mean the lots that were bid in by him for me, which includes the
most that were sold. If he is not in<location_mentioned> San Felipe</location_mentioned> write to him 
immediately.</p>

<p>You need not send any letters to me untill farther orders, for I do
not know where I shall be during the summer.</p>

<p><person_mentioned>Genl Mason</person_mentioned> wishes you to keep his letters and papers, if any should
come for him untill he arrives en esa</p>

<p><person_mentioned>S. F. Austin</person_mentioned></p>

<p>I wrote you from <location_mentioned>Goliad</location_mentioned>—<location_mentioned>Bexar</location_mentioned>—and twice from here by <person_mentioned>Don
Luis del Valle,</person_mentioned> and <person_mentioned>Butler</person_mentioned>.</p>

<p>[Addressed:] <person_mentioned>Don Samuel M. Williams </person_mentioned>  <location_mentioned>Austin</location_mentioned></p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
