
<TEI.2 id="APB4292">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>11-30-1831</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 11-30-1831</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>House plans</document_type>
<document_author>Stephen F Austin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Emily Perry?</document_recipient>
<document_title>Stephen F Austin to Emily Perry?, 11-30-1831</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Unknown</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Austin's house plans for his sister, November 30, 1831.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes></barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 11-30-1831</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>09-16-2010</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>


<text id="APB4292T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Austin's house plans for his sister, November 30, 1831.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><location_mentioned>NORTH</location_mentioned></p>

<p>Back here the <location_mentioned>kitchen </location_mentioned>and other <location_mentioned>out buildings</location_mentioned> will be placed 
<location_mentioned>between the house and Pleasant Bayou</location_mentioned>, so as to be convenient to wood
and water—the <location_mentioned>back yard</location_mentioned> must extend down to the <location_mentioned>bayou </location_mentioned>and all
the large trees ought to be carefully preserved so as to have a cool
<location_mentioned>shady grove</location_mentioned> <location_mentioned>back of the house on the bank of the bayou</location_mentioned>, also this
grove will break off the north winds in winter</p>

<p>The <location_mentioned>garden </location_mentioned>and <location_mentioned>orchard </location_mentioned>can be <location_mentioned>east, or west of the house along the
edge of the timber</location_mentioned>, and the <location_mentioned>cow pens stables &c</location_mentioned> ought to be on the
<location_mentioned>opposite end of the house from the Garden,</location_mentioned> that is, if the <location_mentioned>garden </location_mentioned>is
<location_mentioned>west or below the house</location_mentioned>, the <location_mentioned>cow pens</location_mentioned>, <location_mentioned>stables and calf lot </location_mentioned>barn ought
to be to the <location_mentioned>east of the house up the bayou</location_mentioned> which I think will be the
best place— The <location_mentioned>farm </location_mentioned>ought to be on the<location_mentioned> north side of Pleasant
bayou</location_mentioned></p>

<p>Explanation of the Plan       D Means door—W means windows</p>

G D. means glass door<barker_pb n="716"/>

[Image did not transfer - DML]<barker_pb n="717"/>

<p>Nos 1 and 3   <location_mentioned>bed room</location_mentioned> <location_mentioned>on each end of the front gallery</location_mentioned> 10 by 12ft</p>
<p>N. °2  <location_mentioned> Front gallery</location_mentioned> 34 feet long 10 feet wide—   The whole of the
sills, posts and floors of this and all the other galleries
ought to be of cedar or they will rot from the wet in a
few years</p>
<p>N.° 4   <location_mentioned>Dining room</location_mentioned>, 24 feet square—a door in the <location_mentioned>South west 
corner</location_mentioned> which opens into the <location_mentioned>front gallery</location_mentioned>, another in <location_mentioned>north
west corner </location_mentioned>which opens into the <location_mentioned>back gallery </location_mentioned>  The upper
part of this last door ought to be of glass—   A door into
the passage, and a glass door in the <location_mentioned>South east corner</location_mentioned> on
the gallery of the <location_mentioned>east wing</location_mentioned> marked G D-</p>
<p>N.° 5   <location_mentioned>Passage </location_mentioned>10 feet by 24—a door at each end with a half round
window over head of each door</p
<p>N.os 6 and 7  <location_mentioned> Bed room</location_mentioned> 12 by 24 with a corner fire place in each out
of N.° 7 a door of glass at G D to open to the back gallery of
the west wing</p>
<p>N.° 8   <location_mentioned>West wing</location_mentioned> 14 by 16 with a fireplace and a Gallery on each
side 5 feet wide</p>
<p>N.0 9   A <location_mentioned>closet </location_mentioned>on the back gallery of the <location_mentioned>west wing</location_mentioned></p>
<p>N.os 10 and 11  <location_mentioned> childrens bed rooms</location_mentioned>, through which there is a 
communication into the <location_mentioned>back gallery</location_mentioned> without having to go round
through the passage</p>
<p>N.° 12   <location_mentioned>Back gallery</location_mentioned> 12 by 18 feet—   This will be useful to 
breakfast or Dine in the summer and to keep the water buckets
and wash bowls &c &c—</p>
<p>N.° 13   <location_mentioned>Pantry</location_mentioned>, which opens into the <location_mentioned>back gallery</location_mentioned> and is adjoining
to the <location_mentioned>dining room</location_mentioned>, through the G D at the <location_mentioned>north west
corner</location_mentioned></p>
<p>N.° 14   <location_mentioned>Store room </location_mentioned>12 feet square—such a room is indispensable to
keep liquors and necessaries of various kinds in—</p>
<p>N.0 15 <location_mentioned>Closet </location_mentioned>on the <location_mentioned>back gallery</location_mentioned> of the <location_mentioned>east wing</location_mentioned></p>
<p>N.° 16 <location_mentioned>East wing</location_mentioned>— This is <location_mentioned><person_mentioned>S. F. Austin</person_mentioned>s room </location_mentioned>and is to be finished
expressly for him In the passage there must be a stair
case to go up into the <location_mentioned>garret </location_mentioned>where there may be two good
<location_mentioned>winter bed rooms</location_mentioned>, one at each end, with windows in the
<location_mentioned>gable ends</location_mentioned>—the roofs of the wings need not be as high
as the main body—in fact they might be made flat roofs
with a door to go out of the <location_mentioned>garret </location_mentioned>on them, so as to have
a view of the <location_mentioned>bay</location_mentioned>—</p>

<p>Agreeably to this plan the <location_mentioned>west half and west wing</location_mentioned> of
the house can be made entirely private, for <person_mentioned>family </person_mentioned>use—
for besides the doors into the passage out of N.os 6 and 7
there will be two private back doors, one out of N.° 7 on to
the <location_mentioned>back gallery</location_mentioned> of the <location_mentioned>west wing</location_mentioned>, and one through the<barker_pb n="718"/>
<location_mentioned>childrens bed rooms</location_mentioned> 10 and 11 into the main back gallery,
and thence into the <location_mentioned>pantry </location_mentioned>and <location_mentioned>Store room,</location_mentioned> or out to the
<location_mentioned>kitchen</location_mentioned></p>

<p>The <location_mentioned>pantry </location_mentioned>situated as it is, will be convenient to the <location_mentioned>kitchen</location_mentioned>, and
<location_mentioned>dining room</location_mentioned>, and <location_mentioned>store room</location_mentioned>, and will be a useful and handy place
to arrange and prepare the materials and knicknacks of a dinner or
supper—-also to keep crockery ware &c &c. The <location_mentioned>west wing</location_mentioned> will be
a very pleasant and a very private <location_mentioned>family room</location_mentioned> either for summer
or winter.</p>

<p>The <location_mentioned>dining room</location_mentioned> is large enough to entertain <person_mentioned>company </person_mentioned>in handsome
stile without being jamed to death for want of room—and it will
make a very pleasant <location_mentioned>sitting room</location_mentioned> winter or summer— The door
into the<location_mentioned> back gallery</location_mentioned> will communicate with the kitchen and pantry.
The <location_mentioned>East wing</location_mentioned> will make a room for<person_mentioned> S. F. Austin</person_mentioned>, and will be 
connected with the body of the house through the glass door into the
dining room out of the front gallery of the <location_mentioned>East wing</location_mentioned>.—</p>

<p>The body of the room ought to be 14 feet between the floors so as
to give the roof a sufficient pitch over the galleries— The wings
ought to be 12 feet between the <location_mentioned>floors </location_mentioned>and <location_mentioned>flat roofs</location_mentioned> with banisters
around them—</p>

<p>By raising the house four or five feet from the ground, a <location_mentioned>cellar</location_mentioned>
may be easily made under a part of it—</p>

<p>The whole body of the house might be raised now and enclosed,
making a calculation to add the two wings afterwards, taking care
to have the <location_mentioned>fireplaces </location_mentioned>made on the outside of the wings, and also
to have all the mortises made that might be necessary to unite the
wings to the main body and the wings could then be put up next
year when there is more time to do it— The <location_mentioned>west half of the main
part of the house</location_mentioned>, that is the rooms 6. 7. 10. 11. and S might be
finished this winter and spring so as to receive the <person_mentioned>family</person_mentioned>, and the
whole of the <location_mentioned>east part of the house </location_mentioned>might be let alone and finished
next summer and fall— Lime is so convenient there from shells,
that I would lathe and plaster the inside of all the rooms it will be
much cheaper I think than to ciel them with planks</p>

<p>By commencing on this plan the whole of it may be finished at
different times at a leisure spell or according as <person_mentioned>workmen </person_mentioned>and 
lumber can be had for the <person_mentioned>family </person_mentioned>can move as soon as the rooms 6. 7. 10.
and 11 are finished, or even half finished— This house will be a 
convenient one and large enough for your <person_mentioned>family </person_mentioned>and leave some rooms
to accomodate <person_mentioned>friends </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>visitors</person_mentioned>, of whom you will have a 
number after a while— In a year or two, should more room be wanted,
another <location_mentioned>story </location_mentioned>can very easily be put on to each of the <location_mentioned>wings</location_mentioned></p>

<p>I think that 10 feet is wide enough for the passage, this passage is
in fact but of little use except to divide the house and make the rooms<barker_pb n="719"/>

[Image did not transfer - DL]

<barker_pb n="720"/>

private, and also for the stairs to go up into the <location_mentioned>garret</location_mentioned>— The
ground for the <location_mentioned>garden </location_mentioned>and <location_mentioned>orchard</location_mentioned>, and <location_mentioned>cow pens</location_mentioned> and <location_mentioned>stables </location_mentioned><location_mentioned>corn
cribs </location_mentioned>&c &c, and also the place for the <location_mentioned>kitchen </location_mentioned>and <location_mentioned>smoke house</location_mentioned> and
the <location_mentioned>hen house</location_mentioned> and <location_mentioned>poultry yard</location_mentioned> ought all to be selected and marked
out before the <location_mentioned>house </location_mentioned>is raised, and then you will do everything on
a fixed plan, and all will come out right, even if you are three or
four years finishing it—</p>

<p><person_mentioned>S. F. Austin</person_mentioned></p>

<p><date_mentioned n="11-30-1831">November 30, 1831</date_mentioned>.</p>

<p>This plan shows the situation of the <location_mentioned>garden</location_mentioned>, <location_mentioned>yards</location_mentioned>, <location_mentioned>kitchen</location_mentioned>,
<location_mentioned> cowpens</location_mentioned>, <location_mentioned>stables </location_mentioned>&c— I think that 16 feet square is too small for the
<location_mentioned>kitchen</location_mentioned>, it ought to be 20 feet at least, for the chimney and oven
will take up all one side and in this hot climate a small room for a
kitchen would be very hot and unhealthy— All the <location_mentioned>back buildings
</location_mentioned>ought to be brick with brick floors—a common log cabin would do for
a <location_mentioned>kitchen </location_mentioned>untill you could build of brick you will have to make
bricks next fall for your chimneys— The place where you ought
to make the brick is up the <location_mentioned>Chocolate bayou</location_mentioned> at <location_mentioned>Brays old Cabbin
</location_mentioned>where there is Clay and Timber, and take the brick down by water</p>

<p>By beginning on this plan and finishing it by degrees you can do
it all in a year or 18 months and not feel it materially—and when
it is done you will have a valuable place and a convenient one</p>

<p>EXPLANATION OF PLAN</p>

<p>No. 1 <location_mentioned>Horse Lot</location_mentioned>—The fence round this lot ought to be very high
and strong so as to pen wild horses or Cattle—which can
be driven into the <location_mentioned>lane </location_mentioned>and so through the bars</p>
<p>No. 2 <location_mentioned>Calf Lot</location_mentioned> and <location_mentioned>Cow pens </location_mentioned>  to be divided so as to make it convenient for milking</p>
<p>No. 3 Gate or bars   To go out and in with a carriage or on Horse
back, so as not to interfere with the trees in front of the
house</p>
<p>No. 4 <location_mentioned>Front Yard</location_mentioned>   to be planted with orange trees etc</p>
<p>No. 5 In this<location_mentioned> back yard</location_mentioned> the <location_mentioned>pig styes</location_mentioned>—<location_mentioned>Lye gums</location_mentioned> and such things
can be put up</p>
<p>No. 6 This is laid off <location_mentioned>North </location_mentioned>and <location_mentioned>East</location_mentioned>, and I think it will suit the
course of the <location_mentioned>Creek </location_mentioned>and timber to place the house in that
way and make all the fences to correspond</p>
<p>Note—The Garden fence ought to run <location_mentioned>down to the Creek</location_mentioned>, and also
the <location_mentioned>calf lot </location_mentioned>fence—   This would leave a space of upwards of an
100 feet wide from the garden fence to the <location_mentioned>calf lot</location_mentioned> fence extending
back of the kitchen down to the <location_mentioned>Creek </location_mentioned>which would serve as <location_mentioned>back
yard</location_mentioned>, <location_mentioned>poultry yard</location_mentioned>—and a place for washing and drying clothes,<barker_pb n="720"/>
then there need be no cross fence back of kitchen for the<location_mentioned> back yard
</location_mentioned>would reach all the way down to the <location_mentioned>creek </location_mentioned>which would be about
<location_mentioned>200 yards from the kitchen </location_mentioned>and about 150 yards of that distance
would be through the woods-—</p>

<p>None of these <location_mentioned>woods </location_mentioned>must be cut down on any account as they will
be a shade for the <location_mentioned>calf and poultry lots</location_mentioned> and break off the north
winds from the <location_mentioned>gardin </location_mentioned>and <location_mentioned>orchard</location_mentioned></p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
