
<TEI.2 id="APB1070">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>04-03-1825</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1064-1065</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Humphrey Jackson</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Stephen F. Austin</document_recipient>
<document_title>Humphrey Jackson to Stephen F. Austin, 04-03-1825</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Unknown</sent_from>
	<sent_to>San Jacinto, Texas</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Humphrey Jackson to Austin, April 3, 1825. Judicial procedure in the case of the schooner Mary. The settlers east of San Jacinto wish to remain in
Austin's colony.
</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes></barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1064-1065</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>06-02-2010</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>


<text id="APB1070T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Humphrey Jackson to Austin, April 3, 1825. Judicial procedure in the case of the schooner Mary. The settlers east of San Jacinto wish to remain in Austin's colony.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p>Sir</p>

<p>Inclosed you have the statement of <person_mentioned>James Strange</person_mentioned> Respecting the
* time he was on board the Schooner Mary</location_mentioned> he has had no opportunity
of seeing the <person_mentioned>Alcalde</person_mentioned> since you requested me to get it he says he is
willing to swair to it any time if requested he being very busay at
present I have every reason to belive the within statement of<person_mentioned> Mr.
Strang</person_mentioned> to be Correct I am certain he would not state any thing but
what was true the <person_mentioned>Settlers</person_mentioned> on the<location_mentioned> East of the San Jacinto</location_mentioned> is 
unanimous to Continue in your <location_mentioned>Collony</location_mentioned> they are willing to sine any
Pe[ti]tion for that purpose if you are willing to accept us in your
<location_mentioned>Collony</location_mentioned> I have not been at the <location_mentioned>Trinity</location_mentioned> since I seen you and has not
any thing particular to mention</p>

<p><person_mentioned>H Jackson</person_mentioned></p>

<p>To <person_mentioned>Corl S F Austin</person_mentioned> <location_mentioned>San Jacinto</location_mentioned> <date_mentioned n="04-03-1825">April 3rd 1825</date_mentioned></p>
<p><location_mentioned>Austin Collony District of San Jacinto</location_mentioned></p>

<p><person_mentioned>James Strange the Constable for said District</person_mentioned> Recd, an Attachment
from<person_mentioned> H Jackson Alcalde for said District</person_mentioned> against the <person_mentioned>Master and
owners of the <location_mentioned>Schooner Mary</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> which Attachment I Executed <location_mentioned>on the
Said Schooner</location_mentioned> on the <date_mentioned n="05-01-1824">first of May 1825</date_mentioned> at <location_mentioned>Red fish Bar</location_mentioned> for severel
days after I went on board the wind blowing a gail at <location_mentioned>South</location_mentioned> and
<location_mentioned>South East</location_mentioned> the Vessel Drifting with one Anchor we put the Cabose
out with the small lower Cable it held her a few ours she again
Drifted and commenced thumping <person_mentioned>Capt. Carrico</person_mentioned> Asked my Advice
what was best to do I told him if I give my advice I might be rong
he told me no he Asked for it and I could not be rong in giving it   if<barker_pb n="1065"/>
he did not liked it he could let it alone I told him as he had been
taulcking of Riming Hir a ground and some times of Cutting a way
the Masts if he would now slip the Cable and hoist Sail it was most
likely we could get hir thru the <location_mentioned>Pass of Red fish bar</location_mentioned> and if we could
I could bring her into the <location_mentioned>San Jacinto</location_mentioned> and lay her safe a long the
banck he then gave orders to slip the Cable Maicking sail the
Schooner by this time was so fast a ground she would not mind her
helm <person_mentioned>Capt. Carrico</person_mentioned> then gave orders to hoist all the sail we could and
run hir a ground—at this time there was <location_mentioned>on board </location_mentioned><person_mentioned>Capt Carrico</person_mentioned> the
Cook <person_mentioned>Robert Passmon</person_mentioned> <person_mentioned>the guard</person_mentioned> and my self while I Remained <location_mentioned>on
board</location_mentioned> I took no Command of the Vessel further than preventing hir
pulling to say the Guard and I obayed <person_mentioned>Capt Carrico</person_mentioned> orders and 
assisted in every thing he wanted to be don we don the most of the
pumping the Vessel being very leaky</p>
<p><person_mentioned>James Strange</person_mentioned></p>
<p><date_mentioned n="04-03-1825">April 3 1825</date_mentioned></p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
