
<TEI.2 id="APB4174">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>03-20-1831</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 619-621</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Henry Austin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Stephen F Austin</document_recipient>
<document_title>Henry Austin to Stephen F Austin, 03-20-1831</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>New Orleans, Louisiana</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Leona Vicario or Saltillo, Coahuila</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Henry Austin to Austin, New Orleans, March 20, 1831. Cotton mills for Texas.    Land.    Plans for improvement of the country.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes></barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 619-621</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>09-08-2010</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>


<text id="APB4174T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Henry Austin to Austin, New Orleans, March 20, 1831. Cotton mills for Texas.    Land.    Plans for improvement of the country.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><location_mentioned>New Orleans</location_mentioned>, <date_mentioned n="03-20-1831">March 20, 1831</date_mentioned></p>
<p><person_mentioned>Col S F Austin</person_mentioned></p>

<p>My dear Sir I have written you a long letter by this conveyance
on the subject of <person_mentioned>Mr Ware</person_mentioned>s propositions. I have since had further
conversation with him and find he wishes to come to some conclusion
on the subject before his departure for <location_mentioned>Philada </location_mentioned>if practicable.</p>

<p>In the absence of any advices from you I am some what at loss
what to decide upon. <person_mentioned>Genl Terans officio to the Consul</person_mentioned> requesting
him to facilitate by passports <person_mentioned>emigrants </person_mentioned>to your <location_mentioned>colony </location_mentioned>and also to
<person_mentioned>Dewit</person_mentioned>s and <person_mentioned>McMullen</person_mentioned>s looks more favorable as does the advice from
<location_mentioned>Brasoria </location_mentioned>that the <person_mentioned>collector sent by Bradburn</person_mentioned> had orders to respect
indentures of <person_mentioned>servants</person_mentioned>. We are satisfied that <person_mentioned>Buy </person_mentioned>has no exclusive
right and that the enterprise might be safely undertaken. <person_mentioned>Mr
Ware</person_mentioned> is willing to embark in the matter immediately and take his
chance for a <location_mentioned>grant </location_mentioned>of land, if I will take the direction of the
business; This I would do if my solicitation were granted but were
I to engage myself as director of this concern, and get no land for
myself nor for the manufacturing concern it would be a bad move.
I must therefore continue here in suspense until the eve of his 
departure in the hope that in the mean time something definitive on
the subject of my solicitation may reach me.</p>

<p>I see that your contract for 500 <person_mentioned>families </person_mentioned>expires on the <date_mentioned n="05-20-1831">20th May
</date_mentioned>next consequently what ever is to be done under that grant must be
done promptly I therefore give you our views that whatever may
be needful to be done at <location_mentioned>Saltillo </location_mentioned>may be done whilst you are there
so far as you may deem it expedient</p>

<p>1st It would be desirable to secure a good <location_mentioned>Mill seat</location_mentioned> in a good 
position. This we could not expect to do in <location_mentioned>vacant land</location_mentioned> and must
purchase. It is said <location_mentioned>Houghs on the Bernard</location_mentioned> or <location_mentioned>peach creek</location_mentioned> is the
best in the <location_mentioned>Colony </location_mentioned>and that he offered to sell his league and an
half for 2000$ but the question arises, can he alienate with legal
title, for not having cultivated in totality? It will not do to expend
40,000$ on land that may be taken away from us:— The same 
difficulty might arise were we to use steam power on a purchased tract.</p><barker_pb n="620"/>

<p>Can this difficulty be obviated without legislative provision? 2° We
cannot now give you the name in which to locate the <location_mentioned>grant </location_mentioned>for the
encouragement of a <location_mentioned>cotton manufactory</location_mentioned> and may not be able to do
it before the <date_mentioned n="05-20-1831">20 May</date_mentioned>. Is there any mode by which you can get legal
authority to grant a <location_mentioned>premium of 11 leagues</location_mentioned> to the <person_mentioned>proprietor of the
<location_mentioned>Cotton Factory,</</location_mentioned>person_mentioned> being resident, on his putting in actual operation
at least 1000 spindles if you think proper to do so? This would
arm you for a contract with any other party should this one back
out, but I should expect you to give us the preference if the thing
be done.</p>

<p>My first intention was, in case my solicitation were granted to go
to <location_mentioned>England </location_mentioned>with a small Brig to get my equipment and a stock
of goods for the <location_mentioned>colony </location_mentioned>at first cost to make arrangements for a
direct trade between the <location_mentioned>colony </location_mentioned>and <location_mentioned>England</location_mentioned>, procure <person_mentioned>English 
Artizans</person_mentioned> to erect my <location_mentioned>buildings </location_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>laborers </person_mentioned>under indentures for two
or three years, and run out direct to <location_mentioned><hi rend="italic">Port Austin</hi></location_mentioned><location_mentioned> west end of 
Galveston</location_mentioned> in <date_mentioned n="10-xx-1831">October </date_mentioned>or <date_mentioned n="11-xx-1831">November </date_mentioned>next. At the same time I could
ascertain whether a contract could be made for supplying the <location_mentioned>King's
dockyard</location_mentioned> with live oak, rail road, etc—-but I cannot command funds
enough to do it on my own acct, I do not chuse to engage in it for
the benefit of others. The duty on foreign timber is too high in
<location_mentioned>England </location_mentioned>for private contract there. From <location_mentioned>New York </location_mentioned>I learn that
live oak cut promiscuously will not more than pay charges from
<location_mentioned>Florida </location_mentioned>but large timber cut to moulds is valuable. <person_mentioned>Mr Echford
</person_mentioned>who has the most knowledge of anybody on this subject is to send
me all needful information and the best mode of making it 
available. I mentioned in my last <person_mentioned>Mrs Holley</person_mentioned>s desire to obtain a 
settlement <location_mentioned>grant </location_mentioned>for <person_mentioned>herself </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>son</person_mentioned>. She is fully determined to go
to the <location_mentioned>Colony </location_mentioned>if she can get land for her <person_mentioned>son</person_mentioned>. In case you think
proper to comply with her wish please enclose her the form of
application for her to sign and send back. Her adress is<person_mentioned>—Mrs Mary
Austin Holley</person_mentioned> care of <person_mentioned>Mr Hermogene</person_mentioned> <location_mentioned>La Branch New Orleans</location_mentioned>.
She intends to pass the <date_mentioned n="Summer - 1831">Summer </date_mentioned>here, her sons name is <person_mentioned>Horace
Holley</person_mentioned>.   Respectfully and cordially yours     <person_mentioned>H Austin  </person_mentioned>  [Rubric]</p>

<p>I have this moment recd a letter from our <person_mentioned>cousin Charles Austin
now Mayor of <location_mentioned>Tallahasse, Florida</location_mentioned>.</person_mentioned> He says <person_mentioned>Mr Morgan</person_mentioned> who has
just returned from <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, has set the people <hi rend="italic"><location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>mad</hi> and many
say they shall go there this <date_mentioned n="Fall-1831">fall</date_mentioned>, he says good lands sell there at
5 or 6$ pr Acre 25$ pr acre has been offered for <location_mentioned><person_mentioned>Lafayette</person_mentioned>s 22.000
acres</location_mentioned>. That country in general is wretchedly poor. His son <person_mentioned>Thomas
Hopkins Austin</person_mentioned> is now here, a fine young man, I have placed him
with <person_mentioned>Mr Bogert</person_mentioned> for the present. He wishd to visit <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>but is
not yet experienced enough to trade in that <location_mentioned>country</location_mentioned>.   <person_mentioned>Charles </person_mentioned>says<barker_pb n="321"/>
he had been desired to call him <location_mentioned>home </location_mentioned>to join a young man of Capital
in an adventure to <hi rend="italic"><location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></hi>.</p>

[Addressed:] Al <person_mentioned>Sor Coronel Estevan F Austin</person_mentioned> <location_mentioned>Leona Vicario ó Saltillo</location_mentioned>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
