
<TEI.2 id="APB1965">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>06-16-1830</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1922: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1928), 3 vols., Vol 2, pp. 421-423</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Stephen F Austin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Richared Ellis et al</document_recipient>
<document_title>Stephen F Austin to Richared Ellis et al, 06-16-1830</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>San Felipe de Austin, Texas</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Austin to Richard Ellis, et al., June 16, 1830. Interpretation of law of April 6, 1830. Law and constitution against slavery will be rigidly enforced. Austin approves of this.   Does not want Texas to become a slave country.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes></barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 421-423</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>08-21-2010</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>


<text id="APB1965T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Austin to Richard Ellis, et al., June 16, 1830. Interpretation of law of April 6, 1830. Law and constitution against slavery will be rigidly enforced. Austin approves of this.   Does not want Texas to become a slave country.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><location_mentioned>San Felipe de Austin</location_mentioned><date_mentioned n="06-16-1830"> June 16 1830</date_mentioned></p>
<p>Gentlemen,</p>

<p>You have no doubt seen published in the <location_mentioned>news papers of the
United States,</location_mentioned> the law of the <date_mentioned n="04-06-1830">6th of April last</date_mentioned> passed by the 
<person_mentioned>Mexican Congress </person_mentioned>relative to foreign emigration and other matters.
The 10th article of that law declares that no variation shall be
made <location_mentioned>in those colonies already established.</location_mentioned> My <location_mentioned>colony </location_mentioned>is 
established, and no legal impediment will of course be interposed to the
removal to it of those who have contracted to become <person_mentioned>settlers</person_mentioned>; for
they properly belong to the <location_mentioned>colony </location_mentioned>as much as those who are here.</p>

<p>The law requires that passports should be brought by the 
<person_mentioned>emigrants </person_mentioned>from a <person_mentioned>Mexican consul</person_mentioned>, and this must be done— The 
government has ordered most positively that the 13th article of the
State constitution shall be rigidly inforced, and I am of the opinion
that <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>will never become a <location_mentioned>Slave state or country</location_mentioned>. I will be
candid with you on this point, and say that I hope it never may.</p>

<p>You will recollect that the 13th Article above alluded to is in
these words— No person shall be born a <person_mentioned>slave in this <location_mentioned>state</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>, after
the publication of this constitution in the <location_mentioned>capital of each district,</location_mentioned><barker_pb n="422"/>
and <date_mentioned n="10-06-1830">six months after the publication of this constitution,</date_mentioned> the 
introduction of <person_mentioned>Slaves </person_mentioned>shall not be permitted under any pretext. The
constitution was published in <date_mentioned n="05-xx-1827">may 1827</date_mentioned>. Since then the 
legislature has passed a law guaranteeing contracts, (not contrary to the
laws of this state) made in<location_mentioned> foreign countries</location_mentioned>, so as to permit 
<person_mentioned>families </person_mentioned>to bring the necessary and indispensable <person_mentioned>house servants</person_mentioned> and
<person_mentioned>labourers</person_mentioned>. This provision will be highly useful to the <location_mentioned>country</location_mentioned>
without the least danger of doing any harm for no one will be
willing to risk a large capital in <person_mentioned>negroes </person_mentioned>under contracts with them,
for they are free on their arrival here, and can only be held to
labour by contracts, as <person_mentioned>servants </person_mentioned>are all over this <location_mentioned>nation</location_mentioned>, and in
<location_mentioned>other free countries</location_mentioned>.</p>

<p>In the commencement of this <location_mentioned>settlement</location_mentioned>, I was in favour of the
limited admission of <person_mentioned>slaves</person_mentioned>—- My reasons were, the difficulty of 
procuring <person_mentioned>hands </person_mentioned>in the beginning for the necessary purposes of farming,
and the necessity of holding out inducements that <person_mentioned>slaves </person_mentioned>might be
brought, in order to give the settlement a start, and to draw 
emigration, a truly difficult thing to do at that time. It was an up-hill
business to get a <location_mentioned>settlement </location_mentioned>under way by any means, in the midst of
an entire <location_mentioned>wilderness </location_mentioned>infested with hostile <person_mentioned>Indians</person_mentioned>. The reasons for a
partial toleration of this evil, have now ceased, and the true 
prosperity and happiness of <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>require; that an everlasting bar should
be interposed to the farther introduction of <person_mentioned>slaves</person_mentioned>. Those already in
the country, are to be <person_mentioned>slaves </person_mentioned>for life, unless purchased by 
government, and freed in that way. This is just—-for the law permitted
their introduction. Their <person_mentioned>descendants </person_mentioned>are, of course, free— 
Measures have been taken to exclude<person_mentioned> free negroes</person_mentioned> and <person_mentioned>Mullatoes</person_mentioned>, not 
<person_mentioned>indented servants</person_mentioned>; so that there is no danger of being crowded with
that class, which is probably a worse nuisance than <person_mentioned>slaves</person_mentioned>. I cannot
believe that any reflecting man, either in <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>or out of it, can
seriously wish that slavery should be entailed upon this <location_mentioned>country</location_mentioned>.</p>

<p>To those who do not reflect, I would say, u take your pen-—put
down the number of <person_mentioned>slaves </person_mentioned>now in the <location_mentioned>slave states</location_mentioned>—calculate their
increase for eighty years at the known ratio of augmentation— 
Calculate the extent of <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>to which they are, and must be confined,
and its capacity to support human beings—- Then calculate the
number of<person_mentioned> white population</person_mentioned> and their increase-—deduct from said
increase, the emigration of <person_mentioned>whites </person_mentioned>to other <location_mentioned>countries</location_mentioned>; (no such 
deduction can be made from the increase of <person_mentioned>blacks</person_mentioned>, for they cannot 
emigrate,) compare the two sums, and then suppose that you will be
alive at the period above mentioned, that you have a long-cherished
and beloved <person_mentioned>wife</person_mentioned>, a number of <person_mentioned>daughters</person_mentioned>, <person_mentioned>grand daughters</person_mentioned>, and
<person_mentioned>great grand daughters</person_mentioned>;—would no fears for their fate, a horrible
fate; intrude themselves upon your pillow, and overcloud the evening
of your life???—</p><barker_pb n="423"/>

<p>If <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>is wisely and prudently managed, it will be saved from
the overwhelming ruin which mathematical demonstration declares
must overtake the <location_mentioned>slave states</location_mentioned>; and the <person_mentioned>white population</person_mentioned> will find
within the <person_mentioned>Mexican </person_mentioned>limits a refuge; without being driven to the
<location_mentioned>frozen regions of the north</location_mentioned>. To talk to some of the<person_mentioned> slave holders</person_mentioned>
about justice, humanity, etc, would be talking to a<person_mentioned> deaf man</person_mentioned>, but I
will not believe that any one can look on the future which the above
calculation presents, without shuddering—</p>

<p>The law of the <date_mentioned n="04-06-1830">6th of April</date_mentioned> gives permission to foreign vessels
to engage in the <location_mentioned>Coasting trade</location_mentioned> from the <location_mentioned>colonies </location_mentioned>to the <location_mentioned>ports of
Matamoras and Tampico and Vera Cruz</location_mentioned>. It also admits all kind of
provisions and lumber, free of duty, into the ports of <location_mentioned>Matagorda </location_mentioned>and
<location_mentioned>Galveston</location_mentioned>, for two years. No duties of any kind will be collected,
except tonage, until after the expiration of the law of <date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1823">1823</date_mentioned>, 
exempting <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>from duties for seven years from its publication in the
<location_mentioned>Capital of Texas</location_mentioned>—   It will expire in<date_mentioned n="11-xx-1830"> November next</date_mentioned>.—</p>

<p>You will be pleased to communicate the contents of this letter to
the <person_mentioned>emigrants </person_mentioned>who have contracted to remove to this <location_mentioned>colony </location_mentioned>from
your <location_mentioned>neighbourhood</location_mentioned>.</p>

<p><person_mentioned>S. F. Austin </person_mentioned>   [Rubric]</p>

<p>To <person_mentioned>Mess. Richd Ellis</person_mentioned> <person_mentioned>Geo. Sutherland</person_mentioned> <person_mentioned>Anthony Winston</person_mentioned> <person_mentioned>R. R.
Royal,</person_mentioned> etc etc—  </p>                                                               

<p>The <person_mentioned>colonists in <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned></person_mentioned>have been well and munificently treated by
this Gvt and are satisfied and contented with their situation— the
most undisturbed harmony and tranquility prevails through out all
<location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>—<person_mentioned> Genl Teran</person_mentioned> is shortly expected on here with some <person_mentioned>troops</person_mentioned>
and some <person_mentioned>evil minded persons</person_mentioned> have circulated reports that his object
is to oppress the <person_mentioned>colonists</person_mentioned>— Those reports are without any real
foundation in truth, and have no effect here, but as rumor flies on the
wings of the wind it may waft them to you—but pay no attention
to them— those who bring their <person_mentioned>families </person_mentioned>here, and can produce
evidence that they belong to a contract on colonization which is in
legal opperation, and who can also bring unequivocal evidences of
good character, have nothing to fear—</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
