
<TEI.2 id="APB1966">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>06-17-1830</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1922: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1928), 3 vols., Vol 2, pp. 423-429</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Stephen F Austin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>S Rhoads Fisher</document_recipient>
<document_title>Stephen F Austin to S Rhoads Fisher, 06-17-1830</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>San Felipe de Austin, Texas</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Austin to S. Rhoads Fisher, June 17, 1830. Politics of Mexico settling,
but no hope of permanent quiet. Policy has apparently changed toward
colonization. Reasons for change partly in imprudence of Poinsett and suspicions of the United States. Discussion of colonization of Texas with Swiss and Germans, exclusion of slaves, final independence of Texas if Mexico disintegrates. Suggests that Fisher discuss such topics in Philadelphia papers. Austin emphatically opposed to union with the United States.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes></barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 423-429</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>08-21-2010</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>


<text id="APB1966T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Austin to S. Rhoads Fisher, June 17, 1830. Politics of Mexico settling,
but no hope of permanent quiet. Policy has apparently changed toward
colonization. Reasons for change partly in imprudence of Poinsett and suspicions of the United States. Discussion of colonization of Texas with Swiss and Germans, exclusion of slaves, final independence of Texas if Mexico disintegrates. Suggests that Fisher discuss such topics in Philadelphia papers. Austin emphatically opposed to union with the United States</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p>San Felipe de Austin June 17 1830</p>

<p>Confidential</p>
<p><person_mentioned>S Rhoads Fisher Esqr</person_mentioned>.</p>

<p>My dear Sir, I have just recd yours of <date_mentioned n="06-02-1830">2d inst</date_mentioned> requesting 
information as to the political aspect of affairs in this <location_mentioned>country</location_mentioned>; the
course which the Govt are pursuing towards the <person_mentioned>settlers</person_mentioned>; and ask-<barker_pb n="424"/>
ing my advice as to the removal of your <person_mentioned>family </person_mentioned>here the ensuing
fall.</p>

<p>In relation to the first,—it is rather difficult to say what is the
real state of things at present <location_mentioned>at the seat of Govt in Mexico</location_mentioned>. So
far as can be infered from the public prints, things are more
settled than they have been for some time, and <person_mentioned>Bustamante </person_mentioned>appears
to sit more quietly in the<location_mentioned> Presidential chair</location_mentioned> than he did. <person_mentioned>Genl
Bravo</person_mentioned> has defeated the <person_mentioned>force </person_mentioned>that was in the field near <location_mentioned>?ccapulco </location_mentioned>
in support of <person_mentioned>Guerrero </person_mentioned>and the latter seems to be a <person_mentioned>fugitive</person_mentioned>. 
Perhaps it would be safe to say that no certain calculations can be
made as to the political affairs of the <location_mentioned>capital</location_mentioned>, or as to what changes
may take place in the form of Govt, or whether any. I am 
inclined to think that none will be made, altho, there seems to be a
party in favor of a <person_mentioned>central Govt</person_mentioned>.— In this <location_mentioned>colony </location_mentioned>all is peace, 
harmony, and union—more than ever has been: The prospects of crops
are very good and promise abundance.</p>

<p>On the 2d point— The policy of this Govt seems to have changed
as to colonization in <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, as you may see by the 11th article of
the law of <date_mentioned n="04-06-1830">6th of April </date_mentioned>last, which prohibits emigration from the
<location_mentioned>U. S</location_mentioned>.— The 10th Article of that law however declares that no
variation shall be made <location_mentioned>in the colonies already established</location_mentioned> This
completely covers my <location_mentioned>colony</location_mentioned>, for it is established, and no legal
impediment can be interposed to the emigration of the <person_mentioned>colonists</person_mentioned>
who properly belong to my contracts, neither do I believe that any
will be.</p>

<p>If an opinion can be formed from the public prints, this law has
been produced by a chain of circumstances, some of which are the
following.<person_mentioned> Mr. Poinsett</person_mentioned> became very unpopular, as it seems, and
the prints of <location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned>are teeming with the most bitter invectives
against him. This odium seems to have extended to the <person_mentioned>American
people </person_mentioned>and Govt, to a considerable degree. The charges (so far
as they can be infered from Newspapers for I see no proofs) are
that <person_mentioned>Mr. P</person_mentioned>. intermed[dled] with the internal affairs of <location_mentioned>Mexico</location_mentioned>—that
he formed and organised political parties—that he fomented 
disunion—that his object in doing so was to defraud this Govt, out of
<location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>. In proof of this they say that as soon as all <location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned>was
thrown into convulsions by the virulence of the <person_mentioned>Yorkino </person_mentioned>(founded
as is said by<person_mentioned> P—</person_mentioned>) and the <person_mentioned>Escoses </person_mentioned>parties, the <location_mentioned><person_mentioned>Jackson </person_mentioned>papers of
the U. S</location_mentioned>. Simultaneously vociforated " we must have <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>" - That
<person_mentioned>P—</person_mentioned> was concerned in the <location_mentioned>grantsof <person_mentioned>Exiter [Exter]</person_mentioned> and <person_mentioned>Zavala</person_mentioned> </location_mentioned>, for
colonizing in <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, this caused a suspicion by inference, that as
he was the <person_mentioned>agent </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>representative </person_mentioned>of the <location_mentioned>U S. </location_mentioned>that <person_mentioned>Govt was also
secretly a colonizer</person_mentioned>, and had improper views as to this <location_mentioned>country</location_mentioned>. To
all this the little imprudences and silly expressions of some of the
<person_mentioned>settlers </person_mentioned><location_mentioned>on the frontiers of Texas and elsewhere,</location_mentioned> have been added,<barker_pb n="425"/>
greatly magnified, and construed by some into disobedience, or a
wish to be disobedient etc, etc,—To these matters, have also been
superadded reports, that the present <person_mentioned>representative of the U. S. Govt
to <location_mentioned>Mexico</location_mentioned>,</person_mentioned> was sent especially to purchase, <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>from <person_mentioned>Guerrero</person_mentioned>,
while he had Dictatorial powers, and was under the control of <person_mentioned>Zavala</person_mentioned>,
who it is known was under that of <person_mentioned>Poinsett</person_mentioned>—The time when this
<person_mentioned>offer </person_mentioned>is said to have been made is also noticed, that is when the
<location_mentioned>nation </location_mentioned>was pressed for money, and in distress owing to the <person_mentioned>Spanish</person_mentioned>
invasion, internal divisions etc. etc. Perhaps I hazard nothing in
saying that causes may be discovered in this train of circumstances,
in connection with others, which would have roused the suspicions
of any people, and more particularly when it is remembered that
the <location_mentioned>north </location_mentioned>is a giant, and <location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned>a new and not firmly organised
Govt, and also that the<location_mentioned> U. S.</location_mentioned> have silently, as it were, extended
their <location_mentioned>dominion </location_mentioned><location_mentioned>over the vast regions of Louisiana, Missouri, 
Oregon etc.</location_mentioned></p>

<p>I give you this detail in order that you may form some idea
of the apparent causes, of the change as regards Colonization in
<location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>— Some on the other hand say that it proceeds from <person_mentioned>British</person_mentioned>
influence or from a desire to exclude <person_mentioned>foreigners </person_mentioned>and liberal 
principles, as a stepping stone to the establishment of a central <location_mentioned>republic</location_mentioned>,
and <location_mentioned>aristocracy</location_mentioned>, or a <location_mentioned>monarchy</location_mentioned>. The free admission however of
all other <person_mentioned>foreigners</person_mentioned>, into <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>except<location_mentioned> North American</location_mentioned>, and of the
latter every where else in the <location_mentioned>nation </location_mentioned>seems to contradict this idea.</p>

<p>1—  Queries: will not the true prosperity and happiness of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>
be more effectually promoted by a <person_mentioned>Swiss</person_mentioned>, <person_mentioned>French</person_mentioned>, <person_mentioned>German</person_mentioned>, and
<person_mentioned>English population</person_mentioned> , than by an <person_mentioned>American </person_mentioned>one, nature seems to
have intended <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>for a vineyard to supply <location_mentioned>America </location_mentioned>with wine.—</p>

<p>2— Is not Slavery a curse which must lead to the total ruin and
butchery of<location_mentioned> all southern slave countries</location_mentioned>, and is it not the duty of
the<person_mentioned> Mexican Govt,</person_mentioned> and the true interest of <person_mentioned>every citizen of Texas
</person_mentioned>to keep this <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>clear of it— A few years more and <location_mentioned>Mexico</location_mentioned>
will be the only resting place left for the <person_mentioned>whites </person_mentioned><location_mentioned>South of Illinois,</location_mentioned>
unless the <person_mentioned>blacks </person_mentioned>are exterminated by a general massacre by the
<person_mentioned>Whites</person_mentioned>; and afterwards excluded from being brought into the
<location_mentioned>country</location_mentioned>— In a century more either the <person_mentioned>whites</person_mentioned>, or the <person_mentioned>blacks </person_mentioned>must
cease to exist in the<location_mentioned> southern States</location_mentioned>, or they must intermarry and
all be placed on an equality.—</p>

<p>3—  Is it not rather unkind in the <location_mentioned>U. S.</location_mentioned> to try to extend its vast
and unwieldy frame <location_mentioned>over a part of the territory</location_mentioned> of its <person_mentioned>neighbor</person_mentioned>?
and is it not impolitic and dangerous even to the integrity of that
<location_mentioned>nation </location_mentioned>to enlarge its limits any farther—?</p>

<p>4—  Will not <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>be equally prosperous as a <location_mentioned>State of the
Mexican confederation</location_mentioned>?</p><barker_pb n="426"/>

<p>5—  If this Govt, totally falls into ruin and this <location_mentioned>nation </location_mentioned>should
be split up into <location_mentioned>separate republics</location_mentioned>, will not <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>be better 
independent, than as a <location_mentioned>part of the U. S.</location_mentioned></p>

<p>6—  Can <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>ever be attached to the<location_mentioned> U S</location_mentioned>. without becoming a
<location_mentioned>slave state,</location_mentioned> and does not phylanthropy and the happiness of so large
a portion of the human race, as can be supported here, imperiously
demand, that slavery should be forever excluded from it ?</p>

<p>7—  Is it not a duty which the <location_mentioned>U. S.</location_mentioned>, as being the most powerful
owes to its <person_mentioned>weaker neighbor</person_mentioned> to step forward and make a full fair
and candid examination of the causes which have produced the
present excitements in <location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned>against her <person_mentioned>citizens</person_mentioned>, and if any of
them or her public agents have been in fault to make it apparent—</p>

<p>8—  Is it not the duty of the <location_mentioned>U. S.</location_mentioned> even to overlook any little
jealoucies which the <person_mentioned>Mexicans </person_mentioned>may have manifested, and to pursue
a conciliatory, rather than a harsh course?—</p>

<p>I think that an able and prudent pen that understood the 
character of the <person_mentioned>Mexicans</person_mentioned>, might do much general good by discussing the
above queries in a prudent and masterly manner in the <location_mentioned>Philadelphia</location_mentioned>,
<location_mentioned>New York</location_mentioned>, <location_mentioned>Baltimore </location_mentioned>etc papers— the <location_mentioned>national Gazette</location_mentioned> would be
a good paper for such a discussion—.</p>

<p>News paper publications of the character of "<person_mentioned>Americanus</person_mentioned>," 
" Patriot " etc added to the train of circumstances which I have stated-
have done great harm to the interests of <person_mentioned>Americans </person_mentioned>in <location_mentioned>Mexico</location_mentioned>-
publications of an opposite character would do much good, by 
removing the impressions now prevalent in <location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned>that all those 
publications proceed from the Govt, and that the object is to excite the
<person_mentioned>American people</person_mentioned> to rush into <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>and take it right, or wrong.—</p>

<p>It has always been my policy to keep <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>out of the <location_mentioned>news papers</location_mentioned>,
but it has been dragged in by others and it must now be kept in,
but the other side of the question must now by discussed—that is to
say, that <hi rend="italic">it <location_mentioned>ought not to he attached to the U. S.</location_mentioned></hi> but remain <location_mentioned>attached
to Mexico</location_mentioned>— it might be stated in favor of this (with reference to
the interests of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>) that the coasting and internal trade and
manufacturing advantages will afford more benefits, than anything
which could be gained by an union with the <location_mentioned>North</location_mentioned>, in fact that 
nothing will be gained by the union but the admission of Slavery and
that it would be a curse etc, etc,— And with reference to the interests
of the<location_mentioned> U. S.</location_mentioned> it may be truly urged that, an extention of <location_mentioned>territory to
the S. W.</location_mentioned> would cause a seperation of the <location_mentioned>union </location_mentioned>etc, etc, etc—</p>

<p>I recommend this matter to your attention you will of course
see its vast importance, and its great delicacy— An excitement has
been <hi rend="italic">written up</hi> against the<location_mentioned> U. S.</location_mentioned> and <person_mentioned>Americans </person_mentioned>in <location_mentioned>Mexico</location_mentioned>— the
object is to <hi rend="italic">write it down</hi>—by removing the causes of jealouscy, and<barker_pb n="427"/>
soothing the feelings of the <person_mentioned>Mexicans </person_mentioned>and even tickling their vanity
in a judicious manner—</p>

<p>As regards my own individual views and objects I will give them
to you with the most perfect frankness and candor. It has been,
and is, my ambition to redeem <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>from the <location_mentioned>wilderness</location_mentioned>, and to
lay a solid foundation for its future prosperity. I do not believe
that, that object can be effected by any kind of union with the <location_mentioned>U. S.</location_mentioned>
for such an union would of course intail slavery on this fair region,
which may be made the <location_mentioned>Eden of America</location_mentioned>— <person_mentioned>satan </person_mentioned>entered the <location_mentioned>sacred
garden</location_mentioned> in the shape of a serpent— if he is allowed to enter <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>
in the shape of <person_mentioned>negros </person_mentioned>it will share the fate of <location_mentioned>Eden</location_mentioned>,— We have
been well treated by the <person_mentioned>Mexican </person_mentioned>Govt, and we are bound by our
oaths to be faithful to it— I will loose my life before I will forfeit
that obligation or do aught which my duty as a <person_mentioned>Mexican citizen</person_mentioned>
forbids—. I wish to see a foundation laid here for the happiness
of posterity, as well as for that of the present generation— I have
no kind of views or ambition for office, neither am I avericious—
my constitution is much broken and I wish for peace and quiet
retirement on a <location_mentioned>stock farm</location_mentioned>—</p>

<p>Perhaps you might embark some able and <hi rend="italic">prudent </hi>person on the
<hi rend="italic">right side</hi> of the <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>question in <location_mentioned>Philadelphia</location_mentioned>—or in other words
on the side of justice and general phylanthropy and peace. I am
totally incompetent to such a task, and besides it would do more
good in the papers of the <location_mentioned>U. S.</location_mentioned> than here, for the excitement was
gotten up <hi rend="italic">there </hi>and <hi rend="italic">there </hi>it ought to be put down-</p>

<p><person_mentioned>Timothy Flint (the <location_mentioned>western review</location_mentioned>)</person_mentioned> at <location_mentioned>Cincinnatti </location_mentioned>would be a
<person_mentioned>master hand</person_mentioned>. I had an acquaintance with him in <location_mentioned>St Louis</location_mentioned> many
years ago If you go there you may if you chuse shew him this letter,
<hi rend="italic">but as confidential</hi>.</p>

<p>Governments like individuals are often moved by trifles— It
may seem to us a silly idea that this <location_mentioned>nation </location_mentioned>can be operated on by
<location_mentioned>news paper publications</location_mentioned> in the<location_mentioned> U. S.</location_mentioned>—but such is the fact (as regards
<location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>) for it has been deeply operated upon to our prejudice by
<person_mentioned>Americanus </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>Patriot </person_mentioned>etc, etc—</p>

<p>My dear Sir let me beg of you to be prudent in the management of
this matter (if you move in it at all)— <person_mentioned>Lord Chesterfield </person_mentioned>(I believe
it was) said that a man had more to fear from imprudent <person_mentioned>friends</person_mentioned>
than from the bitterest <person_mentioned>enemies</person_mentioned>— I am not anxious on my own
account— my health warns me that my days are drawing to a close,
but I have been the means of drawing many <person_mentioned>families </person_mentioned>to <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, and
their present and permanent welfare and happiness is very dear to
me, and costs me many anxious hours and days— The object, of
bringing forward such a country as this, is an immence and an hon-<barker_pb n="428"/>
orable one, it requires infinitely more talents and more strength of
constitution than I possess, and I wish to enlist some efficient aid.</p>

<p>I send you a <location_mentioned>publication </location_mentioned>made in <location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned>by which you can see
the general <hi rend="italic">tone </hi>in that quarter.</p>

<p>As regards the removal of your <person_mentioned>family </person_mentioned>I have to say that my
<person_mentioned>brother in law James F. Perry</person_mentioned> left here three weeks since to bring
his, and I have this day written to him to come on in the fall and not
mind what he sees in the <location_mentioned>public papers</location_mentioned>.</p>

<p>This is the best answer I can give to your 3d enquiry</p>

<p>Should you see my relative <person_mentioned>Thos. F. Learning </person_mentioned>please remember me
to him</p>

<p>I returned from <location_mentioned>Bexar </location_mentioned>a few days since, all is well with the <person_mentioned>State
authorities</person_mentioned>- no news from <person_mentioned>Bowie </person_mentioned>or your petition— The Govt
are encouraging <person_mentioned>Manufactories </person_mentioned>as you can see by the law of<date_mentioned n="04-06-1830"> 6 april</date_mentioned>—
write me often, our coasting trade is open for foreign vessels</p>

<p><person_mentioned>S. F. Austin  </person_mentioned>  [Rubric]</p>

<p>By a pacific and just course I have brought forward this <location_mentioned>colony </location_mentioned>to
what it is-— the same course cannot fail to continue the 
advancement of its prosperity— some visionary <person_mentioned>men </person_mentioned>think that a civil war
would lead to the independence of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>— perhaps it might—but
admitting it would, I have one objection to it which with me is 
conclusive and paramount—<hi rend="italic">it would he unjust</hi>—this is not my only
objection, there are hundreds, but this one is enough—</p>

<p>The <person_mentioned>settlers </person_mentioned>here are really well off, and are satisfied—the only
worm that now works in their heads is that no more emigration is
to come they are not to have <person_mentioned>Slaves </person_mentioned>etc—a prudent course will
remove all these difficulties— We must prove to this Govt, by our
conduct that we deserve its confidence—we must get in <person_mentioned>Swiss</person_mentioned>, and
<person_mentioned>Germans </person_mentioned>and I think that if you could excite some educated, common
sence, practical <person_mentioned>men </person_mentioned>of those <location_mentioned>nations </location_mentioned>to come and view this <location_mentioned>country</location_mentioned>;
it would be the means of paving the way for a great emigration—
our <person_mentioned>country men </person_mentioned>in general want <person_mentioned>slaves</person_mentioned>-— this is a troublesome
question to get on with, they must be reasoned with and brought
round by degrees and prudence— The minds of the people here at
this time are very quiet and settled, but one imprudent measure on
the part of <person_mentioned>Govt</person_mentioned>, would have a dreadful effect-— This must be
closely watched and guarded against if possible and harmony and
peace preserved</p>

<p>I send you a copy of my letter to the <person_mentioned>Alabama Gentlemen</person_mentioned> who
were out here <date_mentioned n="Fall -1829">last fall </date_mentioned>and contracted to emigrate— I have, 
requested them to publish it in <location_mentioned>Tuscumbia papers</location_mentioned>—they may not do
it owing to what I have said about Slavery—if they do not you can
if you chuse, exercise your judgement and publish it or not, as you
think best, in some <location_mentioned>Philadelphia paper—</location_mentioned>   write me your candid<barker_pb n="429"/>
opinion as to the course of policy which I have indicated in this
letter— if you disapprove of it—state your reasons—and suggest
alterations— Try and pry into <person_mentioned>old Hickorys cabinet </person_mentioned>so far as to
know what they wish to do as regards <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, how they feel towards
this <location_mentioned>nation</location_mentioned>—tho. I cannot believe that they can have any hostile
feelings for I know of no just motive—</p>

<p>I have scribbled a long letter—too long to Sacmt en limpia, and
must send it all blotted and scratched etc. I have a rough copy of
it—a correct translation of the <location_mentioned>Voz de la patria</location_mentioned>, might serve as a
text, to preach from, for it will shew that hostile feelings do exist
in <location_mentioned>Mexico</location_mentioned>, it will then be natural enough to ask, why they exist?—</p>

<p><person_mentioned>S. F Austin   </person_mentioned> [Rubric]</p>

<p>Do you know <person_mentioned>Mr. McQueen of <location_mentioned>New Orleans</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>— he writes well I
am told and intends removing here exercise great judgement in
enlisting prudent and safe men as writers on this subject, <person_mentioned>S. 
Williams</person_mentioned> has a <hi rend="italic"><person_mentioned>son</person_mentioned></hi></p>


</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
