
<TEI.2 id="APB1961">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>06-14-1830</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1922: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1928), 3 vols., Vol 2, pp. 413-417</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Stephen F Austin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Thomas F Leaming</document_recipient>
<document_title>Stephen F Austin to Thomas F Leaming, 06-14-1830</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>San Felipe de Austin, Texas</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Philadelphia, Pennsylvania</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Austin to Thomas F. Learning, June 14, 1830. Reasons for undertaking to
colonize Texas, and difficulties encountered. Worked noiselessly to avoid
exciting apprehensions of Government. The present law of April 6, 1830,
does not apply to his colony. Friends inserted provisions exempting from its
operation colonies already established. Desires to remain subject to Mexico,
but fears that time may force separation from Mexico, in which case he
would favor independence if Texas had sufficient population. Suggests Swiss
and German colonists. His map designed as a bait to promote colonization
by spreading information about Texas.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes>Two articles written by Thomas H. Benton, published originally in the St. Louis
Beacon, Aug. 1, 8, 1829.
The Daily National Intelligencer, Sept. 26, Oct. 5, 10, 20, 1829, publishes a symposium
of newspaper comment, quoting many papers for and against the acquisition of Texas.
 I have been unable to verify this statement by reference to the proceedings of Congress.</barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 413-417</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>08-21-2010</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>


<text id="APB1961T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Austin to Thomas F. Learning, June 14, 1830. Reasons for undertaking to
colonize Texas, and difficulties encountered. Worked noiselessly to avoid
exciting apprehensions of Government. The present law of April 6, 1830,
does not apply to his colony. Friends inserted provisions exempting from its
operation colonies already established. Desires to remain subject to Mexico,
but fears that time may force separation from Mexico, in which case he
would favor independence if Texas had sufficient population. Suggests Swiss
and German colonists. His map designed as a bait to promote colonization
by spreading information about Texas.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">


<p><location_mentioned>San Felipe de Austin</location_mentioned> <date_mentioned n="06-14-1830">14 June 1830</date_mentioned></p>
<p><person_mentioned>T. F. Leaming Esqr</person_mentioned>.</p>

<p>My dear Sir, It has been a long time since I had the pleasure of
hearing from you by letter. My <person_mentioned>brother in law James F. Perry</person_mentioned>
paid me a visit in<date_mentioned n="04-xx-1830"> april last </date_mentioned>and will remove his <person_mentioned>family </person_mentioned>to this <location_mentioned>colony</location_mentioned>
in the <date_mentioned n="Fall - 1830">fall </date_mentioned>he expects to visit <location_mentioned>Phia </location_mentioned>this <date_mentioned n="Summer - 1830">summer </date_mentioned>and will call on
you— I have as yet heard nothing of the <location_mentioned>Map of Texas</location_mentioned>, since I
forwarded it the surveys have been considerably extended and I
could now form a much more accurate map, tho the one I sent gives
a very correct general idea of the <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>and is fully as correct as
the first maps of new <location_mentioned>countries </location_mentioned>usually are and I think more so, it
cost me great labor and trouble and considerable expence— My
object was not individual profit, it was to bring this <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>
forward into public view, for it has been literaly buried in obscurity up
to the last year—</p>

<p>Respect for the opinions and last will of my <person_mentioned>father </person_mentioned>caused me to
explore <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>in <date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1821">1821</date_mentioned>. I was both delighted and astonished to find
it to be the <location_mentioned>most favord region I had ever seen</location_mentioned>.   Its fertility and<barker_pb n="414"/>
natural resources, so far exceeding any thing I had imagined, 
determined me to devote my life to the great object of redeeming it from
the <location_mentioned>wilderness</location_mentioned>.</p>

<p>It was a heavy undertaking for a young, inexperianced <hi rend="italic">and very
poor man</hi>—My first step was to study the character of the <person_mentioned>Mexicans</person_mentioned>
and ascertain their ideas and views as to <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>— I found they
knew nothing about it, and were profoundly ignorant of its real
value, and also that they considered it next to impracticable to form
a <location_mentioned>settlement </location_mentioned>in its <location_mentioned>wilderness </location_mentioned>without the aid of a very strong 
<person_mentioned>Military force</person_mentioned> for <location_mentioned>garrisons </location_mentioned>to keep the <person_mentioned>indians </person_mentioned>in check. I also 
discover that strong prejudices existed against the <person_mentioned>North Americans
</person_mentioned>owing to the conduct of some who were engaged in the <person_mentioned>revolutionary
expeditions</person_mentioned> that had entered <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>at various times since <date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1811">1811</date_mentioned>, I
saw that all the efforts to get foothold here by means of such 
<person_mentioned>expeditions </person_mentioned>had failed and ended in defeat and ruin, and I believed they
always would fail, These observations convinced me that the only
means of redeeming this <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>from the <location_mentioned>wilderness </location_mentioned>was by 
peaceful <hi rend="italic">silent</hi>, noisless, perseverence and industry, and that the axe, the
plough and the hoe would do more than the rifle or the sword.
under these impressions I began and have pursued the main object
with a degree of patience and perseverence which nothing but its
vast importance to the<location_mentioned> civilized world </location_mentioned>could ever have given me
fortitude to continue through so many years of hardships and amidst
so many discouraging obstacles— The worst is now over and the
few clouds which seem to hang over us are mere shadows when 
compared with those which have passed. I have laid a sufficient 
foundation for others to build on, and a prudent course will make this
<location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>one of the finest in the <location_mentioned>world</location_mentioned>.</p>

<p>The measures lately adopted by the <person_mentioned>Mexican Govt</person_mentioned>, prohibiting
the emigration of <person_mentioned>North Americans</person_mentioned>, affords a striking proof of the
nesesity of the <hi rend="italic">silent </hi>course which I have pursued in bringing 
forward this <location_mentioned>settlement</location_mentioned>. I have never sent any notices or publications
respecting it to be printed in the <location_mentioned>news papers</location_mentioned> untill lately, when I
first began in <date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1821">1821 </date_mentioned>merely put in a notice in the <location_mentioned>Orleans papers </location_mentioned>that
I was authorised to settle <person_mentioned>300 families</person_mentioned> and barely said enough to
draw a little attention, last year I found that the Govt, were 
begining to become suspicious that this <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>was of more value than
they had supposed it was, <person_mentioned>Genl Teran</person_mentioned> passed through here, and
saw it. I found that something must be done to draw emigration
and I determined to have the <location_mentioned>Map </location_mentioned>published as the Most effectual
means of operating on an intelligent <person_mentioned>people</person_mentioned>, and the least dangerous
with the <person_mentioned>Mexicans</person_mentioned>, for not many of them know any thing about <location_mentioned>maps</location_mentioned>
—unfortunately about this time "<hi rend="italic">Americanus</hi>" and other <location_mentioned>publica-<barker_pb n="415"/>
tions </location_mentioned>appeared and <hi rend="italic"><location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned></hi>became A general topic of discussion in
the<location_mentioned> U. S. papers </location_mentioned>This roused the attention of the <person_mentioned>Mexican </person_mentioned>Govt,
and excited their jealoucy that the <location_mentioned>U. S.</location_mentioned> were determined to take
this <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>by force right or wrong, and this mistaken notion has
produced the law of <date_mentioned n="04-06-1830">6 of April</date_mentioned> last prohibiting emigration from the
<location_mentioned>U. S. </location_mentioned>and suspending all the contracts of colonization, except in the
<location_mentioned>colonies that are " <hi rend="italic">established </hi>"</location_mentioned>— this clause was crowded in by
my <person_mentioned>friends </person_mentioned>to cover this <location_mentioned>colony </location_mentioned>(for mine is the only one that is
established) and under it I shall be able with good management to
keep open the door for some time longer, and perhaps untill a new
order of things takes place,</p>

<p>I have had two difficult tasks to perform here, one to manage
the Govt, and the other to manage the <person_mentioned>settlers</person_mentioned>, of these, the latter
was by far the most difficult— I do say that the<person_mentioned> North Americans
</person_mentioned>are the most obstinate and difficult <person_mentioned>people </person_mentioned>to manage that live on
earth, tho I have had many "<person_mentioned> backwoods men</person_mentioned> " and " <person_mentioned>rough fellows</person_mentioned> "
to do with. <person_mentioned>Emigrants from europe</person_mentioned> are not prohibited, and I
sometimes think that <person_mentioned>Swiss </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>Germans </person_mentioned>will promote the 
prosperity of this <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>much more than <person_mentioned>North Americans</person_mentioned>— They
will introduce the culture of the vine, olive etc. they are industrious
and moral, they have not in general, that horrible <hi rend="italic">Mania </hi>for 
speculation which is so prominent a trait in the <person_mentioned>english </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>North
American</person_mentioned> character, <hi rend="italic">and above all they will oppose slavery</hi>— The
idea of seeing such a <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>as this overrun by a <person_mentioned>slave </person_mentioned>population
almost makes me weep— It is in vain to tell a <person_mentioned>North American</person_mentioned> that
the <person_mentioned>white population</person_mentioned> will be destroyed some fifty or eighty years
hence by the <person_mentioned>negros</person_mentioned>, and that his <person_mentioned>daughters </person_mentioned>will be violated and
<person_mentioned>Butch[er]ed</person_mentioned> by them— "it is too far off to think of—" "they can
do as I have, take care of themselves "—" something will turn up
to keep off the evil" etc, etc, such are the silly answers of the <person_mentioned>slave
holder</person_mentioned>—to say any thing to them as to the justice of slavery, or its
demoralizing effects on society, is only to draw down ridicule upon
the person who attempts it— In the begining of this <location_mentioned>settlement</location_mentioned>
I was compelled to hold out the idea that slavery would be tolerated,
and I succeeded in getting it <hi rend="italic">tolerated </hi>for a time by the Govt. I
did this to get a start for otherwise it would have been next to 
impossible to have started at all, for I had to draw on <location_mentioned>Louisiana </location_mentioned>and
<location_mentioned>Mississippi</location_mentioned>, <location_mentioned>Slave States</location_mentioned>, for the first <person_mentioned>emigrants</person_mentioned>— Slavery is now
most positively prohibited by our Constitution and by a number of
laws, and I do hope it may always be so.</p>

<p>I have passed a truly slavish life here for nine years, my 
constitution is much broken, my health bad, and my days are probably
drawing towards a close, but I can claim some credit for what has
been done towards laying a foundation for the formation of a rich
and I hope a happy <location_mentioned>community</location_mentioned>— <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>no longer belongs to the
<location_mentioned>wilderness</location_mentioned>—whether it will ultimately remain attached to <location_mentioned>Mexico</location_mentioned>,
or unite with <location_mentioned>the north</location_mentioned>, or form an <location_mentioned>independent nation</location_mentioned>, is all mere
matter of conjecture, If slavery is excluded, I think the latter the
most probable—but if it is admitted, <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>will become what all
<location_mentioned>slave countries </location_mentioned>are and of necessity must be destitute of physical force
and dependent on some other power even for the preservation of its
internal tranquility—in short it must have a <hi rend="italic">prop </hi>to lean upon, for
no <location_mentioned>slave country </location_mentioned>can stand alone—</p>

<p>I think that much good might be done by a series of publications in
the<location_mentioned> National Gazette</location_mentioned> on the emigration of <person_mentioned>Swiss </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>Germans </person_mentioned>to
<person_mentioned>Texas</person_mentioned>—also against the admission of Slavery here—against annexing
it to the <location_mentioned>U. S.</location_mentioned>—in favor of its adhering to <location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned>as long as the
federal constitution stands <hi rend="italic">and no longer</hi>, but then to set up for
itself, under the protection of the <location_mentioned>U. S</location_mentioned>.— you will of course 
perceive that this letter is not <hi rend="italic">for the public eye</hi>— I have wished to
give <hi rend="italic">you </hi>as a relative, some idea of my labors and views here, they
are pure— I will die sooner than violate my duty to this 
government, and if it would let me work I would make <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>the best state
that belongs to this <location_mentioned>nation</location_mentioned>, but my dear sir the truth is that the
<person_mentioned>Mexicans </person_mentioned>cannot sustain a <location_mentioned>republic</location_mentioned>-— The present form must fall
and what is then to become of Texas ? we are too weak to set up for
ourselves, unless under the protection of our <person_mentioned>powerfall neighbor</person_mentioned>—
and the protection which the strong affords to the <hi rend="italic">weak </hi>is much to be
feared-— If we had population, our course would be a very plain
one, but we have it not— <location_mentioned>Territory </location_mentioned>we have to form a snug 
<person_mentioned>republic</person_mentioned>,— I am in hopes the federal system may stand a few years
longer and that by that time we shall get in some thousands of <person_mentioned>swiss</person_mentioned>,
<person_mentioned>Germans</person_mentioned>, etc, and <person_mentioned>North Americans</person_mentioned>—the emigration is still 
uninterupted to my <location_mentioned>colony </location_mentioned>and there will be a great accession of strength<date_mentioned n="Fall - 1830">
this fall—</date_mentioned></p>

<p><person_mentioned>S. Rhoads Fisher</person_mentioned> of your city has paid us a visit and can give
you much information as to this <location_mentioned>country</location_mentioned>—-</p>

<p>I sent you a <location_mentioned>pamphlet </location_mentioned>sometime since containing translations of
the laws of colonization etc—if you have not recd it you can get
one from <person_mentioned>John P Austin</person_mentioned>, <person_mentioned>(Austin and Tayleur)</person_mentioned> <location_mentioned>New York</location_mentioned>, or from
<person_mentioned>Arch. Austin</person_mentioned> same place—you will see by the law that what I stated
to you relative to the impositions attempted by <person_mentioned>D. A. Smith,</person_mentioned> <person_mentioned>Stephen
Wilson </person_mentioned>etc was correct—the publications of those men had its effect
in producing the law of<date_mentioned n="04-06-1830"> 6 of April</date_mentioned> last. Had all other <person_mentioned>impresarios</person_mentioned>
gone to work in good faith as I did, <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>would now have had a
very heavy population, but I am the only one out of near 80 who
engaged to settle <location_mentioned>colonies </location_mentioned>who has done any thing, <hi rend="italic">except harm</hi><barker_pb n="417"/>
they have not brought one <person_mentioned>family </person_mentioned>to the <location_mentioned>country</location_mentioned>, nor advanced one
step.</p>

<p>I have but little knowledge of my <person_mentioned>mothers family</person_mentioned> I idolised
my beloved <person_mentioned>Mother </person_mentioned>and altho I know none of her <person_mentioned><location_mentioned>Philadelphia </location_mentioned>family</person_mentioned>
connections personally I have towards them all the affection of a
relative— Will you do me the kindness to send me by<person_mentioned> Mr. Perry</person_mentioned>
a short historical sketch of my <person_mentioned>mothers </person_mentioned>parentage and <person_mentioned>family </person_mentioned>and
of my <person_mentioned>maternal relations</person_mentioned> who are alive, where they live, their names
etc I have a great desire to visit the <location_mentioned>U. S. </location_mentioned>and I have no doubt it
would restore my health, but I am tied down here now, by many
heavy and perplexing duties, and to tell the truth I am too poor as
to <hi rend="italic">money</hi>) to bear the expence— I have land but it will not sell
yet—notwithstanding, I do not dispair of seeing <location_mentioned>Philadelphia </location_mentioned>before
I die—.</p>

<p>I think I was called after <person_mentioned>Benjamin Fuller </person_mentioned>who married a <person_mentioned>sister
of my mothers</person_mentioned>,— who inherited his fortune? he promised my
<person_mentioned>mother </person_mentioned>to leave it to me— If I had it now I would make <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>
much the better by it—</p>

<p>I hope <person_mentioned>Tanner </person_mentioned>may make a fortune out of the <location_mentioned>map</location_mentioned>, if so, he
must send me one [of] his best bound general Atlasses—</p>

<p>you may have some curiosity to know my age,   I was born in
<location_mentioned>Wythe county Virginia </location_mentioned><date_mentioned n="11-03-1793">November 3. 1793</date_mentioned>—</p>
<p>very cordially your frend and relation</p>

<p><person_mentioned>S. F. Austin </person_mentioned>   [Rubric]</p>

<p>I regret to say that <person_mentioned>James Austina son of Aunt Margarette</person_mentioned>  died
of consumption here a short time after his arrival from <location_mentioned>Missouri</location_mentioned>,
he was nearly gone when he reached here—</p>

<p><person_mentioned>A</person_mentioned></p>

<p>[Addressed:] <person_mentioned>Thomas F. Learning Esqr.</person_mentioned> <location_mentioned>Philadelphia Pen</location_mentioned>.</p>



</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
