
<TEI.2 id="APB1361">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>04-12-1827</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1628-1629</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>J. Hunter</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Stephen F. Austin</document_recipient>
<document_title>J. Hunter to Stephen F. Austin, 04-12-1827</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Unknown</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>J. Hunter to Austin, April 12, 1827.    Judicial procedure.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes></barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1628-1629</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>07-21-2010</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>


<text id="APB1361T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>J. Hunter to Austin, April 12, 1827.    Judicial procedure.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><date_mentioned n="04-12-1827">April 12th 1827</date_mentioned></p>
<p>The <person_mentioned>Honorable S. F. Austin</person_mentioned></p>

<p><person_mentioned>Judge of <location_mentioned>Austins Colony</</location_mentioned>person_mentioned>,</p>
<p>your <person_mentioned>petitioner </person_mentioned>humbly prays redress for the abuse and to be
released from the persecution and oppression of <person_mentioned>Wm Scott</person_mentioned> who
declares that I shall not be out of the law while I remain in that
<location_mentioned>place </location_mentioned>and that he will have me halled up to <location_mentioned>court </location_mentioned>at least once a
month if it should be for no other purpose than to hackle me by
which he means to ridicule and abuse me as he has been in the habit
of doing at each court day for the last six months in such a manner
that it is impossible to bear it, The <person_mentioned>Alcalde Jackson</person_mentioned>'s letter of last
week will shew you something of the manner in which be abuses not
only me but the <person_mentioned>court </person_mentioned>itself. It seems also useless to obtain a
decission against him as he disregards you or your orders—so
declared—And so in the case of the <person_mentioned>widow </person_mentioned>he has twisted and
quibled for more than a year and raised a great bill of cost rejec[ted]
and picked the <person_mentioned>jury </person_mentioned>untill he got one Exactly to please him who
allowed me only thirty nine dollars and some cents which at the
request of the <person_mentioned>Alcalde </person_mentioned>I agreed to take in property and not distress
the <person_mentioned>widow</person_mentioned>. And now notwithstanding an express order from your
honor that no appeal should be taken in those cases   Behold them<barker_pb n="1629"/>
before you claiming an appeal without Even giving bail or taking
any stay whatever is this lawfull—</p>

<p>He is so well up to persecuting me at the cost of <person_mentioned>others</person_mentioned>—that I beg
leave to cite another case where he taking the advantage of one of
your letters to the <person_mentioned>Alcalde </person_mentioned>(although he wont be ruled by them 
himself) he wishes to make me prove Every Item of all my accounts by
other testimony than my own, he has induced a <person_mentioned>man </person_mentioned>to s[wear to an]
article that was paid to me two years [ago] he is the <person_mentioned>agent </person_mentioned>to 
prosecute. Now I [can prove?] by the <person_mentioned>Alcalde Jackson</person_mentioned> and Eight others
<person_mentioned>citizens </person_mentioned>of our <location_mentioned>place </location_mentioned>that said man has [on]ly declared that I saved
his life and he gave me that article in payment This I mention not
that I am afraid of loosing it but to shew you what steps he takes
[to] persecute me at the cost of <person_mentioned>Others </person_mentioned>and also that I am never to
get of the law . . . said I humbly pray your honor therefore to
instruct me in what manner I am to be redressed and how I am to
get out of the law. The shameful story of the buckle business is not
yet settled and when Ever it is decided he will appeal or take some
other step of delay</p>

<p><person_mentioned>J. Hunter, </person_mentioned>   [Rubric]</p>

<p>The <person_mentioned>Hon. S. F. Austin</person_mentioned></p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
