
<TEI.2 id="APB4613">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>01-13-1834</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1922: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1928), 3 vols., Vol 2, pp. 1024-1026</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Stephen F Austin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Sameul M Williams</document_recipient>
<document_title>Stephen F Austin to Sameul M Williams, 01-13-1834</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Monterrey, Nuevo Leon</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Austin to Samuel M. Williams, Monterey, January 12, 1834. Announcing arrest for urging organization of State government in Texas. Has opposed annexation of Texas to the United States, but has told Mexican statesmen that they should either reform local abuses in Texas or sell the Province to the united States. Warns against excitement over his arrest. His attitude toward the convention of 1833. Attitude toward territorial government for Texas toward statehood.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes></barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1024-1026</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>12-02-2010</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp>
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>


<text id="APB4613T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Austin to Samuel M. Williams, Monterey, January 12, 1834. Announcing arrest for urging organization of State government in Texas. Has opposed annexation of Texas to the United States, but has told Mexican statesmen that they should either reform local abuses in Texas or sell the Province to the united States. Warns against excitement over his arrest. His attitude toward the convention of 1833. Attitude toward territorial government for Texas toward statehood.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p>[From Williams Papers, Rosenberg Library, Galve&ton, Tex,]</p>

<p><location_mentioned>Monterrey </location_mentioned><date_mentioned n="01-12-1834">Jany 12 1834</date_mentioned></p>
<p><person_mentioned>S. M. Williams</person_mentioned>.</p>

<p>On my arrival at <location_mentioned>Saltillo </location_mentioned>on the <date_mentioned n="01-03-1834">3 inst</date_mentioned>. I was arrested by the <person_mentioned>Comt
General</person_mentioned> on an order from the<person_mentioned> Minister of War</person_mentioned> directing that I
should be sent back to <location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned>to answer an accusation, made, as
I understand, by the <person_mentioned>Govt, of the State of Coahuila and Texas.</person_mentioned> I
leave in a few days for <location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned>under an <person_mentioned>escort </person_mentioned>as a <person_mentioned>prisoner</person_mentioned>. My
treatment is very good and I have no cause to complain on that
score. I feel under obligations to the <person_mentioned>Com Genl Don Pedro Lemus</person_mentioned>,
and to the <person_mentioned>Govr of this State Manual Maria Llanos</person_mentioned>, also to <person_mentioned>Col 
Ugartechea</person_mentioned> who is the <person_mentioned>Commandant </person_mentioned>at this place. They have all treated
me in the kindest manner. <person_mentioned>Lemus </person_mentioned>expects to visit <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, and if he
should, and I have one <person_mentioned>friend </person_mentioned>left in that <location_mentioned>country</location_mentioned>, or if there be
one out of the thousands whose fortunes I have labored to make,
who wishes to do me a favor in return, I request that friend, or
that <hi rend="italic">one</hi>, to be the friend of <person_mentioned>Genl Lemus</person_mentioned> for my sake.</p>

<p>I presume that I am arrested for writing the <hi rend="italic">oficio </hi>to the <person_mentioned>Aytos.
of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> dated <date_mentioned n="10-02-1833">2d of October last</date_mentioned>. I made some <person_mentioned>enemies </person_mentioned>in <location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned>for
opposing a <location_mentioned>territory</location_mentioned>, but I do not believe they have had any hand
in my arrest. It has been intimated to me that some <person_mentioned>enemy</person_mentioned>, I know
not who, had accused me of designs to unite <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>with the <location_mentioned>U. S.
of the north</location_mentioned>. Such an accusation is false and I disregard it. I
have said openly to all<person_mentioned> persons in <location_mentioned>Mexico</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>, and to the <person_mentioned>Govt</person_mentioned>, itself,
that I was of opinion the <person_mentioned>local Govt, of <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned></person_mentioned>ought to be organized,
or that <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>ought to be transfered to the <location_mentioned>U. S. </location_mentioned>for situated
as it now is, it is liable to revolutions and anarchy which may do
much harm to the <location_mentioned>frontiers of both nations</location_mentioned>, and finally loose <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>
and ruin the poor and honest <person_mentioned>settlers </person_mentioned>who have labored in good faith
to redeem it from the <location_mentioned>wilderness </location_mentioned>and make it a <location_mentioned>valuable portion
of the Mexican republic</location_mentioned>. The real fact is that at this time <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>
does not belong to <location_mentioned>Mexico</location_mentioned>, nor to <location_mentioned>Coahuila</location_mentioned>, nor to the <person_mentioned>settlers </person_mentioned>who
have redeemed it—it belongs to them in justice and in right that
is to the<location_mentioned> Mexican republic</location_mentioned> and to the <person_mentioned>inhabitants of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>—but in
point of fact, it belongs to <person_mentioned>demagogues</person_mentioned>, <person_mentioned>pettyfoggers</person_mentioned>, <person_mentioned>visionary
speculators</person_mentioned> and <person_mentioned>scheamers</person_mentioned>, to <person_mentioned>indians </person_mentioned>to anarchy and discord and
confusion—to comprehend all in one word—it is without 
<person_mentioned>Government</person_mentioned>.</p>

<p>I hope there will be no excitement about my arrest. All I can
be accused of is, that I have labored arduously, faithfully, and 
perhaps at particular moments, pationately, and with more impatience
and irritation than I ought to have shewn, to have <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>made
<location_mentioned>State of the Mexican Confederation</location_mentioned> separate from <location_mentioned>Coahuila</location_mentioned>.   This<barker_pb n="1025"/>
is all, and this is no crime. But should it be considered otherwise,
it will not take me by surprise. Ever since I returned from <location_mentioned>Bexar</location_mentioned>
a year ago <date_mentioned n="12-xx-1833">last Decr</date_mentioned> and found the Convention called in my absence,
I have consider'd myself as suspended over the altar of sacrifice.
That measure placed me in an awkward position. It compromised
me in the highest degree with the <person_mentioned>people and authorities of <location_mentioned>Bexar</location_mentioned>,</person_mentioned>
on the one hand, and with my <person_mentioned>friends at <location_mentioned>San Felipe</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> on the other,
for altho I had agreed to the calling of a convention before I went
to <person_mentioned>Bexar</person_mentioned>, I did not expect it would have been done in my absence.
I went there to consult with the <person_mentioned>authorities </person_mentioned>of that place. I 
considered that very great respect and deference was justly due to them
as <person_mentioned>native Mexicans</person_mentioned>, as the <location_mentioned>capital of Texas</location_mentioned>, and as the <location_mentioned>oldest and
most populous town in the country</location_mentioned>. And I knew the importance
of getting them to take the lead in all the politics of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, besides
this, I was personally attached to those people as a sincere friend
and wished to act in concert with them. I wished the convention
to meet in <location_mentioned>Bexar</location_mentioned>, but at that time it was death to any man's 
popularity to speak in favor of the <person_mentioned>Mexicans</person_mentioned>. These things are all
pased and had best be forgotten—probably I have no just cause to
blame any one but myself for in some things that occured then I
was a mere <person_mentioned><hi rend="italic">passive actor</hi></person_mentioned>, when I ought to have been a firm and
unbending <person_mentioned><hi rend="italic">director</hi></person_mentioned>. My object was to smother the party spirit and
violent and ruinous divisions which I saw brewing in the <location_mentioned>colony</location_mentioned>;
and as my friendship for the <person_mentioned>Mexicans </person_mentioned>and opposition to violent
measures was to have been used by my <person_mentioned>enemies</person_mentioned>, (who were in fact
also the only real <person_mentioned>enemies </person_mentioned>to <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>) as the kindling materials, the
oil and brimstone to set the flame of discord and confusion ablazing,
I thought it best to deprive them of the kindling matter by a passive
course. I mistook the means, and committed a great error, but I
have learned this lesson in politics, that there is no medium with
envy and party spirit, between victory and defeat.</p>

<p>I was always in favor of the State question, but I feared, especially
after my trip to <location_mentioned>Bexar</location_mentioned>, that it would not succeed unless the <person_mentioned>people</person_mentioned>
of that place took the lead, and it was arranged for them to do so.
The representation and remonstrance of <date_mentioned n="12-19-1833">19 Decr</date_mentioned>, was the first step,
and would have led to all the others, and <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>by this time would
have been a State or nearly so, and the discord that I fear has
arisen between <location_mentioned>Bexar </location_mentioned>and a part of <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>would have been avoided.
All was defeated and deranged and <location_mentioned>Bexar </location_mentioned>was offended and turned
against a measure that it was in favor of. So much for party spirit
and envy, or rather for opposition to <person_mentioned>Austin </person_mentioned>because he was <person_mentioned>Austin</person_mentioned>—
he, must be suspected and watched—<hi rend="italic">he</hi>, who has labored so many
years regardless of personal fatigue or responsability to build up<barker_pb n="1026"/>
<location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, settle it and make the fortunes of its <person_mentioned>inhabitants</person_mentioned>—bien, muy
bien. Such is human nature and such it will always be-—I am tired
of it and for the future wish to have as little to do with mankind or
their affairs as practicable.</p>

<p>If I thought my advice would have any weight, I would say to
<location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, you must all harmonise with <location_mentioned>Bexar </location_mentioned>and <location_mentioned>Goliad</location_mentioned>, that is with
the <person_mentioned>Mexican population</person_mentioned>. If they petition for a <location_mentioned>State </location_mentioned>or a <location_mentioned>Territory</location_mentioned>
and are seconded by the rest of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, the petition will be granted,
and I am equally certain that no petition of this kind will succeed
that is opposed by that population.</p>

<p>If a <person_mentioned>victim </person_mentioned>is required by the <person_mentioned>Govt </person_mentioned>I, of course will be the man,
for those who have really contributed to precipitate these matters
occupy too small a space to be noticed by the Government.</p>

<p>I wish you to send me a certified copy of the representation made
last year by the <person_mentioned>Ayto. of <location_mentioned>Goliad</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>. I have that of <location_mentioned>Bexar </location_mentioned>and need
the other to shew that the <person_mentioned>Mexican population</person_mentioned> complained even
more than the other. Send it under cover to<person_mentioned> W. S. Parrott</person_mentioned> and
direct all letters for me to him.</p>

<p>The <person_mentioned>Aytos. of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>, if they wish to do me justice might state to
the <person_mentioned>Genl Govt</person_mentioned> what they know of my character and conduct. I do
not ask it, if it is done I wish it of their own accord. Such a thing
from <location_mentioned>Bexar </location_mentioned>would have weight. I must request you to provide me
with the means of living in <location_mentioned>Mexico</location_mentioned>. I used one of the bills of credit
that is one thousand dollars—can I use the other? I can sell bills
on <location_mentioned>Orleans </location_mentioned>in <location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned>for 10 pr. ct. I sold to <person_mentioned>Parrott</person_mentioned>—I recd, 
nothing for any of the claims on <location_mentioned>Matamoros </location_mentioned>but am promised something.
I presume I shall be five or six months and perhaps a year in <location_mentioned>Mexico</location_mentioned>,
or I may be sent back to the <person_mentioned>State Govt</person_mentioned> who have demanded me of
the <person_mentioned>Comt Genl</person_mentioned> for what purpose, whether friendly or hostile, I
know not. No man has benefited <location_mentioned>this part of the nation</location_mentioned> more than
I have—in a few years more the <location_mentioned>frontier of Coahuila </location_mentioned>will be safe
from the <person_mentioned>indians</person_mentioned></p>

<p>Remember me to my <person_mentioned>friends </person_mentioned>if I have any and to your <person_mentioned>wife </person_mentioned>and
the <person_mentioned>old settlers</person_mentioned></p>

<p><person_mentioned>S. F. Austin</person_mentioned></p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
