
<TEI.2 id="APB2095">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>08-29-1825</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1922: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1928), 3 vols., Vol 2, pp. 1185-1187</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Andrew Erwin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Stephen F Austin</document_recipient>
<document_title>Andrew Erwin to Stephen F Austin, 08-29-1825</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Nashville, Tennessee</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Nachitoches, Louisiana</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Andrew Erwin to Austin, August 29, 1825. Leftwich and the affairs of the Nashville Company, stock of which is selling at about 100 per cent advance. Concerning the business misfortunes of A. Erwin, Groce & Co.; and the character of Groce.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes>Compare J. Eiwin to Austin, September 30, 1825.</barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1185-1187</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>12-26-2010</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>


<text id="APB2095T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Andrew Erwin to Austin, August 29, 1825. Leftwich and the affairs of the Nashville Company, stock of which is selling at about 100 per cent advance. Concerning the business misfortunes of A. Erwin, Groce & Co.; and the character of Groce.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><location_mentioned>Nashville </location_mentioned><date_mentioned n="08-29-1825">August 29. 1825</date_mentioned></p>
<p>Dear Sir</p>

<p>Strange as it may appear it is true that I have never until <date_mentioned n="08-27-1825">two
days ago</date_mentioned> seen your lengthy epistle to me on various subjects of <date_mentioned n="02-18-1825">18th
February last</date_mentioned> this is owing I presume to my absence from this State
in <location_mentioned>Georgia </location_mentioned>and <location_mentioned>South Carolina</location_mentioned> from <date_mentioned n="11-xx-1824">November </date_mentioned>until<date_mentioned n="04-xx-1825"> April last</date_mentioned> and
my attention to my election for <person_mentioned>congress </person_mentioned>from that time until the <date_mentioned n="08-05-1825">5th
inst.</date_mentioned> in which I was again 2d on the list having 3 others to console
with me in disappointment since when I visited this place for the first
time since <date_mentioned n="11-xx-1824">November last</date_mentioned> and here find your letter previous to seeing
of which however I have seen our old fellow sufferer <person_mentioned>Genl Leftwich</person_mentioned>
and his <location_mentioned>grant </location_mentioned>and several meetings of the <person_mentioned>Texas association</person_mentioned>.    They<barker_pb n="1186"/>
had some difficulty in arranging matters with the <person_mentioned>Genl </person_mentioned>about his 
compensation expenses etc. etc. which however now appears settled by
allowing him his expenses and about $200 pr month for services and
the stock is selling at about 100 pr ct advance It is now believed that
<person_mentioned>Doctr Robertson</person_mentioned> one of our most worthy citizens will go out as <person_mentioned>agent</person_mentioned>
and take with him a large connexion and many respectable <person_mentioned>friends</person_mentioned>
you will find him a great acquisition to the <location_mentioned>settlement </location_mentioned>of your new
<location_mentioned>Country</location_mentioned>, he possesses sterling integrity good sound sense mildness
of manners and conduct and firmness suited to the undertaking and
with all a good stock of practical experience in the ups and downs of
life—I was a <person_mentioned>stockholder </person_mentioned>but poverty prevents my holding on to it—
The old business of <person_mentioned>A. Erwin Groce & Co</person_mentioned>. and <person_mentioned>Erwin & C°</person_mentioned> of which
you have heard so much and so varient from the true state of the case
keeps me in poverty and at present on the limits prescribed for 
unfortunate <person_mentioned>debtors </person_mentioned>from which I shall be released in about twenty
days as I have twice within the last 7 years given up my last knife
and fork to <person_mentioned>creditors </person_mentioned>I did expect to have escaped this ordeal but
so it is owing to <person_mentioned>party </person_mentioned>feelings growing partly out of my defending
myself and <person_mentioned>neighbours </person_mentioned>against <person_mentioned>Genl Jackson & Co</person_mentioned>. with eventual 
success excites feelings of hostility <location_mentioned>from that quarter</location_mentioned> and the 
circumstance of <person_mentioned>Mr. Groce</person_mentioned>s leaving the <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>with property causes some
to suppose I had knowledge of it which he knows is not the fact and
the circumstances of my living <location_mentioned>on a good tract of land</location_mentioned> and having
the use of <person_mentioned>14 negroes </person_mentioned>which are mortgaged to the <person_mentioned>government </person_mentioned>for
three times what they would sell for furnishes a pretext for some
<person_mentioned>illdisposed persons </person_mentioned>to say that I hold property and withold it from
my <person_mentioned>creditors </person_mentioned>Even your neighbour <person_mentioned>Mr. Groce</person_mentioned> who knows these facts
as well as I do sometimes I am told indulges himself in saying we
are all rich and owe him and refuse to settle with him etc etc In your
letter you ask how this matter is above you have the answer all of
which I could prove by <person_mentioned>Mr. Groce</person_mentioned> himself <location_mentioned>in a court of the United
States</location_mentioned> and by Record Testimony in the city of <location_mentioned>Augusta </location_mentioned>were he
here—no man wishes <person_mentioned>Mr. Groce</person_mentioned> to prosper more than I do It is true
he joined me in a <location_mentioned>merchantile business</location_mentioned> in which business I had been
prosperous for more than 20 years—Both our objects were to make
money in which I lost upwards of<hi rend="italic"> $100,000 </hi>of my own capital and
<person_mentioned>Mr. Groce</person_mentioned> near $50,000 leaving us jointly bound for large sums which
both he and myself exerted ourselves to settle and at our last meeting
in <location_mentioned>Augusta </location_mentioned><person_mentioned>James Erwin</person_mentioned> <person_mentioned>Mr. Groce</person_mentioned> and myself each executed our
notes to <person_mentioned>Col. McKinne</person_mentioned> for about ten thousand dollars which each
were to pay and was to exonerate <person_mentioned>Mr. Groce</person_mentioned> from all other liabilities
in <location_mentioned>Georgia </location_mentioned>and he exonerated us from him for all claims by him on
either of us. <person_mentioned>Mr. Groce</person_mentioned> left the <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>without paying his note it
was paid by us and I presume is the claim about which <person_mentioned>James Erwin</person_mentioned><barker_pb n="1187"/>
has been writing <person_mentioned>Judge Thomas</person_mentioned> to which you allude in your letter
in this latter part, however, I may be mistaken as I seldom see
<person_mentioned>James Erwin</person_mentioned> and when I do we speak and feel somewhat different
about <person_mentioned>Mr. Groce</person_mentioned>. I make more allowances for his misfortunes and
his disposition to turn molehills into mountains that he does I have
no knowledge of any other unsettled business between him and us
which would require references as to what was said in <person_mentioned>Mr. Groce</person_mentioned>'s
letter to which you allude and which I had answered which answer
<person_mentioned>Mr. Groce</person_mentioned> had not shown you—I viewed it all as intended for your
eye and others and his own gratification whilst talking about it. as
to either myself or <person_mentioned>family </person_mentioned>having anything to fear from any thing
<person_mentioned>Mr. Groce</person_mentioned> could publish either in this <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>or that it is all a 
mistake—we have no fears of the kind As to your expressions of 
personal regard I assure you it is reciprocal—I view you as 
instrumental in doing much good for yourself and friends and wish you long
life and continued prosperity.</p>
<p>Yours very respectfully,</p>

<p><person_mentioned>Andrew Erwin</person_mentioned>.</p>

<p>P. S. as I write a bad hand and dislike Copying I send you the
above writen by my <person_mentioned>son George Washington Erwin</person_mentioned>, from a Copy
written by myself Since writing the above <person_mentioned>Doctor Felix Robertson</person_mentioned>
has been appointed <person_mentioned>sole agent</person_mentioned> for the <person_mentioned>Texas association</person_mentioned> and will
depart thence in <date_mentioned n="10-xx-1825">October </date_mentioned>or <date_mentioned n="11-xx-1825">November </date_mentioned>next</p>

<p>PS. In addition to all I have said I wish to be remembered 
affectionately to<person_mentioned> Mr Groce</person_mentioned> and all his <person_mentioned>Children </person_mentioned>that are with him, my
regard for all of them as old <person_mentioned>acquaintances </person_mentioned>is undiminished and
had <person_mentioned>Mr Groce</person_mentioned> been as cautious in speaking of my means and 
Intentions to relieve him as was his duty and his Interest I do believe I
should have Effected that Desirable object long since, he has Injured
me without Bennifiting himself—I however am Blessed with a <person_mentioned>family</person_mentioned>
who view <person_mentioned>Enemies </person_mentioned>and Misfortunes as removeable by time and proper
Exertions where truth and Justice is right in front as the poler star,
this rule we adhere to and of Course fear nothing man can do or
say— my best respects to <person_mentioned>Mr Westall</person_mentioned> and <person_mentioned>family </person_mentioned>and all other
acquaintances with you</p>

<p><person_mentioned>A E</person_mentioned></p>

<p>[Addressed:] <person_mentioned>Stephen F. Austin Esqr.</person_mentioned> Care of <person_mentioned>Jacob Cable</person_mentioned> 
<location_mentioned>Nachitoches Louisiana</location_mentioned></p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
