
<TEI.2 id="APB4047">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>10-10-1830</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1922: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1928), 3 vols., Vol 2, pp. 506-510</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Archibald Austin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Stephen F Austin</document_recipient>
<document_title>Archibald Austin to Stephen F Austin, 10-10-1830</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>New York, New York</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Archibald Austin to Austin, New York, October 10, 1830. Biographical notes. Galveston Ray & Texas Land Co.
</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes>Original in possession of Mrs. E. L. Perry.  This letter is unfinished.
The grants to Vehlein, Burnet, and Zavala, which were pooled under the management
of the Galveston Bay and Texas Land Company. See Barker, The Life of Stephen F.
Austin, 321--324.</barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 506-510</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>08-29-2010</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>


<text id="APB4047T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Archibald Austin to Austin, New York, October 10, 1830. Biographical notes. Galveston Ray & Texas Land Co.
</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><location_mentioned>New York</location_mentioned> <date_mentioned n="10-10-1830">10 Octr 1830.</date_mentioned></p>
<p>My Dear friend and <person_mentioned>Cousin</person_mentioned>,</p>

<p>On the morning of the <date_mentioned n="09-08-1830">8 ult°</date_mentioned>, I put my last letter for you in the
<location_mentioned>Ohio </location_mentioned>Bag for <location_mentioned>New Orleans</location_mentioned>, on that Evening, I observed the arrival
of the Nelson at quarantine, two or three days after<person_mentioned> Mr Woodbury
</person_mentioned>came up to the <location_mentioned>City</location_mentioned>, and told <person_mentioned>John </person_mentioned>that he had brought letters
from you, but had left them on board the vessel, in a bout a week
subsequent to that, he delivered to <person_mentioned>John </person_mentioned>your letter for him, and
one for myself and three <location_mentioned>newspapers</location_mentioned>—I had been calculating on a<barker_pb n="507"/>
letter from you, by this vessel, and was much pleased, to find my
anticipations realised—I congratulate you on the dispersion of the
clouds, that were lowering about your political horizon, and that all
was sun shine with you, that you were again fairly before the wind,
with a smooth Sea, and having proved yourself an accomplished
navigator, I trust you will steer clear of all rocks, and quicksands—</p>

<p>I was not so fortunate as to see <person_mentioned>Mr Woodbury</person_mentioned>, and <person_mentioned>John </person_mentioned>saw but
very little of him, I called several times to see him, but could never
find him in. I should like to have seen his papers, to have 
ascertained whether his <person_mentioned>Brother </person_mentioned>was mearly an <person_mentioned>agent</person_mentioned>, or whether he was
actually interested with the others concerned, and to have heard
from him the result of his visit to the <person_mentioned>Governour of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>, in which
he told <person_mentioned>John </person_mentioned>you was so kind as to accompany him—as <person_mentioned>Mr Prentiss</person_mentioned>
told me that <person_mentioned>Zavala </person_mentioned>was one of the principal persons interested in
that <location_mentioned>Grant</location_mentioned>, and that they are of opinion that<person_mentioned> Woodburys Brother</person_mentioned>
was only an <person_mentioned>agent</person_mentioned>, that he had seen <person_mentioned>W</person_mentioned>—once, and that he had
promised to show them his papers, but went into the <location_mentioned>Country </location_mentioned>
without doing so, he sais if his papers will show that his <person_mentioned>Brother </person_mentioned>was
interested he shall have his due, or if he was only to act as <person_mentioned>agent </person_mentioned>he
shall have justice done him, this as it may be—I am not much
acquainted with <person_mentioned>Prentess</person_mentioned>, he formerly lived in <location_mentioned>Lexington</location_mentioned>, and if
there is any person with you from that place; I presume he or they,
can inform you how he stood there,— <person_mentioned>Prentess </person_mentioned>tells me that he
has acted as <person_mentioned>agent for the Sale of Lands in the <location_mentioned>Grant</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> alluded to,
and for the purchase of them also, that he, and several of his <person_mentioned>friends</person_mentioned>
have made a purchase, and that his <person_mentioned>Son</person_mentioned>, who he sais is attached to
the <person_mentioned>Army</person_mentioned>, has obtained a furlough and is a going to visit that
<location_mentioned>Country </location_mentioned>this winter, and that some of his <person_mentioned>friends</person_mentioned>, and many more,
making up quite a <hi rend="italic"><person_mentioned>party</person_mentioned></hi>, are a going out to settle on that <location_mentioned>land </location_mentioned>this
winter—I told <person_mentioned>John </person_mentioned>if he saw <person_mentioned>Woodbury </person_mentioned>he better tell him to move
cautiously, he told me [he] had just time to tell him so in the street,
when he last saw him, that <person_mentioned>W</person_mentioned>— told him, he did not know but
he had some more <location_mentioned>newspapers </location_mentioned>for him, that he would just step
in and look, and call directly after, and see him but did not make
his appearance again—why he should have kept so aloof from
<person_mentioned>John </person_mentioned>and myself. I cannot imagine, we had no design on him, or
his <location_mentioned>lands</location_mentioned>, and all we were desirous to do was to prevent his being
imposed on, if we could help it—He expressed great delight with
<location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, and said he was a going to return immediately with several
of his <person_mentioned>Sons</person_mentioned>, I presume he is now in <location_mentioned>Connecticut</location_mentioned>, and may be back
soon, with some of his <person_mentioned>connections</person_mentioned>, purhaps he was afraid to act
without their council—</p>

<p><date_mentioned n="10-27-1830">27 Octr </date_mentioned>I approve of your idea of a Coat of Arms, and I know
no one better intitled to a Seal of the kind than yourself—I have<barker_pb n="508"/>
had one made on the most approved and recent fashion, which is
very plain, and I think all the handsomer for it, it has been the
fashion here to fore to have them very showey, with a great deal
of work on them, but that fashion is now exploded, the Seal 
without the Engraving cost $16. and for the engraving $10—whole cost
$26—for the Cross and initials he asked $6 and for the addition of
the Bucks Head and Horns $4 there are only two men in the <location_mentioned>City</location_mentioned>
who ingrave seals well, and this man <person_mentioned>Lovett</person_mentioned>, I was recommended
to as being the best, it appears a great price, but I could not prevail
on him to cut it cheaper. I have taken a great deal of pains, and
I hope it will please you, the seals of the fashion previous to the
present, cost from $25 to $35 without the Engraving—I shall send
this by <person_mentioned>Mr Wm T. Austin</person_mentioned> who Embarks in the Nelson, with his
<person_mentioned>wife</person_mentioned>—</p>

<p><person_mentioned>Mr Perry</person_mentioned> arrived here on <date_mentioned n="10-03-1830">Saturday Evening last</date_mentioned>, to see the balance
of his Goods on board the Nelson, I had the pleasure of his company
to dinner with me <date_mentioned n="10-09-1830">yesterday</date_mentioned>, in the Evening we called with an
Introduction <person_mentioned>Mr Treat</person_mentioned> gave him on <person_mentioned>Mrs Mexia</person_mentioned> to look at a military
coat of her <person_mentioned>Husbands</person_mentioned>, that he might give the <person_mentioned>Taylor </person_mentioned>who is to make
a coat for you a description of it, as he had bot the cloth there, and
could not find a Colns uniform of the <person_mentioned>Mexican </person_mentioned>Army in that <location_mentioned>City</location_mentioned>,
we however found it would be necessary for the <person_mentioned>Taylor </person_mentioned>to call and
see it, and <person_mentioned>Johns Taylor</person_mentioned> was to go up for that purpose this 
<date_mentioned n="10-10-1830">morning</date_mentioned>, we also called in the Evening to see <person_mentioned>Mr and Mrs Austin</person_mentioned> we
found them a very pleasant young couple, she is a very pretty little
woman, and I have no doubt they will be found a very agreable
acquisition to the Society in <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>— It was a great treat to me to
see <person_mentioned>Mr Perry</person_mentioned>, he had seen so many of my Connexions that I had not
seen for many years, and some that I have never saw, that felt a
desire to hear about, and he could tell me all about them. I had
only to regret that his stay was so short he left this on his return
home at<date_mentioned n="10-10-1830"> 2 o'clock to day</date_mentioned>. <person_mentioned>Mr Treat</person_mentioned>, I hear has made up his mind
to return in a few weeks to <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>,—<person_mentioned>Mr Woodbery</person_mentioned> is expected here
to return in the Nelson—</p>

<p>I saw <person_mentioned>Prentiss </person_mentioned>yesterday, he told me that <person_mentioned>Zavala </person_mentioned><person_mentioned>Mexia </person_mentioned>etc, was
calculating to make rappid progress in Colonising the <location_mentioned>Grants </location_mentioned>they
represent in <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, they intend Colonising the three <location_mentioned>Grants</location_mentioned>, and
give every incouragement and facility to <person_mentioned>emigrants</person_mentioned>, that land and
money can hold out to induce them to locate there, that lands will
be offered them low and those that are not able will be supplied
with means, talked of all kinds including <person_mentioned>Irish</person_mentioned>, I told him I thought<barker_pb n="509"/>
they would do there <location_mentioned>Colony </location_mentioned>more harm than good, if he introduced
a parcel of <person_mentioned>Irish </person_mentioned>into it—speaks of <person_mentioned>Z</person_mentioned>s having plenty of money at
command, talks of his being very popular with a large majority of
the <person_mentioned>people of Mexico</person_mentioned>, and calculates on a change in the present state
of things, when he will be a great man, if not at the head very
near it, they Calculate to go out <date_mentioned n="Spring - 1831">next Spring</date_mentioned>, to make a 
commencement, and thinks that in less than three years they will have Ten
Thousand <person_mentioned>Setlers </person_mentioned>in their <location_mentioned>land</location_mentioned>, that there will be 40,000 
<person_mentioned>inhabitants </person_mentioned>in <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>in that time, what fine calculations, in that case your
reserved lands will be very valuable at the end of three years— I
shall send you some newspapers by which you will see the effect
of the <person_mentioned>French </person_mentioned>revolution on the different powers of <person_mentioned>Europe</person_mentioned>, a
revolution has commenced in Spain, and we are calculating to hear
every day that it has become generral throughout the <location_mentioned>Kingdom</location_mentioned>,
no danger of <person_mentioned>Ferdinands </person_mentioned>ever troubling <location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned>again I presume,—
Several rich <person_mentioned>Spanards</person_mentioned>, who were obliged to leave <location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned>leave
this for <location_mentioned>New Orleans</location_mentioned> on <date_mentioned n="10-13-1830">Monday</date_mentioned>, with the expectation I presume
of soon being admitted into <location_mentioned>Mexico</location_mentioned>, and I think they are already
coming back from <location_mentioned>Europe </location_mentioned>with the same hope—I was at <location_mentioned>Amboy</location_mentioned>
the other day, and while there I told my youngest <person_mentioned>daughter, Louisa
Mary</person_mentioned> that I had been getting a seal made to send to you in 
consequence of which she has made a safety chain and sent me to forward
to you, being as she considered a very good accompaniment to the
seal, which I have put in the Box with it, I tied up some seeds which
we consider of choice Kinds, among them are some mellon, and I
believe pumpkin or squash seeds, which a friend of mine collected
in <location_mentioned>Mahone </location_mentioned>and gave to me, he told me they produced the best fruit
of any he ever taisted—I ment to have sent you an ear of our
Jursey Corn, to ascertain whether yours was of the same kind or
not, it is prefered for the <location_mentioned>Madeira market</location_mentioned>, and<person_mentioned> Mr P</person_mentioned> has almost
every year an order for some, that we sent this year cost here 61
cents p bushel—</p>

<p>I have written a letter for you, which I send <date_mentioned n="10-11-1830">to morrow</date_mentioned> under
cover to <person_mentioned>Mr Breedlove</person_mentioned>, I shall send it by private conveyance to save
postage, the postage on letters or packages from this to <location_mentioned>New Orleans
</location_mentioned>by water is 60—I suppose I must be in <person_mentioned>Mr B</person_mentioned>s debt 180 and perhaps
250 as three or four packages have passed through his hands—</p>

<p>We have heard that <person_mentioned>Henry </person_mentioned>has arrived with his Steam Boat in
<location_mentioned>your river</location_mentioned>, if he can meet with sufficient incouragement to remain,
the Boat must eventually do well, and be of great importance to your
<location_mentioned>Colony</location_mentioned>—Tell him his <person_mentioned>family </person_mentioned>are all well, and are now living in the
<person_mentioned>family </person_mentioned>of <person_mentioned>parson Curtis</person_mentioned>, in <location_mentioned>Oxford, Connecticut</location_mentioned>—</p><barker_pb n="510"/>

<p>In the Box I sent you some time ago, I presume you found a 
partial genealogy of our <person_mentioned>Family </person_mentioned>commencing above a century back,
which was given to <person_mentioned>Mrs Holly</person_mentioned>, in <location_mentioned>Boston</location_mentioned>, by <person_mentioned>Mr Austin</person_mentioned> of that City,
if [you] did not find it, in the Box <person_mentioned>Henry </person_mentioned>has a copy of it, and can 
furnish you writh one—then there is a large blank to be filled up, and as yet I
know not how it is to be done—-Our <person_mentioned>Grandfather </person_mentioned>on the <person_mentioned>Austin </person_mentioned>side
lived in <location_mentioned>Durham, in Connecticut</location_mentioned>, how he got there, or when, I know
not, He had four <person_mentioned>Sons</person_mentioned>, and two <person_mentioned>daughters</person_mentioned>, <person_mentioned>Elijah</person_mentioned>, <person_mentioned>Moses</person_mentioned>, 
<person_mentioned>Archibald</person_mentioned>, and <person_mentioned>Stephen</person_mentioned>, <person_mentioned>Mrs Eliott</person_mentioned> and <person_mentioned>Mrs Bates</person_mentioned>, your <person_mentioned>Fathers family</person_mentioned>
you of course know all about, and I presume more of the <person_mentioned>Bates</person_mentioned>
family than myself, My <person_mentioned>Fathers children</person_mentioned>, you are acquainted, or
if there is any particulars about them, that you wish to be informed
about <person_mentioned>Henry </person_mentioned>will inform you, our <person_mentioned>Uncle Archibald</person_mentioned> left no children,
and never heard of his having any, <person_mentioned>Stephen </person_mentioned>had one Son <person_mentioned>Charles</person_mentioned>,
who is married, has a family of <person_mentioned>children</person_mentioned>, and lives in <location_mentioned>Florida</location_mentioned>, there
were three <person_mentioned>daughters</person_mentioned>, of which there is only one living <person_mentioned>Mrs Meigs</person_mentioned>,
she has a large <person_mentioned>family</person_mentioned>, and live in this <location_mentioned>City</location_mentioned>, her <person_mentioned>Mother </person_mentioned>is very old
and very poor, and lives with them, the <person_mentioned>Elliott family</person_mentioned></p>

<p>[Archibald Austin]</p>


</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
