
<TEI.2 id="APB4108">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>12-16-1830</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1922: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1928), 3 vols., Vol 2, pp. 556-558</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>John P Austin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Stephen F Austin</document_recipient>
<document_title>John P Austin to Stephen F Austin, 12-16-1830</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>New York, New York</sent_from>
	<sent_to>San Felipe de Austin, Texas</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>John P. Austin to Austin, New York, December 16, 1830. Tornel's efforts
to prevent emigration to Texas. Formation of Galveston Bay & Texas Land
Co.   Swiss immigrants.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes></barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 556-558</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>09-02-2010</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>


<text id="APB4108T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>John P. Austin to Austin, New York, December 16, 1830. Tornel's efforts
to prevent emigration to Texas. Formation of Galveston Bay & Texas Land
Co.   Swiss immigrants.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><location_mentioned>New York</location_mentioned> <date_mentioned n="12-16-1830">December 16. 1830</date_mentioned></p>

<p>My dear <person_mentioned>Cousin</person_mentioned>,</p>

<p>I had this pleasure on the <date_mentioned n="10-28-1830">28. Oct</date_mentioned> per <person_mentioned>Mr. Wm T. Austin</person_mentioned>, who
sailed from here, in the Schooner Nelson due for <location_mentioned>Brazos</location_mentioned>, to which I<barker_pb n="557"/>
beg leave to refer, and have now to add a few lines by <person_mentioned>Mr. Treat</person_mentioned> who
was with you about a <date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1829">year Since</date_mentioned>, Now on the eve of sailing for
<location_mentioned>New Orleans</location_mentioned> on his way to<location_mentioned> Galveston Bay</location_mentioned>. I presume with a view of
fixing on a permanent location. Since my last I have not been able
to obtain any further information worthy of Communicating relative
to the proceedings of <person_mentioned>Mr. Wilson</person_mentioned> in regard to his<location_mentioned> Texas lands</location_mentioned>, but
should not be surprised if he had paid you a Visit ere this, as he
writes from <location_mentioned>Matamoros </location_mentioned><date_mentioned n="10-12-1830">October 12th</date_mentioned>—that he had in part succeeded
in the object of his Visit to <location_mentioned>Saltillo</location_mentioned>, but not to his satisfaction, and
of his intention of leaving in about a <date_mentioned n="11-xx-1830">Month </date_mentioned>to Survey his<location_mentioned> Texas
lands</location_mentioned> and expected to reach here in about <date_mentioned n="05-xx-1831">six Months</date_mentioned>. <person_mentioned>Mr. Tornel,
Mexican Minister at <location_mentioned>Washington</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>, a short time since addressed a 
circular to the <person_mentioned>Mexican Vice Consuls</person_mentioned> directing them not to grant any
passports for<location_mentioned> Coahuila and Texas</location_mentioned>, and to refer those applying for
them to the legation, but on the consul here representing to him the
situation he would be placed in by refusing them to <person_mentioned>American 
Citizens</person_mentioned> against whom no doubt the order was expressly intended to
operate, the <person_mentioned>Minister </person_mentioned>in reply authorized the <person_mentioned>Consul </person_mentioned>to use his own
discretion in granting them since which have been obtained without
difficulty. Passports were however at first refused and a vessel with
a Valuable Cargo, bound to <location_mentioned>Matamoros</location_mentioned>, detained some days and until
the above permission was received from <location_mentioned>Washington</location_mentioned>. Had the 
Government known it at the time which it probably did not, from the
order not being published and so soon annulled, I think <person_mentioned>Mr. Tornel</person_mentioned>
would have been Called on for an explanation of so singular a 
procedure. You will see by the Enclosed that a <person_mentioned>Company </person_mentioned>has recently
been formed here to Colonize the <location_mentioned>Grant of <person_mentioned>Zavala</person_mentioned>, <person_mentioned>Vehlein </person_mentioned>and 
<person_mentioned>Burnet</person_mentioned>,</location_mentioned> and <person_mentioned>Agent </person_mentioned>to be immediately Stationed at<location_mentioned> Galveston Bay</location_mentioned> to
receive <person_mentioned>Settlers </person_mentioned>and afford them every facility in settling on the land.
From what I can learn it is the Most extensive <person_mentioned>land Company</person_mentioned> that
was ever known in this or any other <location_mentioned>Country </location_mentioned>probably extending its
interests throughout the <location_mentioned>States</location_mentioned>, and its <person_mentioned>board of Directors</person_mentioned> is 
composed of the most respectable and influential <person_mentioned>Men </person_mentioned>among us, with
the <person_mentioned>President of one of our first Banks</person_mentioned> at its head, as also on the
<person_mentioned>Trustees</person_mentioned>. They are soon to publish a <location_mentioned>Pamphlet </location_mentioned>which I shall not
fail to send you and was in hopes to have got it in time for this
opportunity.</p>

<p>Should the <person_mentioned>Company </person_mentioned>Carry their plans into full operation and I
see no grounds to doubt it, as the funds at Command are said to be
very heavey, I should think could but be of essential benefit to your
<location_mentioned>Colony </location_mentioned>as I look upon Emigration to any part of <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>as 
favourable to your interest and more particularly <location_mentioned>between you and the
Sabine.</location_mentioned>   I had a conversation <date_mentioned n="12-16-1830">this Morning</date_mentioned> with an intimate <person_mentioned>friend</person_mentioned>.<barker_pb n="558"/>
who is well acquainted and has considerable influence with the 
<person_mentioned>Trustees</person_mentioned>, and strongly recommended that the above <person_mentioned>Company </person_mentioned>should and
without loss of time Communicate to you direct their views and
plans fully, that you may not get an unfriendly impression towards
them, from the various reports which would reach you thro'. Various
sources, and should<person_mentioned> Mr. Treat</person_mentioned> be detained a day or two longer I am
in hopes he will be the bearer of their Communication as I feel 
confident they will see their interest in Making it. the <person_mentioned>Company </person_mentioned>have
already chartered a Vessel to take out 50 to 100 <person_mentioned>Swiss Emigrants</person_mentioned>
and am told they have 250 <person_mentioned>families </person_mentioned>Engaged. They also load the
vessel I presume mostly with provisions. For further particulars
I would refer you to <person_mentioned>Mr Treat</person_mentioned> whom I have no doubt is well 
acquainted with the Views of the <person_mentioned>Company</person_mentioned>, as well as to <person_mentioned>Mr. 
Woodbury</person_mentioned> who also leaves here on <date_mentioned n="12-20-1830">Monday </date_mentioned>for your place Via <location_mentioned>New
Orleans</location_mentioned> and will probably be with you as soon as this. The Coat
ordered made for you by<person_mentioned> Mr. Perry </person_mentioned>I have the promise of this week
and if not disappointed will be in time to send by <person_mentioned>Mr. Woodbury</person_mentioned>, who
offers to take Charge of it or anything I may have to send you. I
have however seen very little of him since he has been here this
time. The Coat has been nearly a Month in the hands of the
<person_mentioned>Embroiderer </person_mentioned>and not possible to send same sooner. <person_mentioned>Col. Mexia</person_mentioned>, who
says he is a particular friend of yours, Very politely loaned the
<person_mentioned>Taylor </person_mentioned>his Coat that there might be no mistake in the uniform, and
is so much pleased with the Making of yours as to order one Made
for himself. As yet no letters from <person_mentioned>brother Henry</person_mentioned> since his arrival
with you, which I cannot account for it being nearly four Months
and very anxious to know how he is likely to succeed there with the
Boat.   In hopes of soon being in receipt of your esteemed favors</p>

<p><person_mentioned>J. P. Austin</person_mentioned></p>

<p>p. a</p>

<p><date_mentioned n="12-17-1830">December 17th</date_mentioned>.—<person_mentioned>Mr. Treat</person_mentioned> being still detained it gives me sincere
pleasure to add, that he is the <person_mentioned>bearer </person_mentioned>of a friendly Communication
to you from the <person_mentioned>Trustees of the land Company </person_mentioned>refered to above
which has been handed to me for perusal and perfectly coincides with
my Views of the propriety of Making known to you their plan of
operations as I can but think it will further the interest of the
<person_mentioned>Company </person_mentioned>as well as yours by having a Mutual and friendly 
understanding at the Commencement, as it will at all events prevent any
unfriendly feelings that might arise from Various reports that may
be in Circulation. That the success of the <person_mentioned>Company </person_mentioned>as they progress
may advance your interest as I think it undoubtedly will is the 
Sincere wish of your Affectionate <person_mentioned>Cousin</person_mentioned></p>

<p><person_mentioned>J. P. Austin</person_mentioned></p>
<p><person_mentioned>Mr. Zavala</person_mentioned> also writes you by this Conveyance</p>
<p>To <person_mentioned>Col. Stephen F. Austin</person_mentioned>  <location_mentioned> San Felipe dp Austin   Texas</location_mentioned></p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
