
<TEI.2 id="APB4564">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>05-06-1833</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1922: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1928), 3 vols., Vol 2, pp. 961-963</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Stephen F Austin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Luke Lesassier</document_recipient>
<document_title>Stephen F Austin to Luke Lesassier, 05-06-1833</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Unknown</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Austin to Luke Lesassier, Bexar, May 6, 1833. People of Bexar wish seat of State government transferred to Bexar, but will not formally petition for it. Will not join in petition for separate State organization.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes></barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 961-963</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>11-21-2010</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>


<text id="APB4564T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Austin to Luke Lesassier, Bexar, May 6, 1833. People of Bexar wish seat of State government transferred to Bexar, but will not formally petition for it. Will not join in petition for separate State organization.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><location_mentioned>Bexar </location_mentioned><date_mentioned n="05-06-1833">May 6. 1833</date_mentioned></p>
<p>Dr Sir.</p>

<p>We arrived at this place on the <date_mentioned n="04-29-1833">29</date_mentioned> having been detained by 
excessive rain, and high waters.</p>

<p><person_mentioned>Don Erasmo Seguin </person_mentioned>was absent at his <location_mentioned>plantation </location_mentioned>thirty miles
below this, where he arrived only a few days since from <location_mentioned>Matamoras</location_mentioned>.
I lost no time in sending for him, but the high waters prevented his
reaching here untill the <date_mentioned n="05-03-1833">3d inst</date_mentioned>. I communicated to him, his 
appointment as one of the mission to <location_mentioned>Mexico</location_mentioned>, and laid before him the
memorial, which was translated with the aid of <person_mentioned>Carbajal </person_mentioned>and
<person_mentioned>Balmaceda</person_mentioned>.</p>

<p>The <person_mentioned>principal citizens of this place</person_mentioned> have held meetings on the
evenings of the <date_mentioned n="05-03-1833">3d</date_mentioned>, <date_mentioned n="05-04-1833">4th</date_mentioned>, & <date_mentioned n="05-05-1833">5th instant</date_mentioned> to discuss this subject At the
meeting on the<date_mentioned n="05-04-1833"> 4th </date_mentioned>it was decided that a memorial should be sent to
the <person_mentioned>state govt</person_mentioned>, asking for the removal of the <location_mentioned>seat of government</location_mentioned> from
<location_mentioned>Monclova </location_mentioned>to this place, <person_mentioned>Don Erasmo</person_mentioned> being the only one who was in
favor of memorializing the <person_mentioned>General Congress</person_mentioned> for the separation and<barker_pb n="962"/>
<person_mentioned>State Govt</person_mentioned> A number of the others were in favor of saying to the
<person_mentioned>Legislature of <location_mentioned>Coahuila and Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>, that if the <location_mentioned>seat of Govt,</location_mentioned> was not
removed to this place, <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>would then separate— This meeting
adjourned after 12 oclock at night, to meet the <date_mentioned n="05-05-1833">next evening</date_mentioned> At
the meeting <date_mentioned n="05-05-1833">on the fifth</date_mentioned> the only question to be decided was the
manner of memorializing the <person_mentioned>state Govt</person_mentioned> for a removal of the <location_mentioned>seat of
Govt</location_mentioned>, as had been agreed to on the <date_mentioned n="05-04-1833">4th </date_mentioned>the late law of the <person_mentioned>state 
legislature</person_mentioned> regulating the " right of petitioning" was examined, and
construed to mean that neither the <person_mentioned>Ayuntamiento </person_mentioned>nor the <person_mentioned>citizens</person_mentioned>
in mass could petition, and that the memorial must only be signed
by three persons at most in the name of the people This 
construction I contended was erroneous The law says that, none but the
<person_mentioned>supreme powers of the state</person_mentioned> can represent the will of the <location_mentioned>people</location_mentioned>,
and prohibits corporations or public meetings, or <person_mentioned>individuals </person_mentioned>from
taking it upon themselves to say what is the will of the people etc
(See the law in <person_mentioned>alcalde </person_mentioned>records) The true meaning of this is, as I
think, that no corporation or persons can petition in the name of the
people, without first consulting them, by calling them together 
However it was decided that the law prohibited the <person_mentioned>Ayto </person_mentioned>from 
petitioning or from calling the people together to petition, and that only
three persons could petition The next question was, who would do
it? Only one man (<person_mentioned>Balmaceda</person_mentioned>) was willing to sign as one of the
three, so that the meeting broke up without doing anything or coming
to any definitive conclusion I believe that if the <person_mentioned>state Govt</person_mentioned> is granted
the <location_mentioned>people </location_mentioned>here will be well satisfied, but I do not believe they will
take any part whatever in favor or against the measure. I 
considered it my duty to use every exertion to procure their co-operation,
and have done so. The most that can be expected is, that they will
not oppose it The fact is, that the movement <date_mentioned n="Summer-1832">last summer</date_mentioned> against
this place, from the <location_mentioned>colony </location_mentioned>has produced a much deeper impression
than I was aware of untill now it has neutralized many who before
that were openly warm <person_mentioned>friends </person_mentioned>and it has made some decided <person_mentioned>enemies</person_mentioned>
to the <person_mentioned>colonists</person_mentioned></p>

<p><person_mentioned>Don Erasmo Seguin</person_mentioned> cannot go on the mission, I am convinced that
no unfriendly feelings deter him—but his private affairs will not
permit his leaving <location_mentioned>home</location_mentioned>.</p>

<p>Nothing was done, of course, as to the appointment of another to
go in his place.</p>

<p>The reports about new disturbances in the <location_mentioned>interior</location_mentioned>, and that
<person_mentioned>Genl Filisola</person_mentioned> had returned with the <person_mentioned>troops </person_mentioned>that were ordered to
<location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, are all incorrect and unfounded The <person_mentioned>Genl </person_mentioned>arrived at 
<location_mentioned>Matamoras </location_mentioned>on the <date_mentioned n="04-24-1833">24th ult°</date_mentioned> as we learn by letters recd, here <date_mentioned n="05-05-1833">last night</date_mentioned>.</p>

<p><person_mentioned>Santa Anna was elected president</person_mentioned> and <person_mentioned>Gomez Farias vice president</person_mentioned> by large <person_mentioned>majorities </person_mentioned>and they have entered upon their respective
offices   All is quiet, so far as I can judge from <person_mentioned>Genl Filisola</person_mentioned>'s com-<barker_pb n="963"/>
munications, and also from his general character I have confidence
that he will be the <person_mentioned>friend </person_mentioned>of liberal principles, and of <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>I leave
here <date_mentioned n="05-06-1833">to-morrow</date_mentioned> or <date_mentioned n="05-07-1833">next day</date_mentioned> for <location_mentioned>Goliad </location_mentioned>and thence to <location_mentioned>Matamoras</location_mentioned>,
and shall see the <person_mentioned>Genl </person_mentioned>as soon as possible The rains have been very
excessive in <location_mentioned>this part of the country </location_mentioned>and all travelling has been
suspended for the last week, but there is now a prospect of good
weather </p>               

<p>The <person_mentioned>legislature of the <location_mentioned>state</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> was to have adjourned on the <date_mentioned n="04-30-1833">last day
of April</date_mentioned>.</p>

<p><person_mentioned>Mr. Sawyer</person_mentioned> arrived from <location_mentioned>Monclova </location_mentioned>a few days since and brings
information that <person_mentioned>Fisher </person_mentioned>was there on his way to <location_mentioned>Matamoras </location_mentioned>He
has been continued in the office of <person_mentioned>Collector of <location_mentioned>Galveston</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>, as I am
informed by <person_mentioned>Sawyer</person_mentioned>, who says that he speaks favourably of the
<person_mentioned>Colonists </person_mentioned>etc etc</p>

<p>I will endeavor to procure their co-operation at <location_mentioned>Goliad </location_mentioned>and write
from there</p>

<p><person_mentioned>S. F. Austin</person_mentioned></p>

<p>N. B. You must make up your mind to answer regularly the 
correspondence of the <person_mentioned>chief of Department</person_mentioned> or be fined and probably
totally ruined. You can at least acknowledge the receipt of his
official letters, even if it is in English.</p>

<p>To <person_mentioned>L. Lesassier Alcalde of <location_mentioned>Austin</location_mentioned></person_mentioned></p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
