-
<TEI.2 id="APB4553">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>04-16-1833</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1922: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1928), 3 vols., Vol 2, pp. 947-950</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>George Fisher</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Stephen F Austin</document_recipient>
<document_title>George Fisher to Stephen F Austin, 04-16-1833</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Moncolva, Coahuila</sent_from>
	<sent_to>San Felipe de Austin, Texas</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>George Fisher to Austin, Monclova, April 16, 1833. upbraids Austin for injuring him with authorities and declares that he could have ruined Austin's colony by divulging certain information which he has. Inclosures: (1) Mexia to Austin, Mexico, March 11, 1833, urging reconciliation with Fisher, who has proved friendship for Texas; (2) copy of a letter written by W. Keene, of Mexico, to Mangino inclosing copy of a postscript written by Austin to a correspondent in Matamoros October 4, 1832, impugning Fisher's good faith; (3) Fisher's comment on Austin's note</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes></barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 947-950</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>11-18-2010</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>


<text id="APB4553T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>George Fisher to Austin, Monclova, April 16, 1833. upbraids Austin for injuring him with authorities and declares that he could have ruined Austin's colony by divulging certain information which he has. Inclosures: (1) Mexia to Austin, Mexico, March 11, 1833, urging reconciliation with Fisher, who has proved friendship for Texas; (2) copy of a letter written by W. Keene, of Mexico, to Mangino inclosing copy of a postscript written by Austin to a correspondent in Matamoros October 4, 1832, impugning Fisher's good faith; (3) Fisher's comment on Austin's note.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><location_mentioned>Monclova </location_mentioned><date_mentioned n="04-16-1833">16th April 1833.</date_mentioned></p>
<p><person_mentioned>Col. S. F. Austin</person_mentioned>.</p>

<p><location_mentioned>San felipe.</location_mentioned></p>

<p>Dear Sir. Enclosed I transmit you a Copy of a letter from our
mutual friend <person_mentioned>Gral Jose Anto: Mexia</person_mentioned> directed to you; original of
which I shall keep until I shall have the oportunity of handing to
you personally. From this letter you will discover how erroneous
an opinion you have formed of my going to <location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned>and which upon
the bare supposition of the <hi rend="italic">" on dits "</hi> from <location_mentioned>Matamoros </location_mentioned>you admitted
as a full fact, according to the contents of the <hi rend="italic">Post Scriptum</hi> to your
letter of <date_mentioned n="10-04-1832">4th Oct. 1832</date_mentioned> directed to your corresponsal in <location_mentioned>Mexico</location_mentioned>, and
of which likewise I acompany you a copy with the note in which I
received a Copy of said P. S. that you may see in what a miraculous
way it came to my hand, and to prove that no thing however secret
it may appear or be treated with will remain for ever unrevealed.</p>

<p>I think my dear <person_mentioned>Colonl </person_mentioned>that I had reason to expect to be treated
by you better than you have done, especially when yourself solicted
and I acquiesced in the presence of our Mutual friend <person_mentioned>Dr Mauricio
Hebenstreit</person_mentioned> in <location_mentioned>Matamoros</location_mentioned>, a reconciliation, and burrying into
oblivion the past reciprocal acts of recrimination, at whose table
we dined on said day. I was expecting and believing that from
that moment a new era comenced to exist between us, and that in
future a most cordial disposition towards the interest of <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>and<barker_pb n="948"/>
the best understanding between us was to commence. But low
behold what must have been my feelings at the receipt of the letter
of which under No. 2 I send you a copy. ? I ask what would have
been yours? and what supposition could you form, upon the 
investigation that said letter was directed to <person_mentioned>Mangino</person_mentioned>. With what
view and intention? My dear Sir do not believe that I am of
yesterday and that I cannot <hi rend="italic">guess </hi>at things if you do, you are sadly
mistaken.</p>

<p>It is very well known to you and to you only, that had I been
disposed, I could and can yet shake the foundation of your <location_mentioned>Colony</location_mentioned>,
and your individual welfare, you also know that I had more than
sufficient reasons for doing so, for you very well know that you
was the Instigated and <person_mentioned>promoter </person_mentioned>of all the mobs against me in
<location_mentioned>Tejas</location_mentioned>, that I should have had no difficulty with no person but lived
in perfect peace and quietness in <location_mentioned>Tejas</location_mentioned>, with my <person_mentioned>family</person_mentioned>. The unjust
persecutions put on foot by your <person_mentioned>associates </person_mentioned>through your 
instigation have destroyed that peace, have ruined my interest, have kept
me separate 3 Years from my <person_mentioned>family</person_mentioned>, and their happiness destroyed,
My defenseless and abandoned <person_mentioned>children </person_mentioned>cry unto heavens for 
vengeance for such acts of injustice. I alone possessed more than a comon
share of patience and forbearing have said nothing to justify myself
of the many foul charges alleged against me, and why ? is it becose
it is not in power? No, it is because I would not [s]trew firebrands
into your colony altho you charged me with it in your letter directed
to <person_mentioned>Col. Bradburn</person_mentioned> from <location_mentioned>Brasoria </location_mentioned>on the <date_mentioned n="12-24-1832">24th Dbre 1832</date_mentioned>. You know
very well that you have done me infinite injustice and have ruined
my and my families happiness and fortune, and yet when I am ready
and willing to forbear and to forgive at your own request in presence
of our mutual friend, you are still, after agreeing to it, disposed
further to persecute me,—Is this just? is it generous? is it noble
Do you suppose that you can keep me in that way out of <location_mentioned>Tejas</location_mentioned>, upon
which country I have as much right and claim as you or any other
man has or can have You are mistaken. I never shall give up my
claim on <location_mentioned>Tejas</location_mentioned>, and not even the assasins dagger will intimidate
me to return and live there, in any vocation or under any
circumstances.</p>

<p>To injure <location_mentioned>Tejas </location_mentioned>and to slander the Caracker of the <person_mentioned>inhabitants </person_mentioned>I
not need to go to <location_mentioned>Méjico </location_mentioned>it is the last place where I would go
to— You ought to know that in <location_mentioned>Matamoras </location_mentioned>in <date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1830">1830</date_mentioned> and<date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1831"> 31</date_mentioned>. I
had the management of the printing press, which I can get again
at any time, should I wish it.— What better medium than this to
injure <location_mentioned>Tejas </location_mentioned>and slander its <person_mentioned>inhabitants</person_mentioned>. Did I ever say any thing
in that <location_mentioned>paper </location_mentioned>injurious to <location_mentioned>Tejas</location_mentioned>? Did I ever defend my own cause
when I could do it? Why? Because I did not wish to reveal 
certain things, and persons compromised,   But can I forever forbear<barker_pb n="949"/>
new persecutions, and torments? You offered to me peace at 
<location_mentioned>Matamoras</location_mentioned>, I accepted, I run a dense vail over the past, you have broched
and opened the half healed wound. Will you quit, or will you 
continue? Will you have peace or war? You can have either, I leave
it to your own choice and discression. You have persecuted me,
you have ruined me, you can finish your work, and I will mine with
subscribing myself.</p>

<p><person_mentioned>George Fisher</person_mentioned>,</p>

<p>[Inclosures]</p>
<p>No. 1.</p>

<p>Sor. <person_mentioned>Coronel D. Estevan Austin</person_mentioned>—<location_mentioned>Méjico </location_mentioned>Marzo 11. de 1833.—Mi muy querido
amigo,—Hoy sale de esta <location_mentioned>capital </location_mentioned><person_mentioned>D. Geo. Fisher </person_mentioned>á encargarse nuevamte de su
antiguo destino en <location_mentioned>Galveston </location_mentioned>por disposición del <person_mentioned>gobierno</person_mentioned>. Yo me guardaría
bien de recomendarlo á V. si su conducta aqui no hubiera sido la de un celoso
partidario de la rebolucion nacional que ha terminado y en la que prestó
servicios importantes. De ello tiene documentos y por ellos ha ganado la
confianza de <person_mentioned>los patriotas</person_mentioned>.—</p>

<p>Con respecto á nuestro querido <location_mentioned>Tejas </location_mentioned>su porte ha sido el mejor, pues lejos de
calumniar ha defendido á sus <person_mentioned>habitantes </person_mentioned>de algunos ataques injustos que les
han querido dar los <person_mentioned>enemigos </person_mentioned>conocidos de su prosperidad.—</p>

<p><person_mentioned>Fisher </person_mentioned>me ha dado palabra de cultivar la mejor armonia con V. y con
todos los <location_mentioned>colonos </location_mentioned>y manejarse de modo que por su parte no haya motivo de
recordar disgustos pasados. Si fuere asi, como lo espero, me prometo que V.
interpondrá su poderoso influjo para que todos esos <person_mentioned>amigos </person_mentioned>le guarden las
concideraciones á que es acredor, supuesto qe. lo pasado fueron meras 
equivocaciones y compromisos que produjo la conducta de <person_mentioned>Terán </person_mentioned>y <person_mentioned>Bradburn</person_mentioned>.</p>

<p>En fin amigo, <person_mentioned>Fisher </person_mentioned>hablará con V. y en la calma yo jusgo qe. todo se
arreglará como se lo pido á V.</p>

<p>El dia 20. debo empesar en mis funciones de <person_mentioned>Senador </person_mentioned>y tanto en el <person_mentioned>Senado</person_mentioned>
como en cualquiera otra parte puede V. disponer de la buena voluntad qe. le
profesa su afmo. amigo.—<person_mentioned>J. Antonio Mejia</person_mentioned>.</p>

<p>No. 2.</p>

<p>Sor. <person_mentioned>D. Jorge Fisher</person_mentioned>.—<location_mentioned>Casa de V.</location_mentioned> <date_mentioned n="01-15-1832 [1833]">Enero 15. de 1832. [1833]</date_mentioned>— Estimado
amigo—Seria faltar á los vinculos de la amistad si no copiara á V. á 
continuación aqui, una carta del <person_mentioned>Sor. W. Keene </person_mentioned>dirijida al <person_mentioned>Sor. D. Rafael Mangino</person_mentioned>,
la que por una casualidad vino á mis manos. Y impuesto V. de su contenido
conocerá quienes sus <person_mentioned>amigos </person_mentioned>y hará el uso qe. á sus fines particulares le 
convenga.—" <location_mentioned>Méjico</location_mentioned> á <date_mentioned n="11-27-1832">27. de Novre de 1832</date_mentioned>—Muy Sor. mió y amigo. Refiriéndome
á la conversación qe. yo tube con V. el otro dia, respecto a <person_mentioned>Jorge Fisher</person_mentioned>, de
<location_mentioned>Tejas</location_mentioned>, lo considero justo remitirle á V. la adjunta copia del P. D. de la carta
del <person_mentioned>Coronel Austin</person_mentioned>, del propio país dirijida á su corresponsal en esta <location_mentioned>capital</location_mentioned>,
á fin de que V. vea en su traducion; que se pueda sacar por medio de algún
confidencial de V.; lo fundado de mi vituperación del carácter de <person_mentioned>Fisher</person_mentioned>, pues
mirando el buen nombre de un hombre con su mas sagrada propiedad, no
puedo consentir en bulnerarlo, sin hallarme apoyado en los fuertes indicios,
á lo menos de su Criminalidad.—Disponga V. de su antiguo amigo y S. S.
q. b. s. m.—<person_mentioned>R Keene</person_mentioned>___________</p>

<p>P. S. extracted from a letter of <person_mentioned>S. F. Austin</person_mentioned> to a Gentleman in <location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned>under
date of <date_mentioned n="10-04-1832">Oct: 4, 1832</date_mentioned>.</p>—<barker_pb n="950"/>

<p>"I understand from <location_mentioned>Matamoros </location_mentioned>that <person_mentioned>Geo: Fisher</person_mentioned> has gone to <location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned>to
slander <location_mentioned>Tejas</location_mentioned>. That man does not merit the confidence of the <person_mentioned>Government </person_mentioned>nor
of any one. On his first arrival here he said more to create a bad impression
on my mind against <person_mentioned>Alaman</person_mentioned>, <person_mentioned>Fagoaga</person_mentioned>, <person_mentioned>Tagle</person_mentioned>, and others, whom he called
<person_mentioned>Escoceses</person_mentioned>, than I ever heard from any other source. He has been a <person_mentioned>Guerrero</person_mentioned>
man, a <person_mentioned>Zavala </person_mentioned>man, and an acordada man etc a <location_mentioned>Jalapa</location_mentioned>, etc a <person_mentioned>Bustamante </person_mentioned>and
other sorts of man; as the case required. I fear he is a bad man. At 
<location_mentioned>Matamoros </location_mentioned>he told me that <person_mentioned>General Terán</person_mentioned> was to blame for all the difficulties about
the <location_mentioned>Custom House</location_mentioned>, that he only obeyed orders. To others he said diferently.
Such a man can do nothing but harm in this or any other <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>where he is
listened to."</p>

<p>Aunque firmó el mismo <person_mentioned>Keene </person_mentioned>esta post data la tachó toda su firma después.—
Quedo de V. como smpe su affo. amigo y segó. Servr. Q. B. S. M.-—<person_mentioned>M. M. Zires</person_mentioned>,</p>

<p>NOTE BY THE <person_mentioned>SUBSCRIBER</person_mentioned></p>

<p>On my arrival in <location_mentioned>Tejas </location_mentioned>I never mentioned the name of <person_mentioned>Alaman Fagoaga</person_mentioned> and
<person_mentioned>Tagle</person_mentioned>, to <person_mentioned>Col: Austin</person_mentioned> as bad men or to create bad impressions, and the last one I do not even know and much less could I say any thing against him. I
always was and will be a <person_mentioned>Guerrero </person_mentioned>man, or of that <person_mentioned>party</person_mentioned>, because they are the <person_mentioned>Democrats of this <location_mentioned>country</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>.— I never was a <location_mentioned>Jalapa </location_mentioned>nor <person_mentioned>Bustamante </person_mentioned>man, other-
wise <person_mentioned>Gral Teran</person_mentioned> would not have applied the 4th. Art° of the plan of <location_mentioned>Jalapa</location_mentioned>
against me, suspending me from my office barely because my appointment
was made by <person_mentioned>Guerrero</person_mentioned>.— At <location_mentioned>Matamoros </location_mentioned>I never told other wise and never will, but that I acted under the orders of <person_mentioned>Gral Terán</person_mentioned>, and the difficulties 
arrising from the <location_mentioned>Custom house</location_mentioned> affairs were through <person_mentioned>Col: Bradburn</person_mentioned>, <person_mentioned>Col Austin</person_mentioned> and others who interpreted the law in a different mode, and wanted the
people to believe that I had discressionary powers granted to me, and that I
was abusing of them and only acted by caprice, malice or revenge.— Let
these charges against me be substantiated before the competent tribunals and
then it will be seen how I acted and in virtue of what orders.—altho I could
have done great deal of harm, had I been malicious enough or revengefull yet I
never have done any nor will do it to the <person_mentioned>people of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>.— A mans character
may be slandered he may be persecuted and ruined, and sacrificed yet time will
reveal the truth and the instigators and promoters, what will ultimately gain
by such proceedings?</p>

<p><location_mentioned>Monclova</location_mentioned>, <date_mentioned n="04-16-1833">16th. April 1833</date_mentioned>.</p>

<p><person_mentioned>Jorge Fisher.</person_mentioned>    [Rubric]</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>


