
<TEI.2 id="APB3016">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>10-15-1825</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1223-1224</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>William A. Sheldon</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Stephen F. Austin</document_recipient>
<document_title>William A. Sheldon to Stephen F. Austin, 10-15-1825</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>New Orleans, Louisiana</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Asks information concerning terms of settlement, conditions of cotton culture, etc. Some cotton trade already between Texas and New Orleans.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes></barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1223-1224</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>06-02-2010</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Cameron L. Sinclair, Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>


<text id="APB3016T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Asks information concerning terms of settlement, conditions of cotton culture, etc. Some cotton trade already between Texas and New Orleans.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><location_mentioned>New Orleans</location_mentioned> <date_mentioned n="10-15-1825">October 15th 1825</date_mentioned></p>
<p><person_mentioned>Stephen Austin Esqr</person_mentioned></p>

<p>Respected Sir,— You will have the goodness to pardon the
self-introduction of an individual whose only object is to obtain
information of your section of the <location_mentioned>country</location_mentioned>. For some years past I
have been located in this <location_mentioned>city</location_mentioned>, and permanently established as a
<person_mentioned>Druggist </person_mentioned>in society with <person_mentioned>Mr. Saml D. Dixon</person_mentioned> under the firm of <person_mentioned>Sheldon and Dixon</person_mentioned>. It is possible that our <person_mentioned>house </person_mentioned>may not be unknown
to some of the <person_mentioned>settlers</person_mentioned> in your <location_mentioned>neighbourhood</location_mentioned>, who will assure you
that my inquiries do not arise out of iddle curiosity— Public report holds out many inducements to persons discontented with their
localities, to emigrate to <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, and 'tis not unfrequently in my
travels in the <location_mentioned>western states</location_mentioned> that I have questions asked me, I am
unable to reply to, particularly as regards the grants of yourself
and <person_mentioned>Mr. Edwards</person_mentioned>.— The information I receive, is vague and unsatisfactory, and in many instances contradictory, but generally
favourable to your <location_mentioned>settlement</location_mentioned>— It would be highly gratifying to
impart information to others by authority emanating directly from
yourself.—</p>

<p>I have been frequently solicited by <person_mentioned>Col. Charles Morgan</person_mentioned>, of the
<location_mentioned>parish of Point Coupée</location_mentioned>, a rich and respectable <person_mentioned>Planter</person_mentioned>, to address
you on the subject of the culture of cotton in <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, and whether any
experiments have come under your own observation, where the
transplanting of the seed to prevent Rot has been successful.— a
letter from him last mail induced me, to open a correspondence with
you, submitting to your option its continuence—</p>

<p>I am under the impression that a small Parcel of Texican cotton
was gin'd here <date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1824">last year</date_mentioned>, and the seed is in our present crop. It is
generally admitted that a change of Seed affords the best preventive known, against a premature decay of the Cotton Plant and the
Southern seed by experiments of <person_mentioned>Col. Morgan</person_mentioned> and <person_mentioned>Ledoux</person_mentioned> is, by
them supposed to be far preferable to that generally planted from
the importations from <location_mentioned>Kentucky</location_mentioned>, <location_mentioned>Alabama</location_mentioned> etc. It is also thought
by them that seed from <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned> <hi rend="italic">might</hi> be obtained with more facility,
and that the staple of <location_mentioned>Louisiana</location_mentioned>'s cotton would be improved in a
ratio to compensate planters in incurring the small additional expense of reshipping it from hence to their <location_mentioned>plantations</location_mentioned>.—It may not
be unknown to you that <hi rend="italic">The Rot</hi> annually increases throughout the
States of <location_mentioned>Louisiana</location_mentioned> <location_mentioned>Georgia</location_mentioned> <location_mentioned>Missippi</location_mentioned> and all <location_mentioned>Florida</location_mentioned>; <date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1825">this year</date_mentioned>
complaints are heavy, and a remedy must be soon afforded to prevent the recurrence of a really national evil.—</p>

<p>Permit me to inquire on what kind of soil, with you, does the
cotton plant best flourish? and whether there is much, or any dif<barker_pb n="1224"/>
ference in the texture or length of staple of the cotton raised near
the <location_mentioned>sea coast</location_mentioned> or in the <location_mentioned>interior</location_mentioned>—on the <location_mentioned>high or low lands</location_mentioned>, or the
<location_mentioned>Prairais </location_mentioned>or <location_mentioned>waving surface</location_mentioned>? and whether the<location_mentioned> natural plains</location_mentioned> afford
rich soil for cultivation or if there is a necessity for clearing land
for a <person_mentioned>plantation</person_mentioned>? and is the timber heavy, of difficult clearing, and
of what species generally bordering on the <person_mentioned>sea coast</person_mentioned>?</p>

<p>The <hi rend="italic">particular</hi> inquiries I desire are the terms on which <location_mentioned>lands </location_mentioned>are
<hi rend="italic">now</hi> disposed of, by yourself, either to <person_mentioned>families </person_mentioned>or individual settlers? do you distinguish in purchasers, men of family, from young
and single farmers, and is the quantity of land specified in any
general law or custom, beyond which an individual cannot contract for? have <person_mentioned>settlers</person_mentioned> the privilege of selecting their lands as
regards situation, and on purchasing have they the power to dispose of any part, or the whole of it again? Is it necessary that
purchased land should be occupied ?</p>

<p><person_mentioned>Mrss. Dewey and Sabin, sole proprietors of the patent for the
corn and cob mills</person_mentioned>, for this and the state of <location_mentioned>Missippi</location_mentioned> desires me
to ask you whether any encouragement would be given among your
<person_mentioned>settlers</person_mentioned> for the running of a few pair of stones, and also the <location_mentioned>mill</location_mentioned>
for grinding the corn and cob, with, or without them for cattle's
food? are there advantageous <location_mentioned>cities </location_mentioned>for <location_mentioned>mill seats</location_mentioned> on streams?
<location_mentioned>Saw and grist mills</location_mentioned>, and at convenient distances for the <person_mentioned>country
settlers</person_mentioned> ?—</p>

<p>Perhaps I have, too long, intruded on your patience with a long
letter of inquiries, but any information you may afford me will
be welcomed with thanks, and reciprocated if you do me the pleasure of requiring it—</p>

<p><person_mentioned>William A. Sheldon</person_mentioned>    [Rubric]</p>

<p>Address—<person_mentioned>Sheldon & Dixon Druggists and Commission Merchants</person_mentioned> <location_mentioned>New Orleans</location_mentioned></p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
