
<TEI.2 id="APB4647">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>06-03-1834</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1922: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1928), 3 vols., Vol 2, pp. 1060-1062</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Stephen F Austin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Samuel M Williams</document_recipient>
<document_title>Stephen F Austin to Samuel M Williams, 06-03-1834</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Exinquisition, Mexico</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Austin to Samuel M. Williams, Mexico, June 3, 1834. Suggesting memorial to government by the ayuntamientos expressing gratitude for reforms and faithful allegiance.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes></barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1060-1062</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>12-05-2010</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>


<text id="APB4647T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Austin to Samuel M. Williams, Mexico, June 3, 1834. Suggesting memorial to government by the ayuntamientos expressing gratitude for reforms and faithful allegiance.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><location_mentioned>Mexico Exinquisition </location_mentioned><date_mentioned n="06-03-1834">June 3. 1834</date_mentioned></p>
<p><person_mentioned>S. M. Williams</person_mentioned></p>

<p>On the <date_mentioned n="05-031-1834">31st </date_mentioned>I drew on the <person_mentioned>house of Beers St. John & Co</person_mentioned>. for seven
hundred forty seven dollars 51/100</p>

<p>I have received three letters from you <date_mentioned n="03-13-1834">13 March</date_mentioned> <date_mentioned n="04-13-1834">13</date_mentioned> and <date_mentioned n="04-15-1834">15 April</date_mentioned>—
also information that I could draw on the above house, from <person_mentioned>Don
E. M. [Ramon Musquiz]</person_mentioned> through his <person_mentioned>brother-in-law</person_mentioned>—all that
<person_mentioned>family </person_mentioned>have been firm and true <person_mentioned>friends </person_mentioned>to me in all my troubles
and I hope my friends will never forget them</p>

<p>I have heard of the laws passed by the <location_mentioned>state </location_mentioned>in favor of <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>I
have not seen them except the land law which I approve of very
much and of all the others so far as I have heard of them</p>

<p>I think it is the duty of the <person_mentioned>people of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> to return thanks in
a public manner to the <person_mentioned>state Govt</person_mentioned>, through the <person_mentioned>Ayuntamientos </person_mentioned>and
<person_mentioned>chief of departments</person_mentioned> for these laws and also to make a most solemn
and positive declaration of their firm adhesion, union and 
attachment to the <location_mentioned>state of Coahuila and Texas</location_mentioned> and to the <location_mentioned>Mexican 
confederation</location_mentioned>. This declaration or document ought to be drawn up in
an able manner, concise, but clear and full and it ought to be 
published in the <location_mentioned>U. S</location_mentioned>. in order to correct public opinion there as to
the intentions and objects of the <person_mentioned>people of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>.</p>

<p>The position taken by them last year was <hi rend="italic">" that the evils which
threatened that <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>with anarchy and ruin must be remedied by
the <person_mentioned>Govt</person_mentioned>, or the <person_mentioned>people </person_mentioned>would remedy them of themselves and
ought to do so, as in the last resort they wiould have the right to do
so on the principle of self preservation"</hi></p>

<p>I sustained this position firmly as the <person_mentioned>agent of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> before the
<person_mentioned>ministers </person_mentioned>and the <person_mentioned>vice president</person_mentioned> and my letter of <date_mentioned n="10-02-1833">2 October</date_mentioned> [was
based] upon it, and upon the public good and general interest of the<barker_pb n="1061"/>
<location_mentioned>republic </location_mentioned>and of <location_mentioned>Coahuila and Texas</location_mentioned> by recommending that the 
constituted <person_mentioned>municipal authorities </person_mentioned>should take up the subject and thus
prevent popular commotions.</p>

<p>A frank and plain statement of these facts and of the true situation
of <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>and the state of public opinion etc all embodied in the
document of public thanks to the <person_mentioned>Govt</person_mentioned>, above mentioned, would place
the whole matter in its true light before the world, and contradict all
the calumnies and false reports, that the <hi rend="italic">intentions </hi>and <hi rend="italic">objects </hi>of
those people, and also my objects, were a total separation from
<location_mentioned>Mexico</location_mentioned>—such reports are all false. It is also reported here that those
<person_mentioned>people </person_mentioned>have abandoned me and wish me shot or imprisoned for life,
and the <person_mentioned>enemies of North Americans</person_mentioned> and of <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>are making use
of this calumny both against me and against the <person_mentioned>people of Texas</person_mentioned>,
for our <person_mentioned>enemies </person_mentioned>wish to make out that those people are ungrateful
and bad, and they say that if they abandon me they would also
abandon the <person_mentioned>Govt</person_mentioned>. etc. etc.—all calumnies and false.</p>

<p>I particularly requested those <person_mentioned>people </person_mentioned>not to be excited on account
of my arrest, and strongly urged and begged that they would remain
quiet and faithful to the <location_mentioned>state of Coahuila and Texas</location_mentioned>, as I had no
doubt the state government would remedy the evils complained of—
I thank the <person_mentioned>people </person_mentioned>for having complyed with my request. The result
has shown that I was right. The evils have all been remedied in a
<hi rend="italic">legal </hi>manner, excitement and commotions kept down in <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, The
<person_mentioned>people of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> and the <location_mentioned>whole state</location_mentioned> and <location_mentioned>nation </location_mentioned>have been served
<hi rend="italic">effectually </hi>and all motives for discontent in future are forever 
removed. My mission to <location_mentioned>Mexico</location_mentioned>—<hi rend="italic">the position taken by my 
<person_mentioned>constituents </person_mentioned>and firmly sustained by me</hi> here, and my imprisonment and
sufferings and the <hi rend="italic">noise </hi>and <hi rend="italic">alarm </hi>occasioned by all these things—
have materially contributed to bring about this happy result—and
I therefore do not regret what I have suffered and the money I have
spent. On my part I risked all for those <person_mentioned>people </person_mentioned>and to sustain the
position taken by them—I now expect that <hi rend="italic">they </hi>on their part will do
justice to the <person_mentioned>Govt </person_mentioned>who has remedied all their evils, to me their
<person_mentioned>agent</person_mentioned>—and to themselves as high minded and honorable <person_mentioned>men </person_mentioned>and as
true and faithful <person_mentioned>Mexican citizens</person_mentioned>.</p>

<p>All this they can do by a public and official document of the 
character before mentioned combining a statement of facts as to 
themselves, and as to me their <person_mentioned>agent</person_mentioned>; thanks to the <person_mentioned>Govt </person_mentioned>for what has
been done; and a clear declaration of union and fidelity to the <location_mentioned>state</location_mentioned>
and to the <location_mentioned>Mexican confederation.</location_mentioned></p>

<p>This will place the matter before the world in its true light, and
do justice to all parties and silence calumny for ever—it will also
keep ambitious or restless spirits quiet.</p><barker_pb n="1062"/>

<p><person_mentioned>D. G. Burnet</person_mentioned> would be a good hand to draft such a document
aided by <person_mentioned>Capt Martin</person_mentioned>, <person_mentioned>Miller</person_mentioned>, <person_mentioned>Jack</person_mentioned>, <person_mentioned>Chambers</person_mentioned>, <person_mentioned>Jones</person_mentioned>, <person_mentioned>Adams</person_mentioned>,
<person_mentioned>Johnson</person_mentioned>, <person_mentioned>Lesassier </person_mentioned>etc—</p>

<p>My <person_mentioned>enemies </person_mentioned>in the <location_mentioned>low country </location_mentioned>that you speak of will do me 
justice—no one can be so base as to calumniate the man who has served
them faithfully and is suffering for their benefit—personal feelings
are momentary in their influence but <hi rend="italic">justice </hi>will finally prevail over
them.   I wrote <date_mentioned n="06-02-1834">yesterday </date_mentioned>to <person_mentioned>Oliver Jones.</person_mentioned></p>

<p>Remember me to <person_mentioned>Ramon Musquiz</person_mentioned> particularly—I shall feel 
grateful to him and <person_mentioned>D. Vr B° [Victor Blanco]</person_mentioned> as long as I live and hope
my <person_mentioned>friends </person_mentioned>will—also remember [me] to everybody—let the present
happy situation of that <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>forever bury all personal feelings.
<hi rend="italic">I bury them forever</hi>—and let us all devote ourselves to cultivate the
soil, make good crops, and be good neighbors and good citizens— so
soon as I can close my affairs so as to get on to a <location_mentioned>farm </location_mentioned>I will do so,
and it will be a difficult matter to drag me away from it—unless
it be to go to a <location_mentioned>ball </location_mentioned>or a <location_mentioned>social meeting</location_mentioned> of friends. I am done with
public matters, that is when I get free from them I mean to keep
so—-and I mean to get free as soon as I can</p>—

<p><person_mentioned>S. F. Austin </person_mentioned>   [Rubric]</p>

<p>You can show this letter to whom you think proper I send it
via <location_mentioned>New Orleans</location_mentioned> I am in good health I was <hi rend="italic">incomunicado 
rigororisimo</hi> from the <date_mentioned n="02-13-1834">13 Feby</date_mentioned> to <date_mentioned n="05-09-1834">9 May</date_mentioned>—no books or writing materials
and very little light—dreary enough, but the idea that <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>would
be benefited and that I had done my duty kept up my spirits and I
bore all patiently. I hope that <person_mentioned>Almonte </person_mentioned>who was sent to <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>by
<person_mentioned>Govt</person_mentioned>, has been well received and kindly treated, no friend of mine
or of <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>would think of treating him or any other <person_mentioned>commissioner
of the Govt</person_mentioned>, in any other manner than with attention and politeness.
The <person_mentioned>enemies of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>, or my <person_mentioned>enemies </person_mentioned>might wish to take a different
course in order to make confusion and difficulty.</p>

<p><person_mentioned>S.F.A</person_mentioned>.</p>

<p>I sent a power of attorney to my <person_mentioned>brother-in-law</person_mentioned> to sell property
and I now send a duplicate.   I wrote him by way of <location_mentioned>Orleans </location_mentioned><date_mentioned n="05-10-1834">10 May</date_mentioned>.</p>


</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
