
<TEI.2 id="APB1253">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>08-23-1826</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1430-1434</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>James E. Brown Austin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Stephen F. Austin</document_recipient>
<document_title>James E. Brown Austin to Stephen F. Austin, 08-23-1826</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>San Antonio, Texas</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>J. E. B. Austin to Austin, August 22, 1826. Authorities at San Antonio have
made strong protest against abolition of slavery- Feels sure that slaves of the
first colony will be safe. Valuable services of Bastrop in representing interests
of Texas. Much regret at union with Coahuila. Saucedo approves collection
of fee from colonists to reimburse you for labor and expense.   Other matters.
</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes></barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1430-1434</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>07-08-2010</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>


<text id="APB1253T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>J. E. B. Austin to Austin, August 22, 1826. Authorities at San Antonio have
made strong protest against abolition of slavery- Feels sure that slaves of the
first colony will be safe. Valuable services of Bastrop in representing interests
of Texas. Much regret at union with Coahuila. Saucedo approves collection
of fee from colonists to reimburse you for labor and expense.   Other matters.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">


<p><location_mentioned>San Antonio</location_mentioned> <date_mentioned n="08-22-1826">August 22 de 1826 (Wednesday)</date_mentioned> </p>
<p>Dr <person_mentioned>Brother</person_mentioned>,</p>

<p>I arrived at this place last <hi rend="italic"><date_mentioned n="08-18-1826">fryday </date_mentioned></hi>but declined writing untill
the present moment as I had not collected matter sufficient for a
lengthy letter and the mail does not go out untill <date_mentioned n="08-24-1826">thursday</date_mentioned>. on
my arrival here I found a letter from you and last mail brought
another; your " triste " letter by last mail has almost given me the
<hi rend="italic">horrors</hi>, to see you so gloomy—I am happy to hear your health is
so much improved—and I hope a favourable <person_mentioned>Slave </person_mentioned>Law will have
a <hi rend="italic">salutary effect</hi> in removing the <hi rend="italic">hippo </hi>and other <hi rend="italic">affecting </hi>
complaints—such as the frets, lowering the eye brows etc etc—</p>

<p>now for the news—in the first place <person_mentioned>Bernardo Gutierris</person_mentioned> has been
removed from office and yr friend <person_mentioned>Genl Anastacio Bustamente</person_mentioned> 
appointed in his place— The <person_mentioned>Government </person_mentioned>is much displeased at the
conduct of <person_mentioned>Gutierris</person_mentioned> he has deceived them on every point relative
to the state of <person_mentioned>Indian </person_mentioned>affairs in this Department—the <person_mentioned>Government</person_mentioned>
has made sufficient appropriations to carry on the <person_mentioned>Indian </person_mentioned>War with
energy but it appears he applied the appropriations of Govt to his
own private use; and represented to the Govt that the Campaign
was proceeding with all possible vigor— <person_mentioned>Bustamante </person_mentioned>will make
this <location_mentioned>head Quarters</location_mentioned> untill the war is finished—no doubt exists that he
is on the way—his proclamación to the <person_mentioned>inhabitants </person_mentioned>of this 
Department has already arrived   you will receive one by this mail—</p>

<p>I perceive by your letter that the <person_mentioned>Slave </person_mentioned>question has caused 
considerable sensation in the <location_mentioned>Colony </location_mentioned>I have had much conversation
with <person_mentioned>Saucedo </person_mentioned>and others on this subject I see no reason why you
should apprehend the abolition of the <person_mentioned>Slaves </person_mentioned>belonging to the <person_mentioned>300
families</person_mentioned>; the thing is decided with regard to that point—<hi rend="italic">those
<person_mentioned>slaves </person_mentioned>are guaranteed to the <person_mentioned>settlers </person_mentioned>by the Law of Colonization and
they cam, not he deprived of them</hi>—this is the opinion that prevails
in this place— The <hi rend="italic"><person_mentioned>Ayuntamiento </person_mentioned></hi>of this place presented a 
memorial to the <person_mentioned>Legislature </person_mentioned>as soon as the project arrived—praying that
the discussion on that important point might be suspended untill
they could have time to <hi rend="italic">consider </hi>upon it, and inform the other
<person_mentioned>Ayuntamientos </person_mentioned>of the Department that they might do the same.
Since then they have given it the attention it merited—and by the
last mail <hi rend="italic">have sent</hi> up a <hi rend="italic">representation couched</hi> in the strongest<barker_pb n="1431"/>
language they could express in <hi rend="italic">favor </hi>of the <hi rend="italic">admission <location_mentioned></hi>in the New
<hi rend="italic">Colonies</hi></location_mentioned>—they <hi rend="italic">declare </hi>it to be <hi rend="italic">indispensable </hi>to the prosperity of
this Department; in fact they have said all they can say—as to
the prospect of freeing the <person_mentioned>slaves </person_mentioned>of the <person_mentioned>300 families</person_mentioned> they declare
it to [be] an unjust abuse of the rights of the <person_mentioned>Colonists</person_mentioned>— As to the
plan of indemnifying the <person_mentioned>Settlers </person_mentioned>for their <person_mentioned>slaves </person_mentioned>it is absurd
where is the <location_mentioned>State </location_mentioned>to obtain <hi rend="italic">500,000</hi>—in. <hi rend="italic">cash </hi>to pay for the <person_mentioned>slaves</person_mentioned>
that are already introduced—for it is not expected they will be
deprived of them—and lay out of their capital 3 or 4 years—all
these things have been considered—and <hi rend="italic">for my part</hi> I have a more
flattering hope of a favourable <person_mentioned>slave </person_mentioned>law—at this time than I have
ever had before—your <hi rend="italic">representation </hi>has been sent on—they say
it is "algo duro"—but they make allowances—<person_mentioned>Saucedo </person_mentioned>showed
me a letter from the <person_mentioned>Baron </person_mentioned>and the <person_mentioned>Senator Cevallos</person_mentioned> on this subject
the <hi rend="italic"><person_mentioned>viejo </person_mentioned></hi>is very warm on the subject—you will receive a copy of
it by mail— The <person_mentioned>Old Baron</person_mentioned> has strove hard for us—I know not
what would have been our fate if he had not been a member of the
Legislature— Our situation would have been a deplorable one 
indeed—</p>

<p>If a favourable <person_mentioned>Slave </person_mentioned>Law is passed it will be attributed in a great
measure to the <hi rend="italic">unremitted </hi>exertions of the <person_mentioned>Baron </person_mentioned>and I wish the
<person_mentioned>Settlers </person_mentioned>to know it—as many of them are inimical to him—popular
opinion has changed very much in his <hi rend="italic">favor </hi>within the last year in
this place—I wrote him a lengthy letter last mail to act a " contra "
to the " Triste " one I supposed you had written At all events if it
comes to the worst and the <person_mentioned>slaves </person_mentioned>of the <person_mentioned>300 families</person_mentioned> are <hi rend="italic">freed </hi>we
have a right to appeal to <person_mentioned>Congress</person_mentioned>—where I am convinced all will
go right—</p>

<p>I have conversed with <person_mentioned>Saucedo </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>Flores </person_mentioned>relative to yr. contract
with <person_mentioned>Burnett </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>Fullerton</person_mentioned>—<person_mentioned>Saucedo </person_mentioned>is fully of the opinion that
you are at <hi rend="italic">liberty </hi>to make any contract of that kind you may think
proper—and recommends the plan as the surest and most expeditious
to settle the <location_mentioned>New Colony</location_mentioned>—he and <person_mentioned>Flores </person_mentioned>also observes that no 
objection can be made as to reserving a certain extent of <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>for them
and having it <hi rend="italic">surveyed </hi>against they arrive—even if they should not
arrive under a year—as the Law allows six years for the settling of
the <location_mentioned>new Colonies</location_mentioned>—</p>

<p>I think you misunderstand the law relative to the introduction of
<person_mentioned>100 families</person_mentioned> before they can receive possession—<person_mentioned>Saucedo </person_mentioned>say's that as
fast as they arrive they can have the quantity of land designated to
them the law allows—and they can go on to it and go to work and
when the <person_mentioned>Commissioner </person_mentioned><hi rend="italic">arrives </hi>they can be put in possession—<person_mentioned>Flores</person_mentioned>
will wait untill he hears more from you—or untill the <person_mentioned>Slave </person_mentioned>
question is decided but he tells me to inform you that you may expect<barker_pb n="1432"/>
the utmost <hi rend="italic">latitude </hi>from him that can be given—without infringing
the Law of Colonization too much—</p>

<p>I have fully explained to <person_mentioned>Saucedo </person_mentioned>the necessity of your <hi rend="italic">receiving</hi>
something to satisfy you for your trouble and the expense you
are at—</p>

<p>he feels fully convinced that it is just and right you should do
so—and says there will be no difficulty on that head—If you can make
a <hi rend="italic">contract </hi>with the <person_mentioned>new Settlers </person_mentioned>to pay 20, 30, or 100 dollars; if you
please over and above what the Govt requires—he says you have a
right to do so—as the Law makes all contracts on the part of the
<hi rend="italic"><person_mentioned>Empresario </person_mentioned></hi>and <person_mentioned>Colonists </person_mentioned>binding provided it is with their consent—
however—he has promised me to do all he can for you on this point—
The <person_mentioned>New Arancel Mr. Kerr</person_mentioned>—will take on—I have seen the 
instructions of <person_mentioned>Flores </person_mentioned>they are very <hi rend="italic">full </hi>and <hi rend="italic">explicit </hi>but they are so lengthy
that owing to my <hi rend="italic">bad health</hi> I shall not be able to copy them for
you—With the advice of <person_mentioned>Saucedo </person_mentioned>I do not think it necessary for me
to go on to <hi rend="italic">Saltillo </hi>but I have written the <person_mentioned>Baron </person_mentioned>that should it be
necessary—to write me Directed to <location_mentioned>san Carlos</location_mentioned>—</p>

<p>I shall leave this the <date_mentioned n="8-24-1826">day after to morrow </date_mentioned>for <location_mentioned>Laredo</location_mentioned>—I wish you
to write to me directed to <location_mentioned>San Carlos</location_mentioned>—you must expect no assistance
from this place untill the <person_mentioned>Comdt Genl Bustamante</person_mentioned> arrives then I 
expect <person_mentioned>troops </person_mentioned>will be stationed on the <location_mentioned>Brazos</location_mentioned>—<person_mentioned>Ahumada </person_mentioned>will be removed
to <location_mentioned>Nacogdoches</location_mentioned>—with the <person_mentioned>Troops </person_mentioned>under his command, and a 
<person_mentioned>garrison </person_mentioned>will be placed on the <location_mentioned>Sabine</location_mentioned>—the Govt has appropriated an 
immense sum for the payment of <person_mentioned>Troops </person_mentioned>stationed in this Department
$60,000 dollars arrived not long since and 30,000 will arrive next
week—and 30,000 more is <hi rend="italic">already </hi> "habilitado "—</p>

<p>Your draft on the Govt at this place has been duly <hi rend="italic">honored </hi>and I
can get the money today—</p>

<p>The <location_mentioned>French </location_mentioned>fleet has met with a <hi rend="italic">total defeat</hi> <location_mentioned>10 miles the other
side of the San Marks</location_mentioned>—6 <person_mentioned>Indians </person_mentioned>stole 80—mules and 25 horses and
left them completely on foot—they have procured 30 yoke of oxen
in this place—and have been a week gone to bring in the waggons—</p>

<p>The order for an Election for <person_mentioned>Electors </person_mentioned>was published in this
place on <date_mentioned n="08-20-1826">Sunday last</date_mentioned>—and the same will be forwarded on to the
<location_mentioned>Brazos </location_mentioned>by this mail—It appears the <person_mentioned>Electors </person_mentioned>are to meet at this
place on the <date_mentioned n="09-06-1826">6th of next month</date_mentioned> for the purpose of Electing an <person_mentioned>Elector</person_mentioned>
to vote for <person_mentioned>Deputies to Congress</person_mentioned> the <person_mentioned>Elector </person_mentioned>that is appointed has
to go all the way to <location_mentioned>Saltillo </location_mentioned>to give in his vote—and has to bear
his own expense there and back; the <person_mentioned>inhabitants </person_mentioned>of this place are
very much disgusted with so absurd a regulation—and I believe they
have come to the conclusion to vote for the <person_mentioned>Baron</person_mentioned>; as he is already
there and it is well known he will only vote for those that are 
favourably disposed towards this Department—they speak of <person_mentioned>Dn Victor
Blanco</person_mentioned>, <person_mentioned>Gonzales</person_mentioned>, <person_mentioned>Cevallos</person_mentioned>, or <person_mentioned>Yesca [Viesca]</person_mentioned>—we are entitled to 4<barker_pb n="1433"/>
<person_mentioned>Electors </person_mentioned>and they must be instructed to vote for the <person_mentioned>Baron </person_mentioned>as
<person_mentioned>Elector</person_mentioned>—O! how the <person_mentioned>Citizens </person_mentioned>of this place do curse the day they
connected themselves to <hi rend="italic"><location_mentioned>Coahuila</location_mentioned></hi></p>

<p>I cannot tell when I shall return I am determined not to do so
untill I do something—If slavery is not permitted I have come to
the conclusion provided I can get 100 mules to employ 4 or 5000
dollars in goods and bring them to this place—I have never seen so
good a prospect to clean 8 or 9000 dollars as offers at this time—
here (and owing to the prohibition laws which they have lately 
received the strictest orders to enforce) And the additional <hi rend="italic">number</hi>
of <person_mentioned>troops </person_mentioned>to be stationed here, the prospect will be better—6 or 7
months hence—</p>

<p>As to the <location_mentioned>Colony </location_mentioned><person_mentioned>Saucedo </person_mentioned>says there is no restriction—there is
one thing I wish to caution you—There has lately arrived here a
new <hi rend="italic">decree </hi>relative to passports and you must be particular to whom
you give pasports hereafter—(the same order has been sent on to
you) you will have to express in the pasports whether they are
<person_mentioned>Colonists </person_mentioned>or not—if they bring goods the <hi rend="italic">kind </hi>and the amt The
cause of this last Decree relating to pasports is owing [to] <hi rend="italic">abuses</hi>
comitted by <person_mentioned>strangers </person_mentioned><location_mentioned>on the Coast</location_mentioned> against the <hi rend="italic">Revenue </hi>laws—and
also for fear <location_mentioned>Spain </location_mentioned>may introduce <person_mentioned>Emissaries </person_mentioned>into this <location_mentioned>republic </location_mentioned>as
she has lately done in <hi rend="italic"><location_mentioned>Buenos Ayres</location_mentioned></hi>—</p>

<p><person_mentioned>Berrimende</person_mentioned> and <person_mentioned>Dn Erasmo's son Juan </person_mentioned>will start on the <date_mentioned n="09-01-1826">1st of next
month</date_mentioned> for <location_mentioned>New Orleans</location_mentioned> they calculate to go by <location_mentioned>Sn Felipe</location_mentioned> you must
try and be at home—I wish you to be <hi rend="italic">very particular</hi> in yr attentions
to <hi rend="italic"><person_mentioned>Juan </person_mentioned>for my sake</hi> for I am certainly <hi rend="italic">indebted </hi>to his <person_mentioned>family </person_mentioned>for
inumerable favors—<[should] he want a new supply of provisions
furnish him with the best let it cost what it may—Also he will want
letters of recomendation to <person_mentioned>persons </person_mentioned>in 
 which I wish
you to furnish him with he goes on to purchase goods, probably
to the amt of 1000 or 1,200—Also tell <person_mentioned>Mrs. Picket</person_mentioned> to have some good
<hi rend="italic">butter </hi>for him to take along on the road—I would rather that you
and <person_mentioned>J. E. G[ross]</person_mentioned>—would come to some understanding different
from the one you are now on—as to Keep from what I have learned
since I left you—it is his intention to leave the <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>shortly—</p>

<p><person_mentioned>Parker </person_mentioned>has been imprisoned in <location_mentioned>La Bahia</location_mentioned> very unjustly I have
procured an order for his release—which the <person_mentioned>Govr </person_mentioned>has sent on to
day-</p>
<p>Do, let me beg of you to assume more cheerfulness you always
put the worst construction on things and thereby render yourself
fretful and melancholy—you are . . . [three lines torn away] there
has been and is still much sickness on this place</p>

<p>I wish you to inform <person_mentioned>Huber </person_mentioned>that he can do well in this place; as to
His procuring a situation in the army it is uncertain untill the arrival<barker_pb n="1434"/>
of <person_mentioned>Bustamante </person_mentioned>for the <person_mentioned>Comte</person_mentioned>- of this place has petitioned for a
<person_mentioned>surgeon </person_mentioned>some time since—And the Govt- has promisd to <hi rend="italic">furnish</hi>
one—but in the mean time <person_mentioned>Huber </person_mentioned>could come on and learn the
language and form acquaintances—The obligation of <person_mentioned>Roxo the
Chief</person_mentioned> has [been] received and enclosed I send you his receipt—
<person_mentioned>Saucedo </person_mentioned>has informed me that from recent information reced- (not
officially) <person_mentioned>Edwards </person_mentioned>will not be <hi rend="italic">permitted </hi>to go on with his <location_mentioned>Colony</location_mentioned>
but will have to leave the <location_mentioned>Country </location_mentioned>beyond a doubt—</p>

<p>I think <person_mentioned>Burnett</person_mentioned>'s prospect pretty good—If <person_mentioned>Burnett </person_mentioned>gets the
settling of that <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>I think you ought to make some 
arrangement to have an interest in it.</p>

<p>Do not neglect to ascertain if <person_mentioned>Bingham </person_mentioned>will sell his <location_mentioned>Gin </location_mentioned>and for
what price—and let <person_mentioned>Musquis </person_mentioned>know by next mail if possible—I wrote
to him on the subject before I left home—Also I wrote to<person_mentioned> Capt.
Hirams</person_mentioned> to collect me a few pounds of Turpentine and to send it to
<person_mentioned>Williams</person_mentioned>—to be forwarded on to <person_mentioned>Dn Erasmo</person_mentioned> by the <person_mentioned>mail rider</person_mentioned>—it
is for <person_mentioned>Musquis </person_mentioned>and . . . [three lines torn away.]</p>

<p>Tell <person_mentioned>Williams </person_mentioned>that <person_mentioned>Dn. Erasmo</person_mentioned> has not time to write him this
mail owing to Multiplicty of business— he thinks he had better come
on here—</p>

<p>Enclosed I send you the measure of <person_mentioned>Saucedo </person_mentioned>for a pair of shoes
which do not fail to send him by the <person_mentioned>Mail rider</person_mentioned> if they can be 
procured.</p>

<p>My health is bad— I continue weak and you must excuse errors in
this lengthy scrawl—</p>

<p><person_mentioned>Lewis </person_mentioned>is still in <location_mentioned>Santa Rosa</location_mentioned> his business is unfinished as yet but
has taken <hi rend="italic">favourable turn</hi>— I am told he is engaged in working
a mine—</p>

<p>(<date_mentioned n="08-24-1826">Thursday</date_mentioned>) Since writing the above Owing to my weakness and
the <person_mentioned>company </person_mentioned>that starts to day for <location_mentioned>Laredo </location_mentioned>not being sufficiently
strong I shall wait until the <date_mentioned n="09-01-1826">1st. of next month</date_mentioned>— When we can make
up a considerable <person_mentioned>party</person_mentioned>— I am <hi rend="italic">informed </hi>the <location_mentioned>road </location_mentioned>is infested by
<person_mentioned>Indians</person_mentioned>.</p>

<p>Give my respects to <person_mentioned>Williams </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>Burnett</person_mentioned>— I am glad to hear
that <person_mentioned>Williams </person_mentioned>" <hi rend="italic">devil</hi>" has started I hope he will have more peace
of mind than formerly—The mail has just arrived from the 
<location_mentioned>interior</location_mentioned>—The first part of the Constitution has arrived— (that is the
project) no part of it has yet been adopted The Discussion comd
[commenced] on the <date_mentioned n="08-22-1826">22d inst</date_mentioned>. next month will bring something
final—<person_mentioned>Bustamente </person_mentioned>left <location_mentioned>San Luis Potasi</location_mentioned> on the <date_mentioned n="08-11-1826">11th of the present</date_mentioned>—
etc. etc.—</p>

<p>I believe I have given you all the news that I am possessed of—</p>

<p>Remember me to the <person_mentioned>widow </person_mentioned>and all of my <person_mentioned>friends </person_mentioned><person_mentioned>Dn. Erasmo</person_mentioned>
and <person_mentioned>family </person_mentioned>send their respects—</p>

<p><person_mentioned>J. B. Austin    </person_mentioned>[Rubric]</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
