
<TEI.2 id="APB1692">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>03-17-1829</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1922: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1928), 3 vols., Vol 2, pp. 183-192</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Stephen F Austin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Josiah H Bell</document_recipient>
<document_title>Stephen F Austin to Josiah H Bell, 03-17-1829</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>San Felipe de Austin, Texas</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Austin to Josiah H. Bell, March 17, 1829. Replying to charges reported by
Bell March 14: The alcalde and the ayuntamiento obeying the State law in
making certain registrations for the citizens; most of popular uneasiness arises
from ignorance of the law and inability of the people to inform themselves
because they do not understand Spanish. If the people object to the lawyers,
let them settle their difficulties by arbitration and drive the lawyers out of
business. He himself knows the laws and is in touch with the acts of the
ayuntamiento; he will protect the people.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes>For the proceedings of the Ayuntamiento see its Minutes in Southwestern Historical
Quarterly, xxi, 299-326, 395-423.    Read also Austin to Bell, Apr. 4, 1829.
See Art. 121 of Decree No. 37, quoted in ibid, 300. The order of the ayuntamiento
on the subject is in Ibid., 400.
It does not appear in the official publication of the laws,
Thomas M. Duke was the first alcalde of the ayuntamiento of San Felipe. The Court
of Alcaldes was an appellate court created by Austin in 1826 to assist him in the judicial
business of his colony. See an article by the editor on the Government of Austin's
colony, Southwestern Historical Quarterly, XXI, 231
</barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 183-192</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>08-10-2010</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>


<text id="APB1692T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Austin to Josiah H. Bell, March 17, 1829. Replying to charges reported by
Bell March 14: The alcalde and the ayuntamiento obeying the State law in
making certain registrations for the citizens; most of popular uneasiness arises
from ignorance of the law and inability of the people to inform themselves
because they do not understand Spanish. If the people object to the lawyers,
let them settle their difficulties by arbitration and drive the lawyers out of
business. He himself knows the laws and is in touch with the acts of the
ayuntamiento; he will protect the people.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><location_mentioned>San Felipe de Austin</location_mentioned> <date_mentioned n="03-17-1829">March 17, 1829</date_mentioned></p>
<p>Dr Sir</p>

<p>I have been so much occupied for some time past arranging the
papers and business of the <location_mentioned>office </location_mentioned>preparitory to my departure for
the <location_mentioned>United States</location_mentioned> that I have not had an opportunity of mixing
much with the <person_mentioned>settlers </person_mentioned>or of knowing what was afloat amongst them
Your letter contained some sentences which induced me to make
enquiries, and I must express great astonishment and regret at what
I have been told in regard to the rumors that are afloat; that is,
if it be a fact that the rumors I allude to are in circulation, and
produce the excitement which it is said they do—</p>

<p>A clamor is made, as it is said, because the <person_mentioned>Ayto </person_mentioned>are about to
levy a tax for municipal purposes—and the pretext on which this
clamor is founded is that the <person_mentioned>Ayuntamiento </person_mentioned>have no right to tax
the <person_mentioned>people </person_mentioned>because the colonization law exempts them and also it is
said that there is no use for funds etc— Those who have 
circulated such ideas are either ignorent of the law, or are wilfully
malicious and wish to create confusion. The colonization law most
postively and expressly says that the <person_mentioned>colonists </person_mentioned>shall be taxed by the<barker_pb n="184"/>
<person_mentioned>Ayto </person_mentioned>in the manner that the <person_mentioned>people </person_mentioned>are in all other parts of the
<location_mentioned>state </location_mentioned>for munnicipal purposes—the law [exempts] the <person_mentioned>colonists </person_mentioned>from
Taxes in all cases except three one is the taxes that are laid generally
by Government to repel a <person_mentioned>foreign </person_mentioned>invasion, another is the tax on
<location_mentioned>mines </location_mentioned>that may be worked by <person_mentioned>colonists</person_mentioned>, and the third is the 
municipal tax that is levied by the <person_mentioned>Ayto </person_mentioned>for municipal purposes—so much
then for the legality of the measure—are funds necessary?—the law
has prescribed the duties of the <person_mentioned>Ayto </person_mentioned>they are numerous and highly
important and cannot be discharged without funds, and if they are
neglected the <person_mentioned>members </person_mentioned>of the <person_mentioned>Ayto </person_mentioned>are each of them individually
liable to a heavy fine—The <person_mentioned>Ayto </person_mentioned>of <date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1828">last year </date_mentioned>did not comply with the
duties required by law in any one particular and each of the 
<person_mentioned>members </person_mentioned>were liable to a fine, and nothing but my own interference and
representations and excuses for them, saved them from the fine—-
This state of things is now at an end, the <person_mentioned>chief of Department</person_mentioned> has
officially notified the <person_mentioned>Ayto </person_mentioned>of this <date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1829">year </date_mentioned>that he will execute the law
upon them, if they neglect their duty any longer—It is made their
duty by law to procure a competent <person_mentioned>Secretary</person_mentioned>, to provide the 
necessary <location_mentioned>public buildings</location_mentioned>, to provide funds to pay for their <location_mentioned>post office</location_mentioned>
accounts, and to pay the necessary and legal expences of the 
<person_mentioned>Municipal authority</person_mentioned> and [the <person_mentioned>Chief] of Department</person_mentioned> has long ago called
on them officially to present to him an estimate of the expences that
are required and to propose a system of taxation to raise the means
of paying those expences—Some persons have said that the <person_mentioned>Ayto</person_mentioned>
have petitioned the legislature to lay a tax such <person_mentioned>persons </person_mentioned>are either
grossly ignorant of the law, or are wilfully malicious— For the
last 13 months the Govt have been repeating order upon order to the
<person_mentioned>Ayto </person_mentioned>to do their duty, to raise municipal funds, and to execute the
laws, the thing has been delayed under one pretext or another untill
I have actually exhausted all the stock of reasonable excuses that
I could devise and have drawn so largely upon shadows and 
frivolous apologies that I am ashamed to interfere any more, for I do
not wish to say to the Govt that the <person_mentioned>Ayto </person_mentioned>are afraid to do their duty
and to execute the law lest the people should resist, for this would in
fact be saying that the <location_mentioned>jurisdiction of Austin </location_mentioned>was in a state of 
rebellion. Instead therefore of petitioning the legislature to lay a tax,
the <person_mentioned>Ayto </person_mentioned><hi rend="italic">have been driven</hi> by the Govt to inform them how a tax
could be levied so as to be as nearly equal upon all as possible— The
<person_mentioned>Ayto </person_mentioned>were brought to the necessity of doing one of three things,
either to propose a tax or to pay a heavy fine, or fly the <location_mentioned>country</location_mentioned>
to save themselves from it— These are the facts as to the law and
[official?] orders relative to a municipal tax—</p><barker_pb n="185"/>

<p>The law most postively requires the <person_mentioned>Ayto </person_mentioned>to keep a register of
births and deaths in the <location_mentioned>jurisdiction</location_mentioned>, and to make a return every
three months to the <person_mentioned>Chief of Department</person_mentioned>. The <person_mentioned>old Ayto of <date_mentioned n="1828">last
year</date_mentioned></person_mentioned>  paid no regard to the law, in fact they did nothing on any
subject that they ought to have attended to. The <person_mentioned>Chief </person_mentioned>has 
postively told this <person_mentioned>Ayto </person_mentioned>that he will fine them if they neglect this duty
any longer, and to save expence to the <location_mentioned>muncicipality </location_mentioned>the plan was
suggested by me to advertise all over the <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>requesting every
one to make a return of the births and deaths in his <person_mentioned>family</person_mentioned>, and this
plan was adopted and the advertisements were posted up— Strange
and incredible as it would appear to any man who possessed 
common sence, that this measure should create discontent and 
misrepresentation, it is nevertheless true, every <person_mentioned>father </person_mentioned>and every <person_mentioned>mother </person_mentioned>and
every <person_mentioned>child </person_mentioned>in the jurisdiction is interested in this law, for it is of
the highest importance to <person_mentioned>children </person_mentioned>that a legal register of their births
should be kept for it secures to the <person_mentioned>children </person_mentioned>beyond the possibility of
a doubt important privileges as native born <person_mentioned>Mexicans </person_mentioned>that some day
or other may be of the greatest advantage to them. But 
independent of this it is the law and should be obeyed— My reasons
for advising [the Ayto.] to take the plan of advertising for all 
persons to make the return was to save expence, for if this plan had
not been adopted, the <person_mentioned>sheriff </person_mentioned>would have been compelled to have
gone to <location_mentioned>each man's house</location_mentioned> and taken the list every three months and
this would have cost the <person_mentioned>people </person_mentioned>of the <location_mentioned>jurisdiction </location_mentioned>about five or six
hundred dollars each three months— It was the wish of the <person_mentioned>Ayto</person_mentioned>
to comply with the law, to save themselves from fine and 
punishment and to benefit <person_mentioned>Parents </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>children </person_mentioned>by forming the register
of births and deaths as the law requires, and at the same time to do
it in a way that would save expence to the <location_mentioned>jurisdiction</location_mentioned>, and for
doing this I am told that the people are discontented and say that
it is to get fees into the office, there are no fees to be paid, but if the
<person_mentioned>sheriff </person_mentioned>is sent round to <location_mentioned>each mans house</location_mentioned> every three months, <hi rend="italic">his fees</hi>
would have to be paid and you and all others may rest assured that
if the returns are not sent in as required by the notices, that the
<person_mentioned>sheriff </person_mentioned>will be sent round, and the <person_mentioned>people </person_mentioned>will be taxed to pay him—
for as I before said the <person_mentioned>Ayto </person_mentioned><hi rend="italic">are compeled </hi>to make these returns
every three months—and it will be putting about 1000 Dollars a year
into the pocket of the <person_mentioned>Sheriff </person_mentioned>if the <person_mentioned>people </person_mentioned>do not comply with the
notices that have been posted upon the subject, and taking 
that much from the pockets of the people— this is the fact as to this
subject of [active?] clamor.</p><barker_pb n="186"/>

<p>All civilized <location_mentioned>countries </location_mentioned>that I know anything about have a vagrant
law—this <location_mentioned>state </location_mentioned>has one, and it is a very good and just and necessary
one—. The <person_mentioned>old Ayto</person_mentioned> paid no regard to it—<hi rend="italic">the <person_mentioned>members </person_mentioned>of that body
believed that it would distroy their popularity to attempt to stop
or correct disorder.</hi> I was of a different opinion and censured
them for permitting rioting drunkeness and fighting etc to the
extent that prevailed here <date_mentioned n="1828">last year</date_mentioned>, and I advised the <person_mentioned>present ?yto</person_mentioned>
to publish the law on the subject and to execute it vigorously. They
have published it in full, and that has raised a clamor against them.
I regret very much that good <person_mentioned>citizens </person_mentioned>should suffer themselves to
be operated upon by the clamors of disorderly and bad <person_mentioned>men</person_mentioned>, because
it tends to encourage such men to be clamorous—they know that
they have nothing to hope from the law nor from justice, for if
the law was executed and justice done them they would suffer heavy
penalties and it is therefore their interest to gull the people by 
crying out oppression, and trying to enlist their sympathies, and 
creating prejudices against the <person_mentioned>authorities</person_mentioned>. I regret this state of things
exceedingly, it has caused me to doubt that there is either a want
of judgment in the mass of the people to discriminate between a
rigid and just execution of the laws, and an abuse of them or that
there is a great mass of moral depravity which revolts from 
restraint or legal control. I believe however that the evil proceeds
from the former, rather than from the latter cause. It is highly 
pernicious no matter from what cause it proceeds, for if the people can
be operated upon by clamorous <person_mentioned>men</person_mentioned>, everything like stability or
security in the administration of Govt is at an end—the civil 
authority must be sustained by public confidence or it can do nothing,
and if the <person_mentioned>people </person_mentioned>are mere puppets in the hands of artfull 
<person_mentioned>demagogues </person_mentioned>and clamorous <person_mentioned>factionists </person_mentioned>whose interest it is to discredit
the civil <person_mentioned>authorities </person_mentioned>and throw them into ridicule, where is the
security of honest men? It is in the good sence and morality of
a <location_mentioned>grog shop</location_mentioned> or <location_mentioned>common brothel</location_mentioned>, rather than in the law or in the
officers of justice-— A man who has mixed a great deal with the
people of this <location_mentioned>colony </location_mentioned>and whose judgment of human nature is very
good has told me repeatedly that a few clamorous bad <person_mentioned>men </person_mentioned>with
smooth and plausible tongues could throw the people into a ferment
and create a prejudice against the <person_mentioned>civil authorities </person_mentioned>whenever they
pleased. I fear his opinion was well founded tho not because the
<person_mentioned>people </person_mentioned>are generally in favor of bad men, but because they lack 
judgement to discriminate between what is the duty of a public <person_mentioned>officer</person_mentioned>,
and an abuse of his authority— This want of judgement arises
from a want of knowledge of the laws by which the persons in
office are obliged to be governed, and also from a disposition to be
suspicious and jealous of " men in power"? it is to be sure a pigmy<barker_pb n="187"/>
sort of power to be a member of the <person_mentioned>Ayto </person_mentioned>for that body can do
nothing except by authority of law and under the direct and 
immediate control and supervision of the Govt—but it is an office, and
the <person_mentioned>American people</person_mentioned> have a national propensity to suspect and to
abuse all men who are in office—this want of knowledge of the laws
then I believe to be the true source of all the evils, and it cannot
be remedied at this time, for it is impossible to have all the laws
translated and printed in the English language, and in this state
of things the only safe guard the people have against the artfull
clamors of designing and malicious <person_mentioned>men </person_mentioned>is to repose full confidence
in the authorities of Govt and to be satisfied that they will not
do any thing contrary to law, nor contrary to the true interest of
the people—</p>

<p>You say that the people have full confidence in me. I must 
confess that they have a bad way of shewing their confidence, by
indulging in groundless and immaginary complaints and vague 
suspicions against the civil <person_mentioned>authority </person_mentioned>when it is well known that I am
here and have my eye on every act of the <person_mentioned>Ayto </person_mentioned>that is of any 
importance—The three measures I have spoken of—the tax—the <person_mentioned>vagrants</person_mentioned>—
and the notice to report births and deaths every three months, were
all adopted with my advice and knowledge</p>

<p>The <person_mentioned>Ayto </person_mentioned>so far have committed no error that I know of, of any
kind unless it is neglecting to do some things that they ought to
have attended to, such for instance as making a return as the law
requires of the <person_mentioned>children </person_mentioned>born of <person_mentioned>slave parents</person_mentioned> and reporting monthly
what their situation is etc. etc.</p>

<p>If the people have confidence in me, they are safe—I know the
laws and the duties of the <person_mentioned>Ayto </person_mentioned>and I also understand what the
people of this <location_mentioned>colony </location_mentioned>ought to do for their own good. Much better
than they do, for if they were left solely to themselves, the <location_mentioned>colony</location_mentioned>
would be ruined and thrown into perfect anarchy in three months-
Let the <person_mentioned>people </person_mentioned>therefore dismiss their unfounded fears and suspicions
and repose in me, if they doubt the <person_mentioned>Ayto</person_mentioned>, and I pledge myself that
they shall hear of it the moment that <person_mentioned>Ayto </person_mentioned>adopt an illegal or a 
pernicious measure, and above all things let them close their ears against
the clamors of those who have <hi rend="italic">more to say,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">less to loose </hi>either
of property or character than any body else in the <location_mentioned>country</location_mentioned>.</p>

<p>There has been some errors no doubt in the administration of 
justice and the fees that have been charged by the <person_mentioned>Alcalde </person_mentioned>and by the
<person_mentioned>Sheriff </person_mentioned>have been too high in some instances—but the present <person_mentioned>alcalde</person_mentioned>
in this respect has only followed what others did last year—the fee
bill will now be published and it will reduce the <person_mentioned>sheriffs </person_mentioned>fees 
considerably, and also the <person_mentioned>Alcaldes</person_mentioned>, and I hope <hi rend="italic">that </hi>will <hi rend="italic">not </hi>make a
clamor—</p><barker_pb n="188"/>

<p>The law regulating fees was passed by the <person_mentioned>Legislature </person_mentioned>of this
<location_mentioned>state </location_mentioned>last year. that law fixes the <person_mentioned>sheriff</person_mentioned>s milage at half a dollar
for each League he rides <location_mentioned>from the seat of justice to the place where
the process is to be served</location_mentioned>. The way I understand this law is that
the <person_mentioned>sheriff </person_mentioned>can charge that sum for the number of Leagues he rides
and no more—for example if he has ten writs to serve at <location_mentioned>Brazoria</location_mentioned>,
and it is 20 Leagues from here to that place he only rides 20 Leagues
to serve them all and can only charge 20 Leagues of milage and no
more, and not 20 Leagues on each writ, for then he would get pay
for 200 Leagues when in fact he had only traveled 20. Heretofore
the <person_mentioned>sheriff </person_mentioned>has charged the full amt of milage on each writ and
agreeably to this rule if he had 100 writs and summons for <location_mentioned>Brazoria</location_mentioned>
he would get pay for 2000 Leagues which would be $1000, when in
fact he had only traveled 20 Leagues and therefore by law would be
entitled to receive 10 Dollars and no more—This is the greatest
abuse that exists in the <location_mentioned>colony </location_mentioned>and this abuse must and will be 
corrected. I urged the <person_mentioned>old Alcaide </person_mentioned>to publish the fee bill and to 
execute it—I do believe that the only reason why it was not published
last year, was because the <person_mentioned>Alcalde </person_mentioned>feared the <person_mentioned>Sheriff </person_mentioned>would make a
clamor and it was supposed that the <person_mentioned>people </person_mentioned>would join him, for it
has always been a general rule with the people to join in any clamor
raised by no matter whom against the <person_mentioned>Alcalde </person_mentioned>or the <person_mentioned>Authorities</person_mentioned>
let it be just or unjust. The fees charged by the <person_mentioned>Alcalde </person_mentioned>have never
been very high, tho they are a little higher than the law allows, but
the present <person_mentioned>Alcalde </person_mentioned>has only followed the rule that was adopted by
his <person_mentioned>predicessor</person_mentioned>, and <person_mentioned>Duke </person_mentioned>followed the rule that was adopted by the
<person_mentioned>old Court of Alcaldes</person_mentioned>, who made a new fee bill much higher than
the one which I established when the administration of justice was
in my hands— No one is bound by law to pay any costs unless the
bill of costs is made out with each item stated and signed by the
<person_mentioned>Alcalde </person_mentioned>and delivered to the person who has it to pay or to his <person_mentioned>agent</person_mentioned>
if he has one, and that bill of costs is a voucher on which the Alcalde
may be punished by the <person_mentioned>Governor </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>Legislature </person_mentioned>of the State if
the fees are more than the law allows—</p>

<p>I cannot say that the decissions of the <person_mentioned>Alcalde </person_mentioned>as a <person_mentioned>Judge </person_mentioned>are
just or unjust. I have made it a fixed rule to keep intirely clear of
that office I mean the<location_mentioned> Judicial Office</location_mentioned>, and not even to give an opinion
when asked, unless it is so far as to translate a law. I have however
observed that the <person_mentioned>Alcalde </person_mentioned>is very particular to call in <person_mentioned>arbitrators </person_mentioned>in
all cases chosen by the <person_mentioned>parties</person_mentioned>, and every case is decided by arbitra<barker_pb n="189"/>
tion, if injustice is done, the <person_mentioned>arbitrators </person_mentioned>and not the <person_mentioned>Alcalde </person_mentioned>are to
blame— The <person_mentioned>party </person_mentioned>who looses a suit will always make a clamor,
it is a matter of course in all [countries], and more so in this than
in any other and for the single reason that every body believes that
the people here can be operated upon and gulled by clamorous <person_mentioned>men</person_mentioned>—
As regards the personalities that have existed in this place between
a few <person_mentioned>individuals</person_mentioned>, there has been too much of it, and some of our
best <person_mentioned>men </person_mentioned>have displayed a childish pettishness and suffered 
themselves to be enraged at trifles and at low bred and unprincipled <person_mentioned>men</person_mentioned>,
when they ought in fact to have paid no attention to them. This is
an infirmity of human nature. It is not every man who can 
command his temper at all times and especially when he is abused and
slandered by others. As a general rule which never ought to be
departed from, a <person_mentioned>person in office</person_mentioned> should never, at no time, act 
officially while under the influence of irritation or passion—he ought to
execute the law calmly and firmly, but not pationately—and he
should do his duty totally regardless of clamor or abuse— My own
temper is hasty to a fault and violent when excited and I therefore
laid down the above rule for my own Govt when I first began the
<location_mentioned>colony</location_mentioned>. I have violated it in some instances and have sometimes
suffered my temper [to rise] at the unjust abuse and 
misrepresentation that has been heaped upon me. I always regretted it
afterwards, for a man in a passion most generally says or does things
that he ought not to have said or done. My fits of irritation 
however have been but momentary. Reason and the Public good told
me that I must bear abuse and clamor and do my duty regardless
of what was said, and I have done so, tho the best personal friends I
have in the <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>have blamed and censured me for not taking up
the cudgels and adopting harsh measures. It is truly fortunate for
this <location_mentioned>colony </location_mentioned>that I had sufficient reflection, not [to] be influenced by
the inflamitory advise of my <person_mentioned>friends</person_mentioned>, nor by my own irritable
temper, to an extent that would have caused me to adopt violent
measures, for I had legal power from the Govt to do a great deal—
my authority up to the time the constitution was published was very
great, and I am now convinced that the rule which I laid down from
the beginning to controul my own temper and to bear all things
patiently as a dray horse [has] saved the colony from total ruin—
There is however reason in all things, and the <person_mentioned>people </person_mentioned>of this <location_mentioned>colony</location_mentioned>
must not expect to find many men who will bear abuse for the sake
of public good as I have done, and they should be more prudent
and cautious and judicious in their complaints and clamors than
they have heretofore been, for otherwise they will distroy 
themselves— Nothing is more necessary and beneficial to the well being
of a community than confidence in the public <person_mentioned>authorities</person_mentioned>, and noth-<barker_pb n="190"/>
ing more distructive than unjust and illfounded abuse and jealousy
of them—</p>

<p>As regards the <person_mentioned>lawyers </person_mentioned>who you say in your letter are causing all
the disturbance in the <location_mentioned>country</location_mentioned>, I believe they are an evil and a great
one but they are patronized and encouraged and paid, by the people.
A <person_mentioned>distiller </person_mentioned>of ardent spirit throws into the world a drug that entails
disgrace and ruin and misery on <person_mentioned>thousands of innocent and helpless
women and children</person_mentioned>, and sinks many a worthy man from the highest
to the most infamous grade of society— Is the <person_mentioned>distiller</person_mentioned>, or are those
who support him most to blame ?</p>

<p>The truth is that the evil lays in the <person_mentioned>people </person_mentioned>[themselves]   It is a
part of the national character of <person_mentioned>Americans </person_mentioned>to be contentious and
litigious, and I do believe that a <person_mentioned>lawyer </person_mentioned>would fatten on 100 
<person_mentioned>Americans</person_mentioned>, when he would starve on 10,000 of any other people on earth.
If you wish to correct this evil therefore go to the foundation and
cut it up by the roots.   Let every man settle his differences by an
arbitration of his <person_mentioned>neighbors</person_mentioned>, or if he goes to law let him attend to
his own business and not employ a <person_mentioned>lawyer</person_mentioned>.   I know of no other way
of correcting the evil for if the <person_mentioned>Alcalde </person_mentioned>was to silence all the <person_mentioned>lawyers</person_mentioned>
and suffer none to appear before him, the people would immediately
cry out despotism and oppression and say it was a hard case that a
man could not employ an <person_mentioned>agent </person_mentioned>to attend to his business for him, and
a talking <person_mentioned>lawyer </person_mentioned>would go about bawling oppression, that he was not
allowed to exercise his profession and that the <person_mentioned>Alcalde </person_mentioned>had taken
his bread from him and his poor <person_mentioned>family </person_mentioned>(if he had one) etc. etc.
And the <person_mentioned>people </person_mentioned>would no doubt take sides with the <person_mentioned>lawyer </person_mentioned>and curse
the <person_mentioned>Alcalde </person_mentioned>much more for silencing the <person_mentioned>lawyers </person_mentioned>than they now do
for not silencing them—   An honest and conscientious <person_mentioned>lawyer </person_mentioned>is a
valuable member of society-—   there is none more so, but a hot headed
fractious [abusi]ng and contentious <person_mentioned>lawyer </person_mentioned>is a curse on any 
<location_mentioned>community</location_mentioned>, and ought to be discountenanced but I really cannot see any
other effectual remidy than the one I have pointed out to correct
this evil—  it must be corrected by settling disputes by means of 
arbitration in each <location_mentioned>neighborhood</location_mentioned>, and by never employing a <person_mentioned>lawyer </person_mentioned>in
any case-</p>

<p>As regards the prejudice that appears to exist against this place,
I must say that it is both unjust and impolitic—   There has been
much contention here it is true, but who caused it?   <person_mentioned>Drunkards </person_mentioned>and
<person_mentioned>vagabonds </person_mentioned>and unprincipled <person_mentioned>men</person_mentioned>, known and acknowledged to be
such by every body—make a difficulty and the people abuse the
<person_mentioned>Alcalde </person_mentioned>and the place for suffering so much disorder   The <person_mentioned>Alcalde</person_mentioned>
attempts to correct the evil by calling these outrageous <person_mentioned>men </person_mentioned>to an
account, and executing the law on them and the people take sides
with the <person_mentioned>vagabonds </person_mentioned>and abuse the <person_mentioned>Alcalde </person_mentioned>and the good part of the
<person_mentioned>citizens </person_mentioned>here because they had attempted to controul the bad ones</p>—<barker_pb n="191"/>

<p>One day the people curse the <person_mentioned>Alcalde </person_mentioned>for not doing a thing, and
the next they curse him for doing it— I say that this prejudice is
impolitic as well as unjust because it is the interest of each man
who lives in this <location_mentioned>colony </location_mentioned>or in this <location_mentioned>section of the country</location_mentioned> to encourage the improvement and advancement of this <location_mentioned>town</location_mentioned>—The day will come
when a selection must be made for the <location_mentioned>seat of Govt of Texas</location_mentioned>—the
people of his <location_mentioned>jurisdiction </location_mentioned>should keep that object in view and by
pushing forward this place pave the way to its location here— If
we can get decent <location_mentioned>public buildings</location_mentioned> and an <location_mentioned>academy </location_mentioned>etc under way
and have the place otherwise improved so as to afford comfortable
accomodations, this place stands a better chance to be the <location_mentioned>seat of
Govt</location_mentioned> than any other point in <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>. I am of opinion that it must
ultimately be on the <location_mentioned>Brazos river</location_mentioned>, but if it is taken to any thing like
the <location_mentioned>center of territory</location_mentioned> it will be somewhere about the <location_mentioned>St. Antonio
road</location_mentioned> or above it— It cannot be long before there must be a <location_mentioned>supreme
Court</location_mentioned> established for <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>and it ought to sit at this town, these
are important considerations, and every one who does or says 
anything to retard the advance of this place is actually doing an injury
to himself that is with the exception of those who live near the <location_mentioned>St.
Antonio road</location_mentioned>, for it is their interest to sink this place and raise up
a town there for the future <location_mentioned>seat of Govt </location_mentioned>but the <person_mentioned>people of the <location_mentioned>Coast</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>would surely rather it should be here, than any <location_mentioned>higher up the river</location_mentioned>— I calculated the chances for this place to be the future seat of Govt
of <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>many years ago and I was then of the opinion that the
<person_mentioned>people </person_mentioned>of this <location_mentioned>Colony </location_mentioned>could make it the <location_mentioned>seat of Govt</location_mentioned> if they took the right course and I am of the same opinion still—</p>

<p>The <location_mentioned>Academy </location_mentioned>is a very important matter and I hope you will aid
us some from that <location_mentioned>quarter </location_mentioned>of the country— If we can get it under
way I have no doubt the Govt will aid us— I will devote a great
deal to this object if it goes on, for independent of the good that
will result to the <person_mentioned>children of the <location_mentioned>Colony</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>, it will give a favourable
character to it <location_mentioned>abroad</location_mentioned>.</p>

<p>My whole thoughts and ambition and desires have been devoted
to the advancement of this <location_mentioned>colony </location_mentioned>and the happiness of its <location_mentioned>citizens</location_mentioned> I have no other wish—no other interest, and I therefore cannot but
observe with deep regret any thing like a want of union or of 
confidence in the people—I have a great desire to visit the <location_mentioned>United
States</location_mentioned> and to spend a year or 18 months there, but I really have
some fears that things will go into confusion My Dr Sir the people
must rely with more confidence on the men chosen by themselves
to take charge of their public matters and they must close their ears
against the idle rumors and clamors of those who are bawling out
oppression in order to screen themselves by throwing obliquy on
the <person_mentioned>authorities </person_mentioned>who attempt to control them</p><barker_pb n="192"/>

<p>As soon as the <person_mentioned>Commissioner </person_mentioned>arrives the <person_mentioned>drunkards </person_mentioned>will raise the
hue and cry against me, for I shall in future reject every man who
is not of the class required by law, and there are several now in the
<location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>who will be rejected, and the more clamor is made about it
the more rigid I shall be—In the beginning of the settlement I was
not so particular as I shall be in future.</p>

<p>The principal part of the tax that is to be raised will be paid by
<person_mentioned>land and slave holders</person_mentioned>—my tax will be higher in proportion to my
disposable means than any five men's in the <location_mentioned>colony</location_mentioned></p>.

<p>You are at full liberty to show all I have said to who you please—
the complaints against the <person_mentioned>Ayto </person_mentioned>are groundless and unjust and ought
to be stoped for no good and much evil will grow out of them
Your friend</p>

<p><person_mentioned>Stephen F. Austin</person_mentioned>    [Rubric]</p>

<p>[To Josiah H. Bell]</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
