
<TEI.2 id="APB4435">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>09-14-1832</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 859-865</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Stephen F Austin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Martin</document_recipient>
<document_title>Stephen F Austin to Martin, 09-14-1832</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>San Felipe de Austin, Texas</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Austin to -—¦----Martin. September 14, 1832.    Statement of settlement with heirs of J. H. Hawkins.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes>In 1859 William B. Victor printed in Cincinnati a Memorial to the Legislature of
Texas, a pamphlet of 35 pages. Victor had married the last surviving heir of Joseph H.
Hawkins, and prayed the Legislature of Texas to repay the advances which he believed
Hawkins had made to Austin over and above the original advances to establish the first
settlers in 1822. He based his claim on letters of Nathaniel Cox, saying that Hawkins's
advances and expenditures totaled some $30,000. Austin pointed out that much of this
money was lost in commercial speculations having no connection with the partnership
between himself and Hawkins. Hawkins estimated his expenditures directly and 
indirectly at $7,000. See Hawkins to Austin, May 31, 1822, and to Mrs. Austin, Mar. 29,
1823. See also Nathaniel Cox to Austin, Mar. 20, June 3, and Aug. 6, 1824. On Apr. 2,
3833, Austin wrote Cox expressing gratification at Cox's approval of his settlement with
the Hawking heirs</barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 859-865</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>10-10-2010</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>


<text id="APB4435T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Austin to -—¦----Martin. September 14, 1832.    Statement of settlement with heirs of J. H. Hawkins.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p>Statement presented to ------ Martin, relative to the settlement of the business between
<person_mentioned>S. F. Austin</person_mentioned> and the <person_mentioned>late J. H. Hawkins</person_mentioned></p>

<p>In <date_mentioned n="11-xx-1821">Novr. 1821</date_mentioned> a contract was made between <person_mentioned>S. F. Austin</person_mentioned> and <person_mentioned>J. H.
Hawkins</person_mentioned>, relative to settling the <location_mentioned>colony </location_mentioned>originally contracted to be
settled by <person_mentioned>Moses Austin</person_mentioned>, the <person_mentioned>father of the said Stephen F. Austin</person_mentioned>.</p>

<p>A <person_mentioned>partnership </person_mentioned>was also formed between the said <person_mentioned>S. F. Austin</person_mentioned> and
the said <person_mentioned>Hawkins</person_mentioned> for certain purposes: this <person_mentioned>partnership </person_mentioned>expired by
the death of <person_mentioned>Hawkins </person_mentioned>in <date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1823">1823</date_mentioned>.</p>

<p>At the time of forming that contract, it was supposed that 
something could be realized out of the <person_mentioned>settlers</person_mentioned>; and an arrangement was
made for them to pay 12 1/2 cents pr acre for the <location_mentioned>land </location_mentioned>they received,
<person_mentioned>Austin </person_mentioned>to be at all the expense. This arrangement was totally 
destroyed by the interference of the <person_mentioned>Govr. of <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>in <date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1824">1824</date_mentioned></person_mentioned>. A large
sum was lost by <person_mentioned>Austin </person_mentioned>for surveys which were made up to that time,
and meanderings of the <location_mentioned>river</location_mentioned>.</p>

<p>In <date_mentioned n="05-xx-1824">May 1824</date_mentioned> the <person_mentioned>Govr. of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> interfered with the said first 
arrangement, and established a fee-bill. None of these fees belonged
to <person_mentioned>Austin</person_mentioned>; and he had no right to use any of them. One hundred
and twenty seven dollars, 50 cents, were allowed to the <person_mentioned>Commissioner</person_mentioned>,
including his milage <location_mentioned>from Bexar to the colony</location_mentioned>; 30 dollars to the
<person_mentioned>Govt</person_mentioned>.; and 8 dollars for the Title. The <person_mentioned>Commissioner </person_mentioned>relinquished
to <person_mentioned>Austin </person_mentioned>the third of his fees</p>.

<p><person_mentioned>Austin </person_mentioned>was appointed by the <person_mentioned>Govt</person_mentioned>, to administer the local 
government of the <location_mentioned>colony </location_mentioned>in all its branches, civil, judicial, and military,
without any salary. He also had to attend in person to all the 
land business.    Besides this he kept an open <location_mentioned>house </location_mentioned>and was compelled to<barker_pb n="860"/>
do so: his <location_mentioned>house </location_mentioned>was always full, for the first six years, as is well
known to those who were here then. It is also well known, that he
had constant visits from the <person_mentioned>Tankaway</person_mentioned>, <person_mentioned>Lipan</person_mentioned>, <person_mentioned>Beedi</person_mentioned>, and other
<person_mentioned>Indians</person_mentioned>; and the situation of things required him to make them large
presents.</p>

<p>These expenses were not all: he paid for expresses, furnished 
provisions, and amunition, and many other things for campaigns against
the <person_mentioned>Indians</person_mentioned>. He was compelled to keep an <location_mentioned>office</location_mentioned>, and a <person_mentioned>Secretary</person_mentioned>,
and <person_mentioned>Clerks</person_mentioned>, acquainted with the Spanish and English languages—It
will be remembered that, at that time, every thing was dear—Cows
at from $20 to $30 each; pork from $9 to $10; beeves from $25 to $80
a head; corn from one to two dollars the bushel; etc. The expenses
of his <location_mentioned>household </location_mentioned>were not less than $2000 a year: his <location_mentioned>office </location_mentioned>including
the <person_mentioned>Secretary</person_mentioned>'s salary, stationery, etc $1500. a year: presents to
<person_mentioned>Indians </person_mentioned>$500 a year. To all this is to be added a variety of other
expenses, such as <person_mentioned>expresses</person_mentioned>, <person_mentioned>guards</person_mentioned>, and supplies for <person_mentioned>Indian </person_mentioned>
expeditions. Also he had a heavy surveying debt to pay, as above stated.
Besides these expenses, there are many others which can not be
mentioned.</p>

<p>A large amount of the fees never has been collected, and never will
be. Also a considerable amount was lost that was received in herdes,
which died or were stolen by the <person_mentioned>Indians</person_mentioned>. Twelve head were stolen
at one time, ten of them mules, at <location_mentioned><person_mentioned>Buckner</person_mentioned>'s old place on the Colorado.</location_mentioned></p>

<p>But even supposing that the fees had all been collected and in
money: the whole amount of the <person_mentioned>Commissioner</person_mentioned>'s fees on<person_mentioned> 300 families</person_mentioned>
at $127.50, is $38,250—of this one third was relinquished by the
<person_mentioned>Commr </person_mentioned>to <person_mentioned>Austin</person_mentioned>, which is $12,750 which would not have half paid
the expenses of the <person_mentioned>local govt</person_mentioned>, and other expenses of the <location_mentioned>colony </location_mentioned><date_mentioned n="1823-1828">from
1823 up to 1828</date_mentioned>, the time when the <person_mentioned>Ayuntamto </person_mentioned>was established; to say
nothing of a compensation for<person_mentioned> Austin</person_mentioned>'s services, and a deduction of
more than one half for property payments at an excessive value.</p>

<p>It will be remembered that <person_mentioned>Austin </person_mentioned>received no salary from the
<person_mentioned>Govt</person_mentioned>., nor any allowance whatever for the local government of the
<location_mentioned>colony</location_mentioned>, that all the labor, expense, danger, and responsability rested
on him alone:—all the vexations, labyrinths of the <location_mentioned>colony</location_mentioned>—matters
with the <person_mentioned>government</person_mentioned>, and with the <person_mentioned>settlers</person_mentioned>, who were several times
in a state of rebellion against him, and always complaining and
abusing him, because they had anything to pay: he had to bear all
this patiently, as the salvation of the <location_mentioned>colony </location_mentioned>required it. The facts
as to advances made by <person_mentioned>Hawkins </person_mentioned>are as follows:</p>

<p>The Schooner Lively, a small vessel of about 30 Tons, was 
purchased for $600 in <date_mentioned n="12-xx-1821">Novr. 1821</date_mentioned>: of this sum <person_mentioned>Austin </person_mentioned>furnished $400,
which he borrowed from <person_mentioned>Lovelace </person_mentioned>and now owes, with the interest—
The Lively brought out 17 or 18 <person_mentioned>men</person_mentioned>, <person_mentioned>emigrants</person_mentioned>, and provisions<barker_pb n="861"/>
and tools. I do not know the whole amount of her outfit; but it
is very evident that it could not have been much. The Lively landed
the <person_mentioned>emigrants </person_mentioned><location_mentioned>at the mouth of the Brazos</location_mentioned>, and was lost on 
<location_mentioned>Galveston Island</location_mentioned>. <person_mentioned>William Little</person_mentioned> had the charge of the <person_mentioned>men </person_mentioned>who came
in the Lively: I never saw any of them until after my return from
<location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned>in <date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1823">1823</date_mentioned>, owing to their having landed in the <location_mentioned>Brazos </location_mentioned>instead
of the <location_mentioned>Colorado</location_mentioned>, to the mouth of which latter river I went to look
for them, agreeably to appointment in <date_mentioned n="12-xx-1821">Decr, </date_mentioned><date_mentioned n="01-xx-1821">and Jany. of 1821 and
1822</date_mentioned>; and not finding them I proceeded to <location_mentioned>Bexar </location_mentioned>and thence to
<location_mentioned>Mexico</location_mentioned>. The <person_mentioned>men </person_mentioned>who came in the Lively became discouraged, and
all returned to the<location_mentioned> U. S.</location_mentioned> except two or three.</p>

<p>For a part of the expences to <location_mentioned>Mexico</location_mentioned>, I drew on <person_mentioned>Hawkins</person_mentioned>; for
I had between 300 and 400 dollars of my own money which I brought
with me from<location_mentioned> New Orleans</location_mentioned> in doubloons. I lost my memorandum
and account book at <location_mentioned>Monterey</location_mentioned>, on my return from <location_mentioned>Mexico</location_mentioned>, and
cannot state what was the amount of my drafts on <person_mentioned>Hawkins</person_mentioned>; but
they were not for a large sum:—I lived very economically, and
even endured privations to save expense. I raised $100 in <location_mentioned>Mexico</location_mentioned>
by the sale of my watch</p>.

<p>When I started for <location_mentioned>Mexico</location_mentioned>, I sent into <person_mentioned>Hawkins </person_mentioned>my <person_mentioned>negro man
Richmond</person_mentioned>, a stout healthy <person_mentioned>negro</person_mentioned>, about 28 years of age: he was
worth $800.</p>

<p>On a fair statement of this whole matter, what benefits or aid,
have I derived, in the settlement of this <location_mentioned>colony</location_mentioned>, from <person_mentioned>Hawkins</person_mentioned>?</p>

<p>He aided in fitting out the Lively: he furnished the amount of my
drafts for the expenses to <location_mentioned>Mexico</location_mentioned>: he could not have been of much
aid in sending out <person_mentioned>emigrants</person_mentioned>, for he died before there was much
emigration. The money which he spent for the goods that 
<person_mentioned>Littlebury Hawkins</person_mentioned> brought out, and a vast sum in the <person_mentioned>negro </person_mentioned>speculation
of which <person_mentioned>John Botts</person_mentioned> had the management, had nothing to do with
the <location_mentioned>colony</location_mentioned>; and I was in no manner concerned in those speculations,
nor ever had any control over them. Both these <person_mentioned>persons </person_mentioned>arrived
after I departed for <location_mentioned>Mexico</location_mentioned>, and left before I returned.—Neither
am I accountable for an enormous interest account which, I am told,
<person_mentioned>Hawkins </person_mentioned>paid in <location_mentioned>New Orleans</location_mentioned>, to raise money for the expeditions
of <person_mentioned>Littlebury Hawkins</person_mentioned>, and <person_mentioned>John Botts</person_mentioned>.</p>

<p>In the contract with <person_mentioned>Hawkins </person_mentioned>I acknowledge to have received
four thousand dollars, but the truth is I had not then received
that amount, and never have received it up to this time. For, as
I before observed, all that ever was spent for the benefit of the
<location_mentioned>Colony</location_mentioned>, that I have any knowledge of, was the outfit of the Lively,
and the amount of my drafts for the <location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned>trip: and out of that
the $400 dollars I borrowed from <person_mentioned>Lovelace</person_mentioned>, and over $300 which<barker_pb n="862"/>
I had of my own money, and the value of my <person_mentioned>negro Richmond</person_mentioned>, and
$100 for my watch, making about $1600 ought to be deducted.</p>

<p>As I before observed, none of the fees that were collected in the
<location_mentioned>first colony</location_mentioned>, belonged to me of right; a part of them were given
to me; but necessity compelled me to use much more of them than
the portion thus relinquished:—and I thus may yet become 
entangled in an endless and ruinous labyrinth. Up to this time
<person_mentioned>Hawkins </person_mentioned>is entirely clear of all responsibility as to those fees thus
used by me. I have always been very cautious not to implicate
any part of his landed interest in any way. I have been a true
and<person_mentioned> paternal guardian</person_mentioned> of the interests of his <person_mentioned>heirs in this <location_mentioned>country</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>,
and I have kept his part of the <location_mentioned>land </location_mentioned>entirely clear. I have not
even sold any more of it, than was absolutely necessary to give
value to the balance, and to comply with the law by having the
land settled; and this has subjected me to the abuse and slander
of <person_mentioned>persons </person_mentioned>who wished to get places near <location_mentioned>Brazoria</location_mentioned>, and who have
spared no pains to try and prejudice public opinion against me.
I have, in fact, from the beginning of the <location_mentioned>Colony </location_mentioned>struggled alone
in this <location_mentioned>wilderness</location_mentioned>, undergoing all sorts of privations, and my life
often embittered by the unjust clamors, slanders, and abuse which
I have been compelled by circumstances to bear. No pecuniary
remuneration could, or ever can, recompense me for the last ten
years.</p>

<p>If the fees, received from the <person_mentioned>Settlers in the <location_mentioned>first Colony</</location_mentioned>person_mentioned>, as
above stated, are now to be considered as <person_mentioned>partnership </person_mentioned>property,
<person_mentioned>Hawkins </person_mentioned>must also become liable for all the responsibilities which
I am, or may ever be, liable to for having used more of those
fees than I had a right to. Also a fair statement must be made
of all the expenses of the local govt, of the <location_mentioned>colony</location_mentioned>, of the losses
by bad debts, robbery of <person_mentioned>Indians</person_mentioned>, <location_mentioned>office </location_mentioned>expenses, losses by 
surveying, and a yearly compensation to <person_mentioned>Austin </person_mentioned>for his services. The
gross amount of all this must be made up: then the amount of the
fees which <person_mentioned>Austin </person_mentioned>was entitled to receive by the relinquishment
of the <person_mentioned>Commissioner</person_mentioned>, must be made out, and deducted from the
gross amount of the expenses. It will then be found that a large
balance of many thousands will be due to pay those expenses, and
the balance will bo a charge against the <location_mentioned>partnership land</location_mentioned>, and
would consume a large part of it.</p>

<p>But this is not all. <person_mentioned>Hawkins </person_mentioned>would also have to be liable, in
union with <person_mentioned>Austin</person_mentioned>, for all the responsabilities that may arise, owing
to <person_mentioned>Austin</person_mentioned>'s having used more of the fees than the amount relinquished
to him by the <person_mentioned>Commissioner</person_mentioned>. In short, it would place <person_mentioned>Hawkins'
estate</person_mentioned> in the situation in which I am now placed; that is liable to
be harrassed as long as I live, and involved in an endless labyrinth
of difficulties; and besides all this, there are matters connected with<barker_pb n="863"/>
this business which are in the highest degree confidential and cannot
be explained without a breach of faith.</p>

<p>I have probably done nearly as much to benefit <person_mentioned>individuals </person_mentioned>as
ever was done by any one man in <location_mentioned>America </location_mentioned>who acted in the humble
sphere of an unpatronised, unprotected, and private <person_mentioned>person</person_mentioned>. I have
been instrumental in laying a <location_mentioned>broad foundation for the fortunes of
many thousands</location_mentioned>. The enterprise has succeeded, and begins to 
attract notice; but no one knows, or seems to care, or to ask, how, or
by what means, or through whose instrumentality it has been brought
about. The only idea most <person_mentioned>persons </person_mentioned>seem to connect with the matter
is, that of a mammoth speculation; and they say that <person_mentioned>Austin</person_mentioned>, in
doing so much for so many, must have done a great deal for 
himself. Thus the most erroneous impressions, and the most unjust
rumors, are set afloat. Ingratitude, jealousy, and suspicions are
always active and vociferous.</p>

<p>What benefit has <person_mentioned>Austin </person_mentioned>received from the fees of the <location_mentioned>first colony</location_mentioned> ?
There are <location_mentioned>six leagues and a half, and two labors, of land </location_mentioned>which were
acquired by <person_mentioned>purchases </person_mentioned>from the <person_mentioned>settlers </person_mentioned>out of these fees, and deeded
to my<person_mentioned> brother J. E. B. Austin</person_mentioned> because there was no <person_mentioned>judicial officer</person_mentioned>
in the <location_mentioned>colony </location_mentioned>but me, before whom the deed could be acknowledged.
The titles for a part of this are doubtful. I have also used a part
of those fees to pay some of my old debts, but I have also used a
large amount of the proceeds of my last contracts that <person_mentioned>Hawkins </person_mentioned>had
nothing to do with, to satisfy the debts that were properly 
changeable to the <location_mentioned>first colony</location_mentioned>: and consequently if the fees of the <location_mentioned>first
colony</location_mentioned> are to go with the <person_mentioned>partnership </person_mentioned>accounts, all I have paid out
of my last contracts on account of the <location_mentioned>first colony</location_mentioned>, must be charged
to that <location_mentioned>colony</location_mentioned>.</p>

<p>What benefit will <person_mentioned>Hawkins' estate</person_mentioned> receive for the advances he
made in fitting out the Lively, and in paying my drafts for the
<location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned>trip, which was all he did advance that was of use to the
enterprise ? The <person_mentioned>estate </person_mentioned>gets the <location_mentioned>half of 22 1/2 leagues of land</location_mentioned>. I get
the other half, and I have done all the labor. In fact I have done
every thing alone and without receiving aid from the personal 
services, or the capital, of <person_mentioned>Hawkins </person_mentioned>to the extent that was originally
contemplated.</p>

<p>To recapitulate.</p>

<p>The first arrangement with the <person_mentioned>settlers</person_mentioned>, as to fees, was distroyed
by the interference of the <person_mentioned>Govt of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>.</person_mentioned> A new arrangement was
made by the Govt as to the fees, which allowed Austin to receive
none of them. The <person_mentioned>Commissioner </person_mentioned>relinquished a part of them to
<person_mentioned>Austin</person_mentioned>. The part thus relinquished has been used by <person_mentioned>Austin </person_mentioned>for
the joint benefit of the <person_mentioned>partnership</person_mentioned>; for by that means he has main-<barker_pb n="864"/>
tained the <location_mentioned>colony </location_mentioned>without creating any charge against the 
<location_mentioned>partnership lands </location_mentioned>which are now clear.</p>

<p><person_mentioned>Austin </person_mentioned>has used more of those fees than were so relinquished;
and by so doing he is liable to be harrassed; and if <person_mentioned>Hawkins </person_mentioned>claims
a part of those fees, he will have to bear his share of that liability:
as also to bear an equal share of all the expenses of the <location_mentioned>colony</location_mentioned>, and
to pay <person_mentioned>Austin </person_mentioned>for his services. This can not be done without taking
<location_mentioned>a part of the premium land</location_mentioned>.</p>

<p><person_mentioned>Austin </person_mentioned>never did receive $4000 for the use of the <location_mentioned>colony </location_mentioned>from
<person_mentioned>Hawkins</person_mentioned>; and he did furnish about $1600 which, on a rigid 
settlement, <person_mentioned>Hawkins </person_mentioned>would be accountable for. <person_mentioned>Austin </person_mentioned>is not liable for
the money spent in the expeditions of <person_mentioned>Littleberry Hawkins</person_mentioned> and <person_mentioned>John
Botts</person_mentioned>; nor for the interest paid by <person_mentioned>Hawkins</person_mentioned>.</p>

<p>It would be the work of many years, and of endless expense, to
bring this matter to a judicial or litigated settlement; and I am
confident that such a settlement, in any court of justice, would in
volve <location_mentioned>more than one half the premium land </location_mentioned>to square the accounts
of the <location_mentioned>colony </location_mentioned>if they were justly, stated; besides the delay and
expense.</p>

<p>I therefore think that in offering to divide the <location_mentioned>premium land,
twenty two leagues and a half, and three labors</location_mentioned>, deducting the
expenses of surveying it, I offer at least one half more than could
be recovered in any <location_mentioned>court of justice.</location_mentioned> The original expenses of 
surveying the premium land are a just charge against it: they were
paid by me in <date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1824">1824 </date_mentioned>and <date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1825">1825</date_mentioned>. More than this I am unwilling to do;
and in doing this I consider that I am relinquishing a part of what
justly belongs to me; for if a fair allowance were made to me, I
should be entitled to a considerable portion of <person_mentioned>Hawkins</person_mentioned>' part of the
<location_mentioned>premium land</location_mentioned>. The truth is, that I could have done all that I have
done, had I never known <person_mentioned>Hawkins</person_mentioned>, nor received one cent, nor aid,
from any <location_mentioned>quarter </location_mentioned>beyond my own resources.</p>

<p>Difficulties present themselves as to the manner of making this
settlement. Ever since <date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1824">early in 1824</date_mentioned> I have repeatedly requested,
and urged often and often, that an <person_mentioned>Agent </person_mentioned>might be sent out to settle
this business. The delay has not been of my causing, or of my 
seeking. Now after so long a period <person_mentioned>Mr. Martin</person_mentioned> is sent with very 
imperfect powers. <person_mentioned>George </person_mentioned>is not represented at all. The original 
contract between me and <person_mentioned>Hawkins </person_mentioned>is not produced: I never had a copy
of it:—there was but one made out and that <person_mentioned>J. H. Hawkins</person_mentioned> retained.
<person_mentioned>Edmund Hawkins</person_mentioned>, who is here present, is not competent to settle
his own share of the business, for by the laws of this <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>he is
a <person_mentioned>minor </person_mentioned>until he is twenty five years of age, and is therefore 
incompetent to bind himself, or any one else. He can not legally hold the
<location_mentioned>land </location_mentioned>after it is divided: he will have to appoint a <person_mentioned>guardian </person_mentioned>in the<barker_pb n="865"/>
manner prescribed by law, and this <person_mentioned>guardian </person_mentioned>will have to attend
to this part of the business.</p>

<p>I wish to make a final settlement of this matter, and will do every
thing to effect that object which will be legal and finally binding
on all <person_mentioned>parties</person_mentioned>.</p>

<p>I make this statement to correct the erroneous impressions which
the <person_mentioned>parties </person_mentioned>interested in this Business appear to have received from
common rumor; and to show that, on my part, every thing has been
done which circumstances would admit to protect the interests of
<person_mentioned>Hawkins' estate</person_mentioned>. Also it ought to be remembered that I requested
a settlement of this business since soon after <person_mentioned>Hawkins</person_mentioned>' death, and
that I could long since have brought it to a settlement by a judicial
process. The delay has been very injurious and very harrassing to
me, but it has been beneficial to the <person_mentioned>estate</person_mentioned>.</p>

<p>There is another erroneous idea relative to the business of 
colonization in <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>. Many believe that actual <location_mentioned>grants </location_mentioned>are made by the
<person_mentioned>Govt</person_mentioned>, of <location_mentioned>large tracts of land, or sections of country</location_mentioned>, to individuals
who are denominated in the Law <person_mentioned>Empresarios</person_mentioned>; and that these 
<person_mentioned>individuals </person_mentioned>can sell this land. This is all a mistake. It is also wrong
to call them <location_mentioned>grants</location_mentioned>: they are nothing more than Trusts by which the
<person_mentioned>contractor </person_mentioned>or " <person_mentioned>empresario </person_mentioned>", is constituted the <person_mentioned>agent of the Govt</person_mentioned>, to
settle a certain number of <person_mentioned>families </person_mentioned>of a particular description, in
certain designated limits, within a limited time. If he comply with
this contract, he will then, and not before, be entitled to receive a
certain quantity of land as a <location_mentioned>grant</location_mentioned>, which is called <location_mentioned>premium land</location_mentioned>,
for which a special title is issued to him by the <person_mentioned>government 
commissioner</person_mentioned>. The <person_mentioned>settlers </person_mentioned>receive their titles direct from the <person_mentioned>Govt</person_mentioned>,
through a <person_mentioned>commissioner</person_mentioned>, and not from the <person_mentioned>empresario</person_mentioned>. In the
colonization law of <date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1825">1825</date_mentioned>, the contracts made between the 
"<person_mentioned>empresario </person_mentioned>" and the <person_mentioned>settlers </person_mentioned>are guaranteed as valid, if not contrary to
that and other laws; but in the colonization law of the <date_mentioned n="01-04-1823">4th of Jany.
1823</date_mentioned>, under which my <location_mentioned>first colony</location_mentioned> was settled, there was no such
guarantee.</p>

<p><location_mentioned>San Felipe de Austin</location_mentioned> <date_mentioned n="09-14-1832">September 14 1832</date_mentioned></p>

<p><person_mentioned>Stephen F. Austin </person_mentioned>  [Rubric]</p>


</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
